is called to order. We welcome
all those who have joined us in
the council chambers this
evening and those who are, uh,
joining us virtually, uh, I
will just tell you in advance
this is going to be a lengthy
meeting and we thank you in
advance for your patience as we
do the city's business. We will
begin with an invocation and a
national anthem, which will be
in lieu of uh the pledge this
evening due to Music Month, our
invocation, oh, first let me.
Let me establish a quorum
council member Bill Kling
council member Little, and the
chair are here and we do have a
quorum. The invocation will be
offered by Huntsville, Alabama
Public safety chaplain,
chaplain Doctor Laurie McCauley
followed by the national anthem
which will be performed by
Huntsville City Schools and
Maitland Conservatory student
Emili Drummond, so please stand
for the invocation and the
national anthem. Our Father, we
thank you right now for the
favor of life. Ephesians 4:3
teaches us, make every effort
to keep the unity of the spirit
through the bond of peace. As
we come together, Father, let
them all. Remember the mission
and the people before any pride
Father bless all of our leaders
from Washington to here cover
them, Father, in only the way
you can. And as we would end,
we'd say, let the words of my
mouth and the meditation of my
heart, be sight, and I
challenge everyone to think,
where will you never be in his
sight, so watch your words.
Amen. Thank you. OK Oh her. you
see. The dog. Lila. what so
proud. we the It's last. ing
who's brought stripes and
bright stars. us. or the. we
who are so gas. stream. ing The
interesting. height and that
our flesh. was still there. Oh
Does that star space. gold.
What Or the P Um Thank you,
Emili, thank you, Chaplain
McCauley, let the record show
that Mr. Meredith and Ms.
Watkins have joined us on the
dais. Council members, we have
a couple of changes to the
agenda. One is that since we
had a different performer
tonight. We will change that
will impact 5A, the mayor's
special recognition, which will
reflect recognition of Emili
Drummond. Um, the other change
is that uh sponsor has
requested 10E be postponed to
the October 8th meeting, and we
will address that when we get
to that item. Are there any
other changes to the agenda. Is
there a motion to approve the
agenda with those changes. Move
to approve motion for Mr.
Little second from the chair.
All in favor, please indicate
you opposed. The motion carries
Council members, you have, uh,
the minutes of previous
meetings in front of you. 4A is
the minutes of the regular
meeting of the city council
held on September 10, 2026. Are
there any changes to be made?
Hearing none, those minutes
will be accepted 4B is the
minutes of the work session of
the city council held on
September 18, 2026. Are there
any changes or additions to be
made. Seeing none of those
minutes will also be accepted,
which brings us to 5A
recognition of Emily Drummond,
Huntsville City school student
and Maitland Conservatory
student and for her
contribution to Music Month,
Mayor Battle. Thank you, Madam
President and counsel. Emily,
if. Come on over here. Yeah. We
want to say thank you for
coming tonight and thank you
for blessing us with your
beautiful music, uh, your
beautiful rendition of the
national anthem. Thank you so
much for doing that and we have
a little certificate to present
to you to say thank you for
being part of Music Month here
in Huntsville and especially
for the, for the for our, our
council. Thank you. Thank you.
OK. Item 5B is another special
recognition by the mayor.
Presentation of a Huntsville
Police Department citizens
award. Chief Charles, if you
would come up with some of your
command staff, I think we have
an award to be presented. Yes,
sir, if Rally Johnson and
Charles Houghton are in the
audience. Come on up here,
please. Yes. Ladies and
gentlemen, it's not often that
our department gets to
recognize and have the
opportunity to recognize a
citizen who stepped in and
helped during a dangerous
situation before our officers
can even get there, but tonight
we have a privilege of
recognizing two people, one of
which is here, Mr. Houghton,
who did exactly that. On August
5th, approximately 7:30 in the
morning, our department
received or responded to a
shooting call in the 6400 block
of Greenbrier Road. Mr. Johnson
Mr. Houghton heard an argument
followed by a gunshot. They had
no idea what they were walking
into, but they chose to act. Mr
Jason, who was unarmed, stepped
in and detained the shooting
suspect. He kept him calm and
under control until the
officers arrived. At the same
time Mr. Houghton went straight
to the victim. He reckoned the
seriousness of the injury, he
applied pressure to the wound.
While Car on 911 and providing
critical information to our
responding officers and medical
personnel. He remained with the
victim until the first
responders could take over. We
never expect members of our
community to place themselves
in harm's way. But a moment of
violence and uncertainty, these
two men showed courage,
compassion, and composure.
Their rations helped our
officers quickly take custody
of the suspect and just as
importantly, help ensure that
the victim received immediate
care. What you both did that
day showed courage, compassion,
and a willingness to help
someone when it mattered the
most. That kind of response
makes a difference and not just
an emergency, but in a
community that we all share. So
on behalf of the Huntsville
Police Department, we want to
thank you for stepping forward,
for looking out for others. For
your commitment to our
community, and we're proud to
recognize you tonight.
Congratulations. Thank you.
Right here, ready. 12 12. What,
2. Thank you. Thank you. Thanks
thank you. Thank you, Mr.
Houghton for your service to
our community. 5C is a
proclamation to declare the
month of September as OBGYN
Cancer Awareness Month. Mayor
Battle is Betsy Feltner,
Fettner here. Betsy, please
come forward and bring, bring
your crew with you. Thank you
so much. Good to see you. Is
this our crew crew, OK. Tonight
we have a proclamation, uh, and
the proclamation has, whereas
gynecological cancers are among
the leading cancer killers of
women in the United States and
more than 125,000 women will be
diagnosed in more than 33,000
women will die from these
diseases this year, whereas the
Laura Crandall Brown Foundation
and they're a state of teal
initiative brings awareness to
all GYN cancers to the people
throughout the state of Alabama
and whereas a good health and
well-being of women in our
state. State and the city of
Huntsville are enhanced by the
increased awareness of GYN
cancers and their symptoms and
treatments, uh, whereas there's
also crucial that all women in
our state, in the city of
Huntsville, take an active role
in learning the symptoms and
risk factors associated with
GYN cancers and whereas we
reflect upon the memory of
those lost to this disease, the
bravery of those currently
battling those diagnoses and
the need for increased
awareness, screening, and
research so that the women of
our state might be spared from
them. In the future and
encourage all citizens to work
together to raise awareness of
GYN cancers. Now therefore, I,
Tommy Battle, mayor of the city
of Huntsville, to hereby
proclaim September 2026 is
gynologic Cancer Awareness
Month throughout the city
encourage all residents of
Huntsville to work together to
raise awareness to GYN cancers
and do commend these the
observance of all this to our
citizens. Thank you so much.
You. Thank y'all for letting us
come today. Thank you so much,
Mayor Battle. Um, there are 5
GYN cancers, only 1 has an
early detection test, and that
is the Pap smear for cervical
cancer. Um, all of the rest of
them are have very vague
symptoms. Um, they can be
things that women experience
from time to time anyway, um,
spotting, um, bloating, lower
back pain, things like that,
and so in our awareness
movement during the month of
September and, and. All months
of the year we want women to
know that if they are having
these kinds of symptoms and
they're persisting for more
than about a week or two to
please see their doctor. Um,
with me tonight, I have some
very brave survivors, some
staff from Tennessee Valley
Gynecologic Oncology, y'all are
very lucky to have them and um
a very brave caregiver who
recently lost his wife, so, um,
thank you for this proclamation
and thanks for having us you.
you. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you Mayor Battle for
recognizing some very special
people in our community. We now
have one recognition for uh on
behalf of the council 6A is a
resolution honoring the the
chapters of Omega Psi Phi
fraternity Incorporated and the
50th Alabama statewide meeting.
Is there a motion to approve
the resolution motion from from
Ms. Watkins. Second from Mr.
Meredith. All in favor, please
indicate and opposed the motion
carries. Ms. Watkins, would you
like to make that presentation?
I'm going to defer to
Councilman Meredith. He's going
to do the presentation. Thank
you. If the members of uh Omega
Psi Phi. I just wanted to make
sure I had the right rat here.
When I'm turning on me this
early. Mary Valley, you want to
join us? How you doing? Good to
see you. You want to join us?
There's one man's sorry, fine
and you sir? Good to see you.
That. Good to see you. Yes sir.
All right. I don't blame you.
I'd want to stack up on her
side too. And thank you all for
picking my side. I appreciate
that. Yeah, yeah. Whereas the
city council and the mayor of
Huntsville, Alabama recognized
the Zai Zai Omicron chapter of
Phi Kappa Kappa chapter and new
Epsilon chapter of Omega Psi
Phi fraternity Incorporated for
their leadership, service, and
commitment to the Huntsville
community as they Alabama
statewide organization Omega
Psi Phi fraternity Incorporated
October 1st through October 4th
2026. And Whereas the 50th
Alabama statewide organization
a significant milestone for
Omega Psi Phi fraternity in
Incorporated, bringing brothers
from throughout the state of
Alabama to Huntsville to
conduct the business of Omega
Fellowship, strengthen the
bonds of brotherhood and
continue the proud legacy of
the fraternity and whereas
Omega Psi Phi fraternity
Incorporated was founded on
November 17 1911 at Howard
University and has established
A distinguished legacy of
leadership, scholarship, civic
responsibility, community
involvement, and others, sorry,
and service to others guided by
its cardinal principles of
manhood, scholarship,
perseverance, and uplift, which
serve as a foundation for the
character, achievement,
leadership, and service
demonstrated by its members,
including Brother Barrington L.
Danes, who has served as
Alabama state representative
from October. 21st, 2023
through October 3, 2026,
demonstrating steadfast
leadership, dedication, and
commitment to the advancement
of Omega Psi Phi fraternity
Incorporated and the
communities it serves, and
whereas the Brothers of Omega
Psi Phi Fraternity Incorporated
have demonstrated an
exceptional commitment to
community service, hard work,
integrity, dedication, and
civic engagement through
mentoring, educational
initiatives, youth development.
charitable outreach,
volunteerism, and other efforts
that enrich the lives of
citizens throughout Huntsville,
Madison County, the Tennessee
Valley, and the state of
Alabama. And whereas the city
of Huntsville recognizes the
significance of welcoming
brothers and guests from
throughout Alabama to the
Rocket City and appreciates the
positive impact their presence
will have on local hotels,
restaurants, businesses,
attractions, and other members
of the Hunt. community and
whereas the city of Huntsville
is proud to recognize the Za
Omicron chapter of Phi Kappa
Kappa chapter and new Epsilon
chapter of Omega Psi Phi. Thank
you. You're welcome. this You
can keep the actual resolution.
You are very welcome. Did you
wanna see if you want. Would
you like to say a few words as
well. Good afternoon. I would
like to bring greetings on
behalf of our forty-third Grand
Bassus, Brother Mark Jackson,
our 26th district
Representative James M. Reed
the 4th and on behalf of the 34
chapters that inhabit the great
state of Alabama, we would like
to say thank you. We move on
the mantra of this year during
this term of impactful presence
understanding that if our
presence has no impact, then
our absence will make no
difference, and we're not just
talking about money and influx
of monies that will come in
from us coming and as As was
stated, the hotels. The
restaurants, the eateries, but
also what will happen in the
community. So as such, we would
like to invite you, uh, on
Friday morning of next week at
10:00 a.m. we'll be going to
the Boys and Girls Club, uh, at
Calvary Hill, and then on the
on the same evening at 6
o'clock we have a public
program, after which we'll have
our talent hunt and the talent
hunt is a competition of
individual children from across
the state who doing piano
recitals, who will do. speeches
we will do dances, who will do
other things and tell us that
they will display, and then we
also invite you to come and see
what we have to offer as we
will be showcasing the first
ever Omega Shark Tank. Well, we
call it the fish bowl, and the
fish bowl only because we just
found out that all the kids
were going to go on spring
break, so we had to go from a
shark tank to a fish bowl, but
we will in the future have the
Shark Tank, but what it is is
exposure for the local
individuals and those across
the state. From different
programs that come and do their
STEM at work that they will be
able to showcase and it will be
judged by members of the STEM
community here in Huntsville.
So first of all, we thank you
once again for this wonderful
award, for this wonderful
recognition, but most of all,
thank you for your help as we
move forward in helping others.
Thank you so very much. God
bless you all. some people On,
on the first step here and then
everyone's gonna come forward.
We're kind of group together in
two rows here. Perfect. that.
OK. All right. There we go. All
Anything else? you everybody.
Here we go. 12. Hold on. Thank
you. Thank you. Mr. Thank you
Mr. Meredith and Ms. Watkins.
For sharing the good work of
the Omega Psi Phi fraternity.
We have no presentations. We do
we're saving those all for
later. Uh, we do have one
announcement, and that is the
vote canvassing for the runoff
election held on September 22nd
will be held September 29th at
12 o'clock in these chambers.
We have no matters with outside
legal representation, and we
have 4 public hearings to be
held. 9A is a public hearing on
authorizing the demolition of
an unsafe building constituting
a public nuisance located at 33
14th 7th Avenue Southwest,
Huntsville, Alabama, and
consideration of a resolution
pertaining to the same, Mister
Irwin, yes, Mayor Battle,
Council member Scott Irwin
Community Development
Department. This resolution
authorizes the demolition of an
unsafe building constituting a
public nuisance at 3314 7th
Avenue Southwest, the owners
and interested parties were
notified. This hearing by
certified and first class mail
and entry parties may be
present this evening to voice
objections we have photographs
of the property for your review
on the screen, an independent
contractor inspected this
property and determined it was
not structurally feasible to
repair graveyard at 85%
structural loss, the
independent assessment know
that the roof has failed with
water damage. There are holes
in the walls, floors, and
ceilings, multiple broken
windows. The property also had
multiple non-permitted
additions. The property has
been declared unsafe. No
Permits have been issued for
repair or demolition and
official notice was sent again
by first class mail on August
12, 2026. We questioned the
demolition and removal of the
structure, the owners and
interested parties were
notified to attend this city
council meeting and the council
chambers where any objections
could be heard. No action has
been taken, and we're now
requesting the council's
authorization to ate this
nuisance. Thank you, Mr. Irwin.
The public hearing on this
matter is now open. Is there
anyone here wishing to comment
on item 9A. Seeing none, the
public hearing is closed. Is
there a motion motion from Mr.
Little. Second from Mr. Kling
to approve the resolution. Is
there any discussion? Questions
for Mr. Irwin. All in favor,
please indicate aye and opposed
The motion carries. 9B is a
public hearing in order to hear
consider and act upon all
objections or protests, if any,
for removal of a public
nuisance at 3200 Tucker Drive
Northwest Huntsville, Alabama,
and consideration of a
resolution ordering abatement
of a nuisance located at the
same property, Mr. Irwin. Yes,
again, Mayor Battle, council
members, this public hearing is
in reference to the property
located at 3200 Tucker Drive
Northwest. The property is in
violation of the state public
nuisance Act regarding junk
community development issued a
notice to the property owners
and interested parties and the
property remains in violation.
community development is
seeking your authorization to
abate this junk public nuisance
the condition of the property
is before you on the video
screen, including photos from
when the property was initially
determined to be a nuisance,
the owners and interested
parties were notified to attend
this city council meeting in
the council chambers or any
objections could be heard
regarding the abatement of this
public nuisance property owners
are present this evening and
they have made substantial
improvement. However, the
nuisance conditions do still
exist upon your approval of
this resolution, we will
continue to work with the
property owners. to allow them
the opportunity to complete the
cleanup, however, failures to
do so in a reasonable amount of
time will result in the city
moving forward with our
standard abatement process.
Thank you, Mr. Irwin. The
public hearing on 9B is now
open. Is there anyone here
wishing to comment on this item
? Please step to the microphone
Give us, if you will give us
your name and address for the
record. We will look forward to
hearing from you. My name's
Diana Cunning, and I live at
that address with my husband
and um We're working very hard
to straighten everything up and
and make it, you know, the best
we can. So You know, we're not
a nuisance to the neighborhood
because we love Huntsville and
we want to stay here. Thank you
Is there, you, you can, is
there anything else you would
like to say? No, they just
weren't working very hard to
clarify, you know, fix the
problem we wanna do it very
good. Thank you. Is there
anyone else wishing to comment?
Seeing none, the public hearing
is closed. Is there a motion to
approve the resolution to
approve motion from Mr. Little.
Second from the chair. Is there
any discussion? Yes, Mr. Kling.
I think as we've done in the
past and just so everyone
understands we are basically
giving Mr. Irwin the authority.
to conduct things as he sees
fit and it would be his
judgment as much as how Good
faith effort you're making and
if there's a problem and
nothing's happening, then he
has the authority pretty much
to lower the boom, so. Just so
you understand what our motion
was that the intent. any other
comments or questions, Ms.
Watkins? Oh. The council
members, I did speak with the
owner prior to the meeting this
evening and explained the
process upon your approval.
There will still be an
opportunity for the owner to
complete the nuisance abatement
and we'll work with them in a
reasonable amount of time to
allow them that the opportunity
to do so. And, and we
appreciate the good faith
effort that has been made so
far and look forward to getting
that cleaned up. Um, All in
favor please indicate aye and
opposed? The motion carries.
Thank you, Mr. Irwin. Thank you
Thank you. We'll move on to 9C.
9C is a public hearing on the
zoning of 2.62 acres of land
lying on the north side of Old
Monrovia Road east of Wayne
Road to Highway Business C4
District and consideration of
an ordinance pertaining to the
same, Mr. Nunez, good evening,
council members. Mayor Battle,
Thomas Nunez, manager of
planning and zoning services.
This item is located north side
of Old Monrovia Road and east
of Wayne Road, uh, the property
is seeking to petition is
seeking to zone the property C4
um, which is consistent with,
uh. Zoning in that particular
area. It is for a proposed
commercial development. Thank
you, Mr. Nunez. Is there anyone
the public hearing is now open.
Is there anyone here wishing to
comment on item 9C. Seeing none
the public hearing is closed.
Is there a motion to approve
motion Meredith. Second from Mr
Little. Discussion. All in
favor, please indicate. Aye,
any opposed. Motion carries. 9D
is a public hearing on amending
a platt restriction to remove
the restriction requiring
compliance with the front and
rear yard setback requirements
of the residents 1B district of
the zoning ordinance as
established on the zoning plat
of the Cove at Green Mountain,
as recorded in Platte Book 2024
pages 100 to 101 of the probate
records of Madison County,
Alabama in consideration of an
ordinance pertaining to the
same, Mr. Nunez, good evening,
council members. Uh, this is a
unique item, as you all don't
see, uh. Repeals or actions to
uh amend plot restrictions, but
this one is before you as it is
located west of South Green
Mountain Road and south of
Naughty Walls with this
particular proposal, this
property, uh, uh has uh, was
annexed zoned residence 1B
rezoned to R2, the property
owner proposed a plant
restriction of residents 1B, uh
zoning density controls and
also front and rear yard
setbacks. Throughout that
development, uh, the proposal
has moved forward. In that
action, what has happened is,
is that the initial uh the
developer is still developing
the same property. Uh, they are
now finished with their first
phase. Additionally, the
initial proposal had 60 ft lots
So I'll switch from this
particular action to show you.
The lot sizes and what your um
ought to look at. Excuse me. So
the proposal itself is as they
look through this development,
they were, uh, they found that
the front yard and rear yard
setbacks did not fit. Uh, this
is what the plat restrictions
would have allowed with the
rezoning, they were allowed
everything in green and the red
is what was proposed in the
latt restrictions. Now, what
you're seeking to repeal is
what is in the orange, where
the current setbacks will read
for 30 and 35 ft, but the front
yards would be, they're
proposing to go to a 20 and 20.
5 ft. Through this development,
the initial development had
approximately 153 lots. They
have now reduced that and it's
102 lots or a reduction of 49
lots, and it also uh looks at a
lot size or comparative
depiction of the products. So
the initial product was what
you see on the left at the 60
and the new proposed lot would
be at the 80 ft lot in the
product that you see there.
Through that development, they
were able to find that the
product did not fit. Coming to
planning staff because this is
a Zoning plot restriction and
the city council does not
actually enforce restrictions.
They approved the proposed
restrictions. The action has to
come back before city council
to amend those particular
restrictions. So this is what's
before you now for this
proposed development and this
repeal is back to these, this
lot proposal for so that the
product can fit on the lots
proposed. Thank you, Mr. Nunez.
Is there anyone here who wishes
to comment on item 9D. The
public hearing is now open. Is
there anyone who wishes to come
? Comment on item 90. Please
come to the To the podium and
uh share with us your name and
address for the record, please.
Hi, I'm Miranda Fike at um 2022
Polk Drive. Uh, I would just
like to request the
consideration of the quality of
properties that people moving
into Huntsville be um that they
receive be considered over the
profit. Um, that's something
that I've kind of seen pretty
consistent is Cassius King,
prophet is leading in in
decisions that people are
making and if we're talking
about um decreasing the lawn
size and decreasing that set.
Back from the road, that's
going to affect not only the
amount of outdoor space that
these people have which I get
if they're purchasing this.
That's their prerogative that
they can choose this, but also
the aesthetics of the
neighborhood, and I take pride
in Huntsville being a pleasant
place to live, and I don't
think that this will contribute
to that. Thank you. Is there
anyone else wishing to comment?
Seeing none, the public hearing
is closed. Is there a motion to
approve the ordinance motion
for Mr. Little, a second from
the chair. Comments, questions?
Mr. Nunez, just to clarify,
this is not on Green Mountain,
it's on the east side of Green
Mountain. Is that correct? just
to clarify that for everybody,
though use for the term of the
plat, it was the COVID Green
Mountain. It's at the base of
Green Mountain, technically
within our Owens Crossroads, um
area, so to speak, and by
reducing the proposed plan by
49 lots, are we creating larger
lots? Yes, initially those lots
were proposed. 60 ft, which is
traditionally what you see in
some of the other developments
that are just north of here,
and they are going to an 80 ft
lot size which keeps that
initial plot restriction of the
7500 square feet as abided by
the initial zoning once it was
annexed, which was Residence 1B
and then additionally, they are
going to an 80 ft product, the
minimum lot sizes are 60 ft
under Residence 1B, but they
continue to abide by that.
Thank you. Anybody else? All in
favor, please indicate any
opposed motion carried. Thank
you, council members. Thank you
Mr. Nunez. We have several
public hearings to be set. 10A
is a resolution to declare a
public nuisance located at 3307
Butcher Drive Northwest,
Huntsville, Alabama, to set the
date when objections will be
heard. Is there a motion to set
the hearing for October 8th.
Second. Motion by Mr. Kling,
seconded by Ms. Watkins. All in
favor, please indicate opposed.
Motion carries. 10B is a
resolution to declare a public
nuisance located at 2610
Pentelope Drive Southeast,
Huntsville, Alabama, and to set
the date for when objections
will be heard. Is there a
motion to set the hearing for
October 8th. So moved motion by
Mr. Little, seconded by Mr.
Kling. All in favor, please
indicate opposed. The motion
carries 10C is a resolution to
declare a grass weed public
nuisance located at 13028 May.
Drive southeast Huntsville,
Alabama to set a date for when
objections will be heard. Is
there a motion to set the
hearing for October 22nd.
Motion for Mr. Little, second
for Mr. Kling. All in favor,
please indicate any opposed.
The motion carries. 10 is a
resolution to declare grace
grass weed, public nuisance
located at 1020 Stevens Avenue
Northeast, Huntsville, Alabama
to settle the date, set the
date for when objections will
be heard. Is there a motion to
set the hearing for the October
22, 2026 regular council
meeting. Motion for Mr. Little,
second. From the 2nd for Mr.
Kling. All in favor, please
indicate aye opposed. The
motion carries. 10E is a
resolution to set a public
hearing on a vacation of a
right of way between Lots 1 and
2 Arrowhead Drive, and the
introduction of a resolution
consenting to and the
introduction of an ordinance
vacating the right of way
pertaining thereto, um. To be
set for the November 5th, 2026
regular council meeting. Is
there a motion to set the
hearing. Motion for Mr. Little,
second from the chair. This
item has been, before we take
action on this, this item has
been requested by the sponsor
to be postponed for
consideration until the October
8th, um, regular council
meetings, so the chair makes a
motion to postpone
consideration to the October
8th meeting now that it has
been a motion has been made,
seconded, and it is on the
floor. Is there a second 2nd by
Mr. Little, any discussion. All
in favor, please indicate aye.
The motion carries, and we will
postpone for consideration to
the October 8th meeting. We
have several folks who have
signed up for a gender-related
public comments. We will hear
so uh let me read the little,
uh, prelim here. This portion
of the meeting is reserved for
persons wishing to address the
council on matters relating to
the specific content of items
on the meeting agenda. You may
sign up to speak on the public
comments roster prior to the
meeting when called, approached
the microphone and state your
name, home address, and city of
residence. Each speaker may
address the council for 3
minutes. Speakers shall refrain
from entering into a dialogue
with council members or city
staff and from making comments
regarding the Good name and
character of any individual. I
will call um the name of the
person who has signed up and
also the name of the person who
will follow them so that you
can be ready to come up. The
first person to make a gender
related comments is Angela
Condri, uh, subject item is
budget allocations is Ms.
Condri here? Miss Condri. And
she will be followed by Marcus
White. Good evening, counsel.
Name name and address for the
record, Angelica Conry 35811
Huntsville, Alabama. Thank you.
My name is Angelica Condri, and
I'm the president of Rocket
City Roller Derby and training
coordinator for Cave City
Junior Roller Derby. I'm here
tonight to ask you to support
the appropriation for Rocket
City Roller derby's program. I
want to be very clear that we
are, what we're asking for, we
are not asking the city to buy
us a building. We are asking
the city to invest in a
community sports program that
has outgrown the temporary
spaces available to it. Rocket
City Derby has been part of
this community for nearly 23
years, and we provide organized
athletic opportunities for
adults. We support junior
roller derby and youth
development, and we bring
visiting teams with spectators
into Huntsville. We also create
events that bring people
together and every time we hold
one of those events, we partner
with a local charity and give
back to our community. That is
something I don't think I've
emphasized enough in the past.
Our events aren't just about
skating, they're an opportunity
for us to use our platform to
support other organizations and
causes right here in Huntsville
This year we lost a long-term
facility that had allowed us to
operate consistently. Parks and
Rec stepped up and helped us
survive the season, and I
cannot overstate how much that
support meant to us. Without
Parks and Rec, I don't believe
we would have been able to have
the season we did, but
temporary spaces come with
limitations. We can't build
sustainable sports programs
around constantly piecing
together whatever space happens
to be available. The goal of
this appropriation is to help
us move from simply surviving
from venue to venue to building
a sustainable roller derby
program here in Huntsville, one
that can continue generating
membership revenue. Hosting
events, supporting youth
athletes, and bringing visitors
into our city and giving back
to local charities. Ultimately
we need a home that is
appropriate for roller sports.
Huntsville has made a
significant investment in
skating and recreational
skating at Stoner Park, and
that is wonderful for
recreational skating. We don't
currently have what we don't
currently have is a dedicated
indoor roller sports
environment for athletes who
need a competition quality
surface and space for organized
training and events. That kind
of facility could serve more
than just Rocket City roller
derby. It could support both
adult and junior derby, provide
a home for roller hockey,
including teams that have
disbanded since there was a
lack of an appropriate facility
Give Huntsville's local speed
skaters a place to train and
compete as well. It could
become a true multi-disciplined
roller sports facility serving
multiple groups of athletes and
creating opportunities for
programs that struggle with the
same lack of appropriate space
that we do. I'm not asking you
to solve that entire program
tonight. I'm asking that you
invest in the program that can
grow into that solution. Rocket
City Roller derby has already
demonstrated that we can. We
can bring people together in
this community. We can create
events, we can develop athletes
and we can give back. With the
city's support, we can take the
next step from surviving
without a home to building a
sustainable future with one.
Thank you for your time and
thank you for everything the
city and Parks and Rec has
already done for us. Thank you,
Ms. Condre. The next person to
speak will be Marcus White. The
agenda item concerns hearing
aids. Following Mr. White, we
will hear from Amy Price who
has comments regarding the
budget agenda item. Good
evening, Mayor and council. My
name is comedian Marcus White.
I'm a resident here in
Huntsville. My address is 3805
Memorial Parkway. Thank you
City of city of Huntsville City
of Huntsville. Thank you. Uh,
tonight I am, uh, here to pass
the, help pass the ordinance of
26-836 uh to remove the local
tax of hearing aids. Apparently
we have an expense on hearing
aids already, um, somebody
actually thought it was OK to
say, hey, let's put more taxes
on these guys, you know, um,
with the hearing aids. I think
it's already cost thousands of
dollars and can you imagine
saving up all that money just
to hear somebody whisper in
your ear, hey, don't forget
about the taxes. All right, uh,
that is a, that's a whisper we
all hear. We hear it on
property taxes, we hear it on
food, and we also hear it on
gas. And we also heard it on
gas. Did I say gas? OK, because
gas hides the mud. I just
thought I wanna say that. All
right, um, with that being said
I think, um, that we should
definitely reach out to more
people and be part of getting
this here passed as far as just
being able to not uh put taxes
on hearing aids. Hearing aids
already cost a lot and for
Huntsville, I feel that that's
not right. That's just like
putting taxes on eyeglasses
just to see these high utility
bills as well, um, you can
imagine walking into a hearing
aid store and a salesman comes
out and says, We, how can we
help? help you. Well, obviously
I need some sound. Um, you test
drive all these hearing aids
and it's just so you can hear
your family again, so you can
hear emergency vehicles, and so
you can hear just so someone
tell you that I love you and
when you ask how much is that?
And they say $6000. The first
thing you're gonna do is act
like you didn't hear that. What
? It was $6000 and don't forget
we're gonna tax you on that. I
mean, I think that's a problem.
My main thing just to get back
to the series at hand, this
This is not a luxury. This is
more of a standard that needs
to happen. I want, you want to
hear people, uh, doctors, you
want to hear your, uh, work
assignments. You wanna be able
to hear, like I said, someone
tell you, hey, I love you and
all of that, you want to hear
general conversations and
you're tired of hearing people
with hearing aids. I'm sure
they're tired of hearing people
say, you know what? Never mind,
don't worry about it. That is
the most important thing to me.
I have a grandmother that has a
hearing aid and we was driving,
she didn't hear the ambulance
coming up on the side of us.
And I said, Hey, Grandma, you
need to pull over. There's an
ambulance coming. And the first
thing she said was, what? I
said, you're not Lil John. You
use an ambulance, you need to
pull over. And so we finally
got pulled over and the
ambulance passed by. She said,
I didn't even hear the
ambulance pass by, so that's
why I'm here today to say
please pass this, uh, removal
tax on hearing aids. Thank you
and have a good one. Thank you,
Mr. White. We will now hear
from Amy Price, whose agenda
item is budget item 19A
followed by Dustin Dykes who
also has comments regarding
agenda item 19A, the budget.
Hello, that's a tough act to
follow. I don't know that I'll
make you laugh as much. Um, I'm
here your name, name and
address for the record. Amy
Price, uh, District 5. My
address is in the record. Thank
you. um, I hope that tonight
you guys will talk about the
cameras and other similar
technology out as their own
line item in the budget. A
budget's a moral document and
an indication of values and
lack of transparency,
particularly around
surveillance technology is
deeply concerning. And modern
ALPRs, as we've heard, are
built to be surveillance
technology. Surveillance is a
breach of public trust. That
breach crosses into abusive
authority when it is employed
without transparency against
the people that authority is
intended to serve. I hope that
you will choose. I hope that
you will choose to allow public
input and oversight over the
city's employment of this
generation of ALPRs and all AI
augmented surveillance
technology. Thank you. Miss
Price, we will. Can we please
have order in the chambers.
Thank you. The next person to
speak will be Dustin Dykes.
Again, agenda item 19A, the
budget, followed by Tara Bailey
who will speak regarding the
hearing aid tax item 19G. Good
evening to the esteemed members
of the city council and my
fellow residents of Huntsville.
My name is Dustin Dykes. I live
at 709 Moon Creek Circle and
reside in District 5 of
Huntsville. Thank you. I'd like
to use my time this evening
speaking on agenda item
2026-1039 regarding adoption of
the FY 27 annual operating
budget Specifically, I'd like
to ask that the Huntsville
Police Department's proposed
operations budget of
approximately $6.5 million be
amended such that no money is
allocated towards the operation
or use of automatic license
plate reader cameras. I would
like to propose that the city
of Huntsville accomplish this
by not renewing a potentially
even terminating its current
contract NMOU. For ALPR systems
and simultaneously not entering
into any new contracts or MOUs
with any other companies of a
similar nature with regards to
LPRs, such as, but not limited
to Axxon and Motorola solutions
Kyle Dousman, Kimberly Williams
Jason Killinger, Angela Lipps.
These are but 4 names on a
growing list of 14 that
represent Americans across this
country whose 4th and 14th
Amendment rights were violated
following an unlawful arrest
due to the use of AI in law
enforcement. This number soars
into the hundreds when you also
consider those in our country
who were briefly pulled over
and or detained at gunpoint due
to errors made by ALPR systems.
In a commentary of the legal
system in the 1760s, William
Blackstone penned the maxim
that it is better that 10
guilty persons go free than 1
innocent person suffer. In the
1780s, our founding father
Benjamin Franklin expanded that
viewpoint to a ratio of 100 to
1. I am capable of recognizing
the utility and benefit that
ALPRs offer law enforcement in
their efforts to aid society
and meaningfully reduce crime.
However, that utility and
benefit becomes meaningless
when we, the people's
constitutional rights are
infringed and our well-being
harmed. Just this week, 3 US
senators, Josh Hawley, Raphael
Warnock, and our own Kitty
Britt expressed their concerns
for the abuse and lack of
regulation of ALPR networks,
and I will add that in that
same congressional hearing, the
CEOs of four leading ALPR
companies that were invited to
testify, yet none felt it was
important to do so despite the
tremendous nationwide concern
about on this topic by citizens
of all manners of various
political beliefs this year
more than 200 cities and
counties have terminated their
contracts with ALPR companies,
and while some of those cities
signed contracts with a
different ALPR company assuring
stricter guardrails and abuse
detecting audits. More than 100
walked away from AR. ALPR
technology entirely to include
a municipality with a
population comparable to that
of Huntsville. Following the US
Supreme Court ruling this
summer in Chatri v. United
States, which is my opinion
that civil liberties
organizations have gained
newfound leverage for pending
lawsuits that could one day
soon see ALPR Networks ruled
unconstitutional at that point
in time, I would like
Huntsville to be able to look
proudly at their history as one
of the cities which decided
voluntarily and proactively to
stop using ALPRs rather than
being on the wrong side of
history as a city which only
did so when compelled by legal
precedent and judicial mandate.
With all of this in mind, that
is, this is why I once more ask
that the city of Huntsville
amend its budget to exclude any
funding towards ALPR systems. I
would like to thank the
Huntsville City council and
each of your constituents in
attendance for hearing my
comments tonight. And I would
like to thank my city
councilman, Mr. Meredith, for
attending and hearing the
people's comments at the public
forum on ALPR's last week.
Thank you and good night.
Before you step away. But.
Before you step away, don't
give the name of your street,
but what is the number you have
709. Thank you. Thank you Mr.
Dykes. We'll now hear from Tara
Bailey. Again, item 19G, the
hearing aid tax, who will be
followed by Jonathan Salad Sais
Item 19D the uh Public safety
races. Ms. Bailey. Good evening
Mayor and council. I'm Tara
Bailey. I'm a resident of
Madison, and my address is
correct on the sheet. Tonight
I'm asking you to pass
ordinance number 26-836 to
remove the local sales tax from
hearing aids. I've personally
met with every member of this
council about this issue. I
first reached out in 2024,
shortly after Madison became
the first city in Alabama to
remove its local sales tax on
hearing aids. I want to thank
council member John Meredith
for bringing this ordinance
forward and council member
Michelle Watkins for her
support. I also appreciate the.
Entire council for taking the
time to consider this issue and
to have a conversation about
how we prioritize the needs of
our community. I understand
their concerns about giving up
an estimated $150,000 in annual
revenue. I don't take that
concern lightly, but I think we
have to put that number in
perspective. Huntsville is
considering a budget of more
than 360 million. So we're
talking about roughly 150,000
out of 360 $360 million dollar
budget that is very. a very
small portion of the city's
overall budget. I think that
brings us to a bigger question
is 150,000. Dollars worth
asking people who need hearing
aids to pay more for something
they genuinely need. A hearing
aid isn't an accessory. It
isn't a luxury. It allows
someone to hear their doctor
communicate with their family,
work, participate in their
community, and stay connected
to the world around them. My
grandmother wore hearing aids.
She lived on a fixed income,
and I talked to her every day.
So when I look at this issue, I
don't just see a line item on a
budget, I see my grandmother,
and I see people who are
already making difficult
choices about where their money
goes. Alabama has already
recognized the importance of
hearing instruments by
exempting them from sales tax.
State sales tax through
September 30th of 2029. Other
Alabama communities, including
Madison, Colbert County, Mobile
County, Baldwin County, and
Opelika have also adopted local
exemptions. So this isn't an
untested idea, and because
Huntsville's proposed exemption
is only for one year, I think
that gives you an opportunity.
Give people who need hearing
aids a break for one year.
Gather the actual data, see
what the physical impact really
is, then come back next year
and decide whether to extend it
based on what you've learned. I
support Huntsville's. Efforts
to maintain sustainable revenue
but I also believe we have to
look at the scale of the
revenue we're talking about and
ask whether this is the place
we want to collect it.
Sometimes leadership means
deciding what not to tax. I
want to live in a community
that looks at the things people
genuinely need to participate
in the world around them and
asks, how can we make those
things more accessible and
affordable. That's the kind of
community I want to be a part
of. I hope it's the kind of
community you want to build too
please vote yes on ordinance
number 26-836. Thank you. Thank
you, Ms. Bailey. We will now
hear from Jonathan Sais. His
item number 19D and then we
will hear from Michael Conkling
item 19B, the cola. Hello, my
name's Jonathan Sais. Uh, my
address is 815 Wheeler Avenue
here in Huntsville, Alabama.
I'm here to speak on the agenda
of, uh, the police department
and, um, Huntsville Fire
Department pay scale
readjustment. I am a city
employee, how, however, I'm
here as a citizen today to
speak to you and I appreciate
you listening. I don't have a
speech for you other than I'm
gonna shoot from the hip on
this because I'm not a speaker.
But um it was proposed to the
police department and the fire
department that, uh, there was
a raise put in place for this
fiscal year. However, that is
not the case. It was put out to
the public that way, and it was
put to us that way. Um, there
was a proposal given to, uh,
the mayor's office and it was,
uh, completely shut down. Now,
on the beginning end of this
pay scale. Yes, it does good
for your beginning officers.
There's nothing wrong with that
and I'm proud of that. However,
for your middle officers and
your senior officers who have
been here 2025, 30 years, it
does nothing If you are a
middle, uh, say you're in the
middle of the road as an
officer right now, you see no
pay raise whatsoever if you are
a senior officer, you may pay
raise. So we have a a huge gap
from the beginning, police
officer to your senior officers
There there is zero retention
built into this pay scale you
have got to have your senior
officers, investigators and
supervisors stay around long
enough to train these new
officers. If you don't, you're
going to be in trouble because
we have rookies right now
training rookies. We are short
anywhere from 80 to 90 officers
right now. We have got North
Precinct and other precincts
asking for officers to stay
over or stay. late on a daily
basis. North precinct right now
is paying a tremendous amount
of money in overtime to have
its staff to protect the
citizens of Huntsville. Um, I
wanna stay as a police officer.
I want to be here. I've got 23
years in, I can go in less than
2 years. I did not want to go
in less than 2 years, but this
has made a decision easier for
your senior officers to leave
and go ahead and retire. I've
had a few tell me that it just
made their decision easier. So
you're fixing to lose on your
back, on your, on your top end,
you're not gonna have a
retention level. You're going
to be at square one. We're not
going to gain any officers or
firefighters if we keep this up
I appreciate you listening. I
appreciate the support from the
citizens, the officers that are
here and the ones that couldn't
be here tonight. Thank you.
Thank you, sir. We'll now hear
from Michael Conkling. Subject
is 19B, the cola. And then we
will hear from Molly Ann Kluck,
Subject is 19A budget. Hey,
good evening, uh, Michael
Conklin, 815 Wheeler Avenue.
Thank you. City of Pennsyl, I
wanted to take a brief moment
to speak, uh, bluntly about the
cost of living, cost of living
adjustment and its effect on
the Huntsville Police
Department. Uh, some of the
information I have is anecdotal
and some of it comes from FBI
stats and the city city's um.
I'll touch on some of what Mr.
Salas just said also, and I'm
also here. I am unemployed with
the city of Huntsville Police
Department, but I am here as a
citizen tonight. Um, Another 2%
cost of living raise doesn't
cover the other increased cost
of living expenses. As an
example I can give you right
now is health insurance. In the
past 3 years, uh, my hourly pay
increased 5.6%, well, 6%, while
insurance went up 19.4%. Now
obviously Obviously I'm not
blaming the council for the
increased, uh, health insurance
premiums. And I do see the
potential for creating a
separate pay scale. Uh, for
police and fire, uh, but we're
way behind the eight ball in,
in that regard, way behind. Um,
and then. The way that it's
proposed would jeopardize
several officers' retirement
rates but the separate pay
scale should have been done
years ago if that's the intent.
Uh, that would have allowed
other incentives such as uh
shift differential language
incentive, etc. Now we're
playing catch up at a dire time
in our staffing, as Mr. Sala
said, uh, um. Every single day
we get emails from every single
precinct, every single shift,
asking for people to stay over.
I know you guys have seen the
overtime expenses. So, uh, it's
no surprise to you, uh, but
it's every single day at every
precinct. Right now we start uh
West Precinct 3rd shift 4 days
out of the week we start at or
below minimum manpower. 3 days
is below minimum. And one day
at minimum. Now that doesn't
include if we have anybody on
military, any type of training
or anything like that. Or uh if
anybody gets sick, has some
type of emergency that that's
the starting point. It's below
minimum. Um, I don't know if
you guys know those numbers or
what the command staff tells
you because we're not privy to
that information. I've been a
patrol officer for 15 years
with the city of Huntsville.
And I can tell you that the
manpower has never been this
bad. I'm gonna skip some of
this just to catch up with time
Right now, on a, if, if one of
those days that we're below
minimum manpower, we have to
find someone to cover our shift
and typically pay out of pocket
I had to do this on my oldest
daughter's graduation this year
It was my responsibility to get
that covered. So the department
is in a place where not only
recruitment is a huge need but
also that retention that Mr.
Salas was talking about. And,
and we, when we talk is made
about potential raises and how
the meetings went well, uh, but
another 2% cost of living
adjustment, to be honest with
you, is a little bit of a slap
in the face. Uh, we not only
need our own pay scale, we need
a significant raise to help
with retention and recruitment.
Um, The Thank you very much.
Thank you. We'll now hear from
Molly Ann Cluck. Item is 19A,
the budget, followed by Carson
Davis. Item is 19A. I Just to
be clear, you did say Molly and
Cluck. It's hard to hear. Molly
All right. Uh, my name's Molly
Anne Cluck. Um, my postal code
is code is Huntsville and um I
am a resident of Huntsville.
Thank you. Yeah, there we go.
Address correct form. I'm here
to level concerns about agenda
item 19A and state my
opposition to ALPRs and the
decision to bury their funding
inside an $88 million police
budget. This is public money
being spent on mass
surveillance and hiding ALPR
expenditures inside a massive
police budget does not make
them any less objectionable.
Huntsville residents have a
right to know exactly how much
of their money is being used to
track their movements, who
profits from the contracts and
who has access to the data.
This lack of transparency is
particularly troubling in light
of the dispute between council
members Meredith and Robinson
over the September 18th budget.
Meeting Robinson converted a
special session into a work
session, removing the council's
ability to take legislative
action that day. The result was
a budget presentation without
the opportunity for immediate
legislative action just days
before today's scheduled budget
vote. Considering Robinson's
great love of flock cameras, it
doesn't take much of my
imagination to consider why she
did this. But why does this
matter? It matters because
ALPRs are mass surveillance
technology. They collect
information about the movements
of people who are not suspected
of committing crimes, creating
records that can reveal where
people work and spend their
personal time. Their use raises
concerns about reinforcing
existing patterns of
discriminatory policing,
particularly in communities of
color and lower income
neighborhoods. And this
council's lack of transparency
extends beyond the budget, as
you have refused to release
ALPR audit logs even as
residents question how the
system is being used. There's
also a national security
dimension that the council
cannot dismiss. Huntsville is
home to people working in many
sensitive industries, and
recent reports describes
researchers being able to
extract approximately 1.6
million images and 27,000
videos from a compromised flop
camera demonstrating that these
systems can expose enormous
quantities of location data. A
compromise mass surveillance
network gives hostile foreign
intelligence services valuable
information about the routines
of people with security
clearances. The council
therefore faces two distinct
questions. Why we cannot see
the full cost of this program
and why you are accepting the
privacy discrimination and
security risks of collecting
this information in the first
place. Our demand is clear.
Separate every dollar allocated
to ALPRs from the general
police budget and publish a
complete itemized accounting of
equipment, maintenance,
software, data, storage, and
vendor contracts. Put that
expenditure before the public
and the council as an explicit
budget item before any vote.
Residents deserve to know
exactly how much of their money
is being committed to
surveillance, a budget that
conceals those costs should not
pass without that disclosure.
The next person to speak will
be Carson Davis. Subject is 19A
the budget. And following um Mr
Davis, we will hear from Clay
Perri. Item is 19A, the budget.
My name is Carson Davis. I'm a
software engineer and
artificial intelligence
researcher here in Huntsville,
Alabama. My address is on the
sheet. Thank you. Last
Wednesday we listened while our
police officers lied to us
about whether or not Flock can
track us. The director of the
North Alabama Crime Center said
and I quote, what LPRs cannot
do is track your movement. But
then a room full of engineers
and scientists came to this
podium to desperately try to
explain what should be obvious
to any child. If you take a
picture of someone when they
leave work, and then at the
grocery store and then at their
kids' daycare, and then outside
of their neighborhood, then you
were tracking them. And that is
a violation of our basic rights
to privacy. But Flock does not
want to stop at pictures. Last
month, we learned that Flock's
latest AI surveillance tool, OS
Investigate, reads bumper
stickers, physical descriptions
and driving patterns. Police
officers can now ask a chat
agent for cars that travel
together. They can ask for cars
that went to 3 grocery stores
last night, and we know from
public records requests that 50
police agencies around the
nation have already used Flock
to track peaceful protesters.
Now I know that our police are
proud of using the latest
technology, so I asked them,
will Huntsville ever use these
surveillance tools and the city
administrator told me point
blank yes, as long as it is
legal, then they are willing to
use this technology. And of
course this just assumes that
it's only the government
violations. violating our
rights, but read the news
license plate readers have been
hacked all across the country,
and yesterday's Senate hearing,
we learned that stolen flock
logins are for sale today on
Russian forums just this month,
as mentioned, hackers stole a
flock camera and accessed 1.6
million photos. Do you want
random criminals watching your
children go to school? It is
not a matter of if we get
hacked. Kurt Warshek, the
director of the multi-agency
Crime Center admitted on
Wednesday. that they cannot
promise our cameras will not be
breached, I quote, any system
can be breached ultimately. So
I ask you, if this data is not
safe, then why are we taking
the photos. We live in one of
the most advanced military
cities in the country. Tens of
thousands of engineers work
every day on top secret
classified projects for the
military, the FBI, and foreign
nations space program. Imagine
our enemies knowing where a
missile defense scientist lives
where car they drive, which
daycare their children go to.
When these cameras are
inevitably hacked. That is the
national security risk that you
are signing us up for. I have
one simple request. Listen to
the engineers in this room.
Listen to the scientists.
Listen to the citizens of
Huntsville and get these
license plate readers out of
our city. Thank you. Thank you,
Mr. Davis. We will now hear
from Clay Perri, and he will be
followed by Kathy Perri. Item
is 19A, the budget. I'm Clay
Perri. I live at 2323 Rothmore
Drive in Huntsville, Alabama. I
first wanna uh thank Councilman
John Meredith for having the
forum last week, um, you gave
the time and respect that the
the residents of the city
deserve. I know the crowd was a
bit much at times and um your
composure and professionalism
was greatly appreciated. You're
you're an outstanding public
servant. I just want to get
that off the record for the
rest of the councilmen who
weren't there. I just want you
to know that there were more.
Technologically savvy people on
this side of the room that
understands the technology
involved with those systems
then sets on the other side of
this podium, and that's to
include the law enforcement
agents that use it. I think you
should take what's been said on
this side of the podium to
heart when making your
decisions. So I wanna make sure
that the city of Huntsville and
transparency puts out the
contracts and agreements
publicly for there to be
reviewed because I'm told. By
law and H. Huntsville law
enforcement that that we own
the data. If it goes where they
said it went, we do not own the
data. We do not control it. We
had Mr. Warz already who's in
agreement with the FBI, the
Secret Service state that they
share information they have
access to it. HPD does not
control it. To say that. It
lowered 29 cameras in a city of
225 miles. It lowered the
double percentages in crime
rates is a manipulation of the
mathematics. Huntsville
actually has 400 to 500 cameras
that the police department uses
200 of those are LPRs. Only 29
flocked. So where was the
scientific method applied to
those percentages again, it
puts out that it's like
Huntsville City Police
Department is trying to the
residents in the safety and use
of these things. All right, on
the side, the side, LPs cannot
do. I asked specifically. The
director Of our multi-knit
force. If they um have the
technology he couldn't even
state the model numbers and if
they had it, the city of
Huntsville the gunshot
technology which it takes off
the sound in the vigilance
cameras, which is about the
other 200 and something cameras
we have for ALPRs, so we are
monitoring using that
technology. The Flock cameras
are capable of that. Is it
enabled? No, we should have the
right to look at those logs
publicly um. Releasable. I saw,
I saw on the slide deck on the
warning banner that they say
they have to click past. I saw
the states listed as California
Colorado, Connecticut, New
Mexico. That means that that
states, multiple agencies have
access into that system and so
Huntsville does not control it.
You cannot guarantee our
privacy. Thank you, Mr. Perri.
Your time is up. Thank you for
being with us. We'll hear now
from Kathy Perri. Item is the
budget. Followed by David
Matthews, Item is the budget.
Cathy Perri, uh, 2323 Rothmore
Drive, Huntsville. Thank you.
About the A, the ALPRs. I want
people that are doing illegal
activity caught, but I have
concerns about the ALPRs. I
just don't trust the person on
the other end of the camera who
is on the other end who can
access the data because HPD
doesn't own it and as
technology continues to advance
what will they do with it five
years from now? Maybe it's true
that it's only being used to
solve crimes today. What if
someone decides to use it for
other purposes. offices or if
others come into power and our
government or police department
that have different ideas. LAPD
is the 3rd largest police force
in the US. In July they stated
they're not renewing their
contracts because of serious
concerns around civil liberties
and civil rights issues,
particularly around privacy and
the data that's being collected
Lucas County, Ohio has an
estimated population of 423,000
which is equivalent to Madison
County, Alabama's population.
Last month one of their
commissioners asked for a pause
in the use. A flock cameras and
an audit by an outside third
party because he found that
Lucas County had 9,464642
searches of its flock camera
data in a 30 day period. These
searches involve more than 3200
law enforcement agencies of the
top 20 law enforcement entities
that access their data only 4
were from organizations in Ohio
at the other 16 were from out
of state entities, and that's
counting the FBI as an in-state
operating entity. The sheriff,
who is proud of it, said that's
why our dad is being assessed
so many times because we're all
part of the national database
that Flock maintains. That's
the beauty of the system.
That's why it's. So effective
because if you commit a crime
in one state and flee to
another state, this database is
still going to track your
movements and we're gonna find
you. We're not simply talking
about a camera taking a picture
We're talking about a database
that can tell any person
searching where your car has
been, where you were, and the
forms and patterns to monitor
your everyday movements. Flock
is about surveillance, not just
cameras. Be invisible in public
should not automatically mean
permanently being tracked. The
Constitution protect. more than
our rights, more than our right
to avoid being arrested. It
also protects our ability to
live, associate, speak, worship
organize, and move through our
community without unnecessary
government surveill
surveillance where it tends to
cross the line into mass
surveillance and how quickly
we've done that without
regulation or control. That's
what concerns me. We're
basically building an
infrastructure for surveillance
It's just being slow rolled out
to normalize the progress each
step of the way. Thank you, Ms.
Pree. We'll now hear from David
Matthews. Subject is the budget
followed by Cayden Helbling,
subject is 19A, the budget.
Good evening. Good evening. My
name is David Matthews. I
reside at 232 Approach Lane and
Tony. Thank you. I want to
address the budget, uh, that's
on the table. The punch line is
I want to request that line
items be attached to that
budget so that individual items
can be approved or removed
specifically the intent is so
that Flock cameras or more
generally ALPRs in general. can
be a separate line item. With
the intent that they would be
removed. Have I been blessed
with the unique opportunity to,
I've been an engineer in
Huntsville for, I measured in
decades, not years. I have a
unique position now that I'm
grateful to have. I get to
manage a team of engineers that
deals with this technology
every day that deals with this
technology, not just for
Huntsville, not just for the
state of Alabama, but, but for
the country at large as defense
contractor support in the AI
world. I'll make the offer to
all the council members if you
feel that you need more data to
make an informed decision on
why should we cancel these
contracts, I stand ready. My
team stands ready to provide
that data so that you don't
feel like you're making it
emotionally or subjectively. I
can tell you to put a wrapper,
a bow on that box. There is no
valid reason why we should have
not just flock, but ALPRs in
general and what you really
need to be aware of is if the
city of Huntsville,
well-intentioned though they
may be, say we're going to
release the logs we're going to
protect the data. It does not
matter. The minute that data
leaves that flock camera, it's
in the ether. It's in the
cellular network. It's going to
an AWS. As cloud, the city of
Huntsville cannot pass a law to
contain that, to protect that,
you're basically saying if we
have fought cameras, we're
willing for every vehicle of
every citizen on every
Huntsville or Madison County
Road for all that data to be
available nationwide. That's
what you're saying it not might
not be your intent. But again,
the minute that data leaves
that camera, it cannot be
controlled. There's this
concept that's in Huntsville,
rightly so, called ethical
hacking. I work with a team,
not my engineer specifically,
but that are paid by the
federal government to perform
ethical hacking to follow
guidelines and rules to look
for vulnerability,
vulnerabilities in our own
systems, so it's a very
positive way to check ourselves
if you looked at a scale from 1
to 10 of what are the system's
most easily hacked versus most
difficult. I would argue that I
think my time is up. I would
argue that flock cameras are
easily a 0 or a 1. They are
very vulnerable to attack. So
thank you, sir. The offer
stands. We'll now hear from
Kayden Helbling. Subject is 19A
the budget. Good evening. I'm
Caden Heebling, and I live in
Huntsville. My address is on
the sheet. Thank you. Uh, Last
week this city held its first
public forum on Flock and ALPRs
The city made its best case for
using them. Then for over 2
hours residents spoke.
Engineers, PhDs, and everyday
people. Not a single of them
spoke in support of Flock or
vigilant or any plate reader.
Not even today was there a
single person speaking out in
support of them, because the
problem isn't flock or any
specific vendor, mass
surveillance is wrong no matter
what label you put on it or
what guardrails you put around
it. The money for these cameras
is in tonight's budget. And
there's no line item for it. If
you pass this, the finance
director keeps paying and
renewing. And no one on this
council votes again. Councilman
Meredith committed last week to
bring a line item discussion
during the budget process. If
he moves an amendment, he needs
a second. There are a few
amendments we would like to see
considered. First, no spending
or renewal on ALPRs without a
separate vote of this council.
It wouldn't mean removing any
camera or canceling a contract,
but it would mean your vote in
public before any money moves.
Even even better, stop funding
them altogether. A motion that
spins no 2027 money on ALPRs
and keeps the money inside the
police budget could be brought
tonight. There has never been a
stand-alone vote on these
cameras in this city. Above all
of these. Take up an ordinance
like Walker County's commission
did and vote unanimously to ban
ALPRs off our streets entirely.
I'm asking each of you to say,
by your next meeting, whether
you would sponsor or support
one here. You ask the people of
Huntsville what we thought and
we told you. The question
tonight is whether or not you
act on it. Thank you. Thank you
Mr. Helbling. We have several.
Can we have an order, please?
We have several people who have
signed up and there is no
associated item with them um.
Uh, they all indicate it is
regarding data centers. And we
don't have, we, we have a TVA
data center rate. Adjustment,
but we don't have anything
specific to data centers. So if
it's all right, we will hold
that Madam President, isn't the
rate for data centers on data
centers, if, if the comments
are regarding that rate, then
we will go on but again, limit
your comments to the agenda
item. The, so we have Nancy
Horgan, who is going to be
speaking about data centers.
We're going to assume that's an
item 17A. Is Miss Organ here?
Ms. Anderson is here. I know.
Ms. Anderson, you would you
like to speak regarding the TVA
rate uh data center rate Madam
President, yes, I wonder if it
would be helpful if you or
somebody could explain exactly
what that item is and what the
relationship, so then they'll
understand what it is that you
were talking about. So this is
item 17A, a Huntsville
Utilities item to execute a TVD
rate change amendment that
would create a distinct rate
for data senders to cover
additional capacity needs,
ensuring that costs are fully
covered through future
increasing rate and reinforcing
grid reliability. So if you
have comments regarding the TDA
uh rate change, then this is
your opportunity to speak,
otherwise we'll wait until the
end of the meeting, so Ms. Uh,
Horgan is not here. Ms.
Anderson, would you like to?
Give us your name and address
for the record, and, uh, make
comments regarding the TVA data
center, yes, my name is Lynn
Anderson. I live at 10023
Conrad Drive, um, we're very
happy that TVA is TVA is um is
going to um not. This on the
backs of the ratepayers, so
this is a good thing, uh, we've
been, I've been working with,
uh, with Jenny for over a month
to try to get a meeting on the
meta AI data center, a lot of
the public, my group is called
Empowering Women's Causes. We
are a nonprofit 501c4 we've
been heading this up, but this,
this issue crosses all lines we
know that uh Meta was created
in 20. 18 that Huntsville and
it was really under the radar
so there's really nothing we
can do about the data center
right now, but we are
interested in their, their
phases that are not yet here.
They're on a 340 acres. There
are problems with sound
pollution. There are, uh,
people who are can't stand the
lights going on. There's
problems with water pollution.
We've heard all kinds of things
how wonderful so. So, um, up
until this evening, I, we've
been on a cliffhanger and I
appreciate Jenny Robinson
working with us to get this
meeting going, but, um, Henry
Thornton, who is the metadata,
the made the meta data center
representative, uh, somehow is
not able to make any of the
meetings that we are trying to
schedule with him, and I feel
that the city council needs to
put this on as a work session.
We have questions about
accountability, transparency,
uh, all kinds of things from
the beginning of this, the
public really wants to know
what's gonna happen in 20 years
when this technology is no
longer adequate. How is our TVA
or and, and Huntsville
utilities and water usage. What
is that? What about the
pollution? We have no questions
and Jenny had a meeting with us
With, with David Little as well
we had about 30 or 40 people we
met here in this building and
we have hundreds of people who
have questions, so what I'm
asking tonight, and I
appreciate you listening to me
is, uh, for a meeting with all
of you in the city council so
we can ask our questions if Mr.
Thornton can't come from Meta,
then that's, that'll just be
the way it is. We'll, we will
have questions for him. But I
think that you all need to hear
about this all across the
country people are closing down
data centers we can't do that
now because it's here and
there's no way to close it down
We're not asking for that, but
we are asking for a moratorium
on the next phases of this data
center we need information and
I would hope we could have this
transparency and accountability
from you, the city council, and
your mayor Battle. Thank you
for your time. You, Ms.
Anderson, um. The next person
is if it's hard to read Yvette
Flores Marvin. And I believe
data center is still is the
concern is that person here.
And that concludes all those
who have signed up. That
concludes our agenda-related
comments. We will now move on
to comments from the mayor.
Thank you Madam President, um.
We'd like to congratulate all
all involved, uh, engineering,
administration, everybody who
was involved in making in
getting the $10.8 million
dollar grant for Resolute Wade.
Uh, that was the Arsenal's
number one priority, and that
will help move, move that
project along quickly. Um, and
I sad, sad point, uh, on this,
uh, past week, Martha Herford,
um, uh, passed away. Uh, she's
the wife of Sonny Harford, uh,
mom of of Sonny Herford Junior.
and um we We offer condolences
to the family. Um, with this
cyber Week in Huntsville, the
International cyber summit is
here, uh, 3000 strong over at
the BBC. I think they're ending
up today, but they've had some
great, uh, talks and their,
their talks were very
interesting. They had AI. They
hit um uh the cyber area, uh,
uh, all areas that are, you
know, the areas that are now
the topics of conversation and,
um, it was a very educational,
um, uh. Uh, seminar and uh you
walked away with just a little
bit more knowledge than you had
had before, uh, today Eli Lilly
had their day of giving. Uh,
they, uh, they passed out
50,000 pounds of food supplies,
um, uh, to, uh, people who felt
like they were in need and the,
and the city of Huntsville and
Madison and Madison County, uh,
and you know this, those are
the kind of companies that you
want to bring to your community
those that give back to your
community and give back on a
regular basis. And, uh, it was,
it was a great day of people,
uh, doing good things for our
community, uh, for the record,
I'd like to appoint Kyle
Collins, uh, the reappointment
of Kyle Collins to the planning
commission to expire October 3,
2029. And that's all I have.
Thank you, Madam President.
Thank you, Mayor Battle. We'll
move on member comments, and we
will begin with council member
David Little. Thank you, Madam
President. I'll be real brief.
Um, October 13th is the date
for our Cove area town hall and
association with Planning Month
It'll be at 5:30 at the
Goldsmith Shiftman School.
Thank you. Thank you, Mr.
Little. We'll hear now from
council member John Meredith.
And I will use Mr. Little's
time and my time as well. Um, A
lot of folks have been asking
me if I ever heard back on my
request of uh the city attorney
to give an opinion. On. It
really wasn't an opinion, it
was the rules, the
parliamentary rules of whether
or not you as the council
president after a closed door
meeting with the administration
could arbitrarily change a
called and noticed special
session of the council to a
work session of the council
over the objection of a council
member with no vote of the
council. What I got was several
pages of We'll call it legalese
um, that the deflected. Um,
obfuscated. And really did not
answer the question, um. The in
the section called Brief
Answers, um, there was some
discussion of two council
members calling a special
session. Um, however, if the
council president as the
presiding officer and under her
discretionary authority called
the special meeting in
conformance with the applicable
law, even at the informal
request of a council member,
which was me. Um, then she
quote should have the
discretionary authority to
change the special meeting in
favor of a work session even
over the objections of the
single member requesting the
special meeting. She provided
no verifying footnotes to that
and to my understanding, should
have is not a legal phrase. Um,
it certainly doesn't mean she
had it. He would have said she
shall have the authority. It's
not what he said. He said she
should have. Which again to me
legalese that obfuscates the
answer to the question. I did
As well. In his conclusion, he
stated that it was his opinion
or the opinion of his office
that the council president was
operating within her authority
when the special meeting she
had called under her
discretionary authority was
counseled in favor of a work
session. To be totally honest
with you, I kind of thought.
That's the way it would come
down from the legal office. But
that is why when I asked for
that. Ruling parliamentary
ruling. I also asked
specifically that an opinion be
asked of. The Attorney general.
And I was later informed,
obviously not during the
meeting where the request was
made, where I believe the
knowledge existed, but it was
not communicated in an open
forum. Um That a single council
member could not call for such
a request that it had to be by
the uh uh action resolution of
the council. There's no sense
for me to pursue that. Because
I know which 3 votes are going
to vote against that. So
there's absolutely no issue or
opportunity for me to pursue
that line of uh A redress. The
only person that can singularly
do it is the mayor. I'm not
going to ask him to do it
because I know he's going to
say no. So it's just.
Disappointing. That once again,
Parliamentary procedure. I
dismissed by this council. To
further That, and I think I'm
gonna do this every meeting
moving forward. Is point out
when Robert's rules and
parliamentary procedures are
not followed by this council.
There was an attempt made in
the last meeting. All of what
I'm about to say is just from
the last meeting. The last
regular meeting. There was an
attempt for Um, the Huntsville
utilities person, presenter to
talk about 3 different issues
all at once without debate.
Which Is not Allowed under
parliamentary procedure. The
chair was perfectly willing to
allow it. And thank goodness
the HU person acquiesced and
said, I, I can do it that way.
And he did it that way. And
then Mr. Klay, Asked about
dirty water or brown water I
believe is the term used. The
Chair did not stop him. But the
moment I asked about water
quality. Having couched it in
terms of is there money being
spent to The test for certain
things. She interrupted me
saying that I was out of line.
Will you let Mister Kling talk
about something without even
tying it to the budget. That is
a breach of parliamentary
procedure. Didn't stop her.
After the vote for unanimous
consent on the hearing aid
ordinance that I introduced.
She allowed Mr. Kling to
explain why he voted against it
Which is a breach of
parliamentary procedure. Once
something has been dealt with.
It cannot be discussed. That
issue had been dealt with. They
voted it down. She should not
have allowed Mr. Klein. To
explain his vote. That was a
breach of parliamentary
procedure. She's pretty good at
allowing breaches of
parliamentary procedure. That
benefit her cause. The last bit
of housekeeping. Is her request
At the, I guess it was the last
special meeting. I think she
made it again. At um the work
session in fact I think she
gave it at the work session
first, but anyway, it was about
submitting amendments in
advance for tonight's meeting.
I When I had previously
submitted an amendment in
advance. To the legal
department on amending. The
sustainability commission. That
the mayor wanted to. To start
That had been properly brought
before this council. Meaning it
had a motion and a second. It
belonged to the council. It was
the council's duty at that
point to have debate on that
issue and to vote on that issue
It was requested by the mayor
that that issue be postponed to
the next meeting. But lo and
behold, miraculously. That
issue did not wind up on the
agenda for that next meeting,
of which it had been postponed
to. And for 3 months. I've
badgered the council then it
wasn't made up of these 5, but
I badgered that council for 3
months after that. To do the
right thing. They never did.
And the mayor went in. Created
an ad hoc Sustainability.
Commission Bypassing this
council. Who again had that
issue on the floor.
Miraculously went away. He
created an ad hoc totally by
himself. And the rules of this
body were violated. That is why
I did not offer the amendments
you asked for as a courtesy in
advance because when I did that
that is what happened. So don't
ask me for courtesies that you
don't extend to me. I We're
going to ask for order in the
chambers. Not for my regular
comments. We had a great
discussion at the community
forum on Flock. It ran long.
Passion We're high. And I
understand that. I get that.
And even when the focus was
anti-me. Citizens. Of
Huntsville have that right. You
do not have to agree with
everything, any of us up here
say. And you have the right and
honestly the duty. To say so. I
wish. Law enforcement. Didn't
have to leave early, but
honestly, that was the longest
form that there ever was. Um, I
normally did them as council
president and they rarely one
or two ran past 5:30. This one
ran past 7 o'clock. It was long
It was hot. But As stated
earlier, not a single person
came up in defense of Flop.
From the general public. I
think that has to be noticed. I
think that has to be recognized
And I think it has to be
honored. And it is my intention
to talk about. The flock In uh
19A when we get to the budget
and I concur. With whoever said
Our budget needs to be in line
item. Yeah Frankly, I have
asked for that. I have spent
years asking for that. I still
don't have it. And I'm a member
of this council. And I can't
get a line out of budget. I've
also asked as president of the
council and then this year
serving as the chair of the
finance committee to
participate in the outside, uh,
appropriations for outside
organizations. And was not.
afforded that opportunity
either. But We will have a
discussion as best we can. On
flock here tonight. There are a
lot of constraints around that,
um but we have to live within
those constraints because the
rules need to be followed,
whether they hurt us or whether
they help us, and we're going
to follow the rules as best I
can get this council to do so.
I also wanted to uh mention
that I was able to attend the
North Alabama Regional
Transportation Summit on the
19th of this month. Great
discussions, um, everything
from roads to greenways and
everything in between, uh, I
had opportunities to, uh, twist
the arm of Congressman Dale
Strong while I was there on
some projects that are near and
dear to the 5th District, um,
there were many, um, state
legislators there and um county
commissions and um it was a
great opportunity for me to, to
not only push for things in my
district. District, but also to
to better the relationship that
I have with those folks, um,
District 5 is very unique, um,
whereas most of my colleagues
have one county commissioner
that is within their
jurisdiction. I have 4. Two in
Limestone County and 2 in
Madison County. So it behooves
me to have a whole lot of
personal relationships in that
particular transportation
summit afforded me. To hit all
of them. And it was very uh a
very good use of my time. I
also had the privilege of
attending the Northeast Alabama
Regional meeting and reception
of the leadership Alabama
organization, um, I was
fortunate enough to be in one
of their cohort classes. And uh
I know they're gonna yell at me
but I had forgotten exactly
which one. when and old as I am
all of those years flow
together, um, but one of the
things that we spent a lot of
time talking about their um was
frankly TVA and the
relationship with TVA to uh
Huntsville utilities and a
little bit about the data
center uh issue that will come
up here later tonight. Madam
President, thank you. Thank you
Mr. Meredith. We will now hear
from council member Michelle
Watkins. Good evening, um, on
Tuesday night I had a community
meeting to address um some of
the violence that's going on in
the city, especially specific.
I want to talk about my
district and I want to thank
Chief um Giles and Officer
Osley for coming out. They got
up and they shared, um,
comments, spoke to the crowd,
and people were genuinely glad
that you were there, Chief, as
you can tell they had a lot of
questions for you and um they
were welcoming. It was a really
nice meeting, so thank you so
much for always supporting when
I call you. Thank you. Um,
council members I, I, I need to
clarify something because
several people came to the mic
and in the past you come to the
mic and you say someone had a
meeting and the rest of you
weren't there. We don't
coordinate each other's
schedules. I didn't find out
about council members, um,
Meredith's flock camera meeting
until the day of and I already
had a meeting that I could not
cancel. I did not know that um.
Council member um Little and
council member Robinson had a
meeting about data centers. I
didn't even know they had the
meetings, so we don't, what I'm
saying is we don't coordinate
each other's calendars like I
don't check with them to see
what's on their calendar, they
don't check with me because we
have so many meetings sometimes
if they overlap. We have
meetings at the same time they
happen, but anytime you want to
meet with me talking about flat
cameras, data centers. I'm not
gonna run from it. I'm gonna
sit and listen to you and I
would genuinely. Try to get you
the answers you need, but
that's why I wasn't at the
meeting, um. I want to thank
everyone that came here tonight
And had courage to get on the
microphone, especially our city
employees because you
enlightened me tonight to some
things I did not know. I did
not know North Precinct. Had a
lot of overtime because they're
short staffed. No one's never
shared that with me. And I
think sometimes people think
council members know everything
but it's so many moving pieces
going on at one time, you can't
keep up with everything, and we
just don't know what we don't
know, so thank you for coming
to the mic. More than that,
thank you for sharing your
thoughts and your concerns, and
that's for everyone. This is
what democracy looks like. When
you come into the council
chambers and you share your
concerns, your frustrations,
your thoughts with us. And a
lot of times I'm looking down
when you're talking, but I'm
actually taking notes with your
names because sometimes when I
get those answers for you, I'll
reach out to you, but um.
Leaders listen. And sometimes,
um. It's tough to sit up here
and hear some things we have to
make tough decisions, but that
doesn't excuse the fact that
we're here working for you. So
anytime I make a decision, it's
always gonna be based solely on
what's best for the city and my
community. It's not a special
interest group, it's not a
specific person. Anybody that
knows me knows I always had the
vested interests of my
community first, and I do
because it's important that you
listen to the people. Um, I'm a
native Huntsvillian. If anybody
didn't know. I grew up here. I
went to school here, lived here
all my life. I was utterly
disappointed when the miller
went out and police don't
nobody outbursts. Because I
don't want the audience cleared
but I was utterly disappointed
at the word outsiders. As us
being a progressive city that
invite Space Command, uh, Space
Force that invite Toyota, all
these industries and government
entities to our city. How dare
us have the audacity to call
somebody a outsider. No, no.
Please don't. And I'm saying
this because if Michelle
Watkins had said that. It had
been a rupture all around this
council. Everybody would have
been in an uproar about me
saying it, but when certain
people say things, it's like,
oh yeah, they're liberal.
Social democrats. And I'm
offended. Because I don't care
if you're a Republican or a
Democrat. I took a nonpartisan
position to represent the
people in the city, not a group
But the people And we have to
be careful what we say about
people because we have people
moving here daily. And for them
to hear somebody say outsiders.
It's appalling to me. Um, One
last thing. When we get ready
to talk about this budget. I'm
gonna have a lot of questions.
And everybody knows I ask
questions. I don't ask
questions to be nasty, to be
smart. I to have clarity and
sometimes I know the answer,
but I ask asked questions
because I want you to
understand. And know what
they're talking about. So I'm
gonna have questions about this
budget. It's gonna be a long
night. It's just going to be a
long night. Um, I'm not
satisfied with some of the
answers I got. I'm not
decisions that were made. But I
will say this. I'm going to
work with this council. As much
as possible. But when I don't
agree, I just don't agree.
Thank you. Thank you, Ms.
Watkins. We'll now hear from
council member Klein. Well, I
want to commend all of you for
coming out. Kling gets up to
speak and people start walking
out. Story of my life, uh, this
is a good, this is a good
meeting. It's kind of like
making sausage. It's not pretty
but the final result is what
we're working to try to come up
with. Uh, I long, hot summer
campaigning. Throughout the
district that I represent. And
there were, you know, 3, there
were 2 other races that were
taking place. Two other
districts were involved in, you
know, other school board races
additionally and the turnout
that we had was so low that 20%
I think was the max, and
there's something disappointing
about that. Uh, we have a great
country. People have the right
to vote. People have the right
to come to public meetings.
People have the right to get up
and speak, and that type of
participation was something.
that was a disappointment to me
uh. I appreciate hearing from
people. You're not may agree
with what I do, you may not
agree. I don't know how
everything is going to come out
but the fact that people are
here and like somebody said, we
don't know it all, and it's
good to hear from people in the
public, so all of you that are
here. And are listening to me
being long winded. Thank you
for showing up because that is
a very, very, very good thing.
Um, Couple of other things I
wanted to bring concern about,
number one, let me say thank
you to all the people who came
to my town meeting Monday night
It was a great spontaneous
meeting, not as big as this,
but we had a lot of good
talking back and forth, uh, and
that was, uh, what the meeting
was about. The only rule I have
is no one can wear a necktie.
There's no set agenda. It's
what the people want to talk
about and to me that's the best
hour I spent out of every month
being on the city council, and
I appreciate that the people
who come to that. Also, I want
to raise a concern, and I don't
think I'm the only person in
this room, but there's been a
very serious problem with
recycling taking place, we get
public works to come in. Public
works comes in and catches
everything up. We take a deep
breath and next thing you know,
we're all getting phone calls.
I'm getting numerous phone
calls about myths recycling,
people who have had their
recycling sitting out on the
street for over 2 weeks and
still they're not getting
picked up, and uh we have got
to do something about this one
way or another. I'm not sure
exactly what the answer is, but
it's a very serious problem,
and I don't think I'm the only
council member. up here who's
who's aware of that, so that's
something that I really hope
that we can work on in the
future. Um, this is not budget
because it's not related to any
expenditure, but as I mentioned
in previous meetings, I hope
that in the future when we have
road resurfacing taking place.
And let me commend the mayor
because he basically is giving
us a new record. It's
resurfacing. It's broken into
four smaller budgets, but
altogether it looks like it's a
new record as far as street
resurfacing in the city of
Huntsville $24 million.22
million dollars, and that,
that's a very good commitment,
but when we have those
contracts for resurfacing with
the asphalt, the contract that
comes in for the person, the
company that comes in
beforehand to lay out. The
concrete repairs that need to
be done, the milling of the
street, prepping it, there
should be a very short turnover
time Holiday Drive, I think,
went on for over 7 months, and
there have been other hardwood,
I think, lasted very long.
Eustace again has been a very
long period of time, months, I
think well over a month has
taken place. So hopefully in
the future we can get those two
contractors coordinated so that
when one comes in and does the
prep, the asphalt. Contractor
can be behind that person. To
take place of that Um, Kind of
surprised to have my vote, uh,
committed, uh, my vote. It's
something I own. Nobody else
owns. Uh, Mr. Meredith, I think
insinuated that I was one of
the 3 votes. On something about
an attorney General's opinion.
What I understand about the
counsel bylaws as written is
that the president of the
council, the position of
president of the council,
whether it was me when I was
president, uh, Council member
Meredith, when he was president
Council member Robinson, but I
think there's something in
there that says the president
of the council shall set the
agenda. And that is my
understanding of which I think
covers that situation. However,
I am open-ended that if Mr.
Meredith still feels it's worth
pursuing an attorney General's
opinion, I would certainly vote
to support it. I don't think
there's anything wrong with
asking for an opinion, whenever
there's a legal question that
comes up. Again, that's my
understanding, but I, I would
support that if that's
something Mr. Meredith feels
like he wants to put on the
table. Again, all of you,
thanks for coming out. Uh, I
think as council member Watkins
says it's going to be a long
night. You may not be pretty.
And um there's going to be a
lot of emotion, I think, as we
get into this, but, uh, again,
that's, that's what the process
is like and it's been done
televised. It's being done in a
public forum. We are not having
secret meetings where a quorum
of the council gets together in
a in a You know, closed door
and works this thing out, so
whatever happens tonight will
happen, and again, it's not
pretty, but uh thank all of you
for being here. Um. That's all
happened, Madam President.
Thank you, Mr. Kling. Um, I
wasn't planning to address this
but I'll go ahead. We have 3
types of meetings that the
council can participate in. The
first is the one that you're
here tonight, uh, these
meetings are actually set by
statute that we are required to
meet twice a month so that the
public's business can be done
in public. And thank you for
being here to be part of that
process. We not only vote on
agenda items. We we give the
public an opportunity to
comment. You've taken advantage
of that opportunity tonight.
The second type of meeting in
addition to those. Meetings
required by law where the
business of the city is
conducted is a work session.
Work sessions are held to
examine items of sufficient
complexity that they require an
extended period of time for the
council to study the issues, to
to ask questions, and to study
out items before a decision is
made. The third type of meeting
is a special meeting, Special
meetings are rarely called.
Because we want to protect. The
public's right. To see the
council do the work and get the
information to make decisions,
the public's decisions in
public. They are usually
restricted to very specific
subjects, for instance, the
canvassing that will be held
next week will be a special
meeting. If we are receiving
information from a bond
attorney and voting on a bond
issuance because the markets
are going to close at a
particular time. We will hold a
special meeting. They are a
very, very rare again because
we have two meetings in which
those cities, but the city's
business is done and we want to
protect that. And so those
special meetings are rarely
called. They may be called by
the mayor. They may be called
by the council president. They
may be called by two members of
the council who submit in
writing the reason for that
meeting again because those
special meetings have to be
protected. We have never held a
special meeting regarding the
budget, the budget has always
been voted on at a regular
Keith held one when he was
council president. Then there
was one exception. What Mr.
Meredith has failed to tell you
is that in that opinion from Mr
Riley, it was noted that Mr.
Meredith, when he was president
Called the budget meeting as a
special meeting and then
changed it to a work session.
It was not footnoted and there
was no evidence presented to
that fact. We also you know,
this is my comment time, Mr.
Meredith, and I would
appreciate, but I'm not gonna
let you gaslight me. You do it
all the time and I, and I've
let you get away with it, you
gaslights Meredith, I'm, I'm
sure we can provide evidence of
that if needed. It's not needed
on me. I let it go. The point
and and that's impugn my
integrity and, and I don't
appreciate it. Well, you need
to bone up on parliamentary
procedure, Mr. Meredith, you're
out of order. If your question
is regarding parliamentary
procedure, you are out of order
We're going to take a 5 minute
break until 7:25. It is 7:25
and we'll call this council
meeting back to order. We have
a quorum, Ms. Watkins and Mr.
Little are here. Yes. I will
conclude my comments by just
saying how much we will miss Mr
Shane Davis. This is his last
meeting tonight, and we want to
recognize his service to the
community and thank him. And I
think he has already just
stepped out. He won't even hear
this, but we want on the record
just want to thank him for his
service to the community and
wish him well in the work that
he does as he pursues his new
opportunities. Item 14A is a
resolution authorizing
expenditures for payment. Is
there a motion to approve those
expenditures. I move for the.
For authorization and approval
of expenditures in the amount
of $33,75,24.25. 22nd for Mr.
Little. All in favor, please
indicate opposed. The motion
carries. 14. Madam Chair, you
didn't, you didn't hear me. I,
I, I, I'm so sorry. I did and
Mr. Meredith should have been
the same then, Ms. Watkins took
them, uh, made the motion, and
we will let Mr. Meredith take
the 2 on. All in favor, please
indicate any oppose the motion.
carries 14B is an ordinance
approving appropriations goods
or services for the District 5
Council improvement funds. Is
there a motion to approve? So
moved Watkins, second from Mr.
Meredith. Mr. Meredith, would
you like to share with us the
good work you are doing. Yes,
but first I need to amend the
ordinance number 26-852, uh, by
changing the appropriation
amount set forth below. $12,000
to the Huntsville City Schools
in the specific designations as
follows. Well, hang on, if
we're going to follow proper
procedure, let's get a motion
and get it on the floor, and,
uh, oh, I'm sorry, we have it
on the floor and we're, and now
we're amending it. So your
amendment is 12,000. $12,000
appropriation to the Huntsville
City Schools in the specific
designations as follows $7000
to the Williams Middle School
Girls basketball program for
supplies, uniforms, and other
participation fees, and 20,500
to the Columbia High School
Girls' flag football program
for supplies, uniforms, and
other participation fees and
2500 to the Columbia High
School track and field program
for uniform. Let's share
seconds the motion. Um, is
there any discussion of the
amendment, the motion to amend?
Is there any discussion? All in
favor, please indicate opposed
motion carries the the the
motion is now amended. All in
favor of approving the main
motion as amended, please
indicate. I, I, and he posed
the the motion carries and the
ordinance approving
appropriations for goods and
services for District 5 Council
Improvement funds is approved
as amended. We have a whole
bunch of board appointments to
be voted on. 15A is a
resolution to reappoint
Geraldine Tibbs, the
beautification Board place 13,
her current seat for a 3-year
term to expire September 30,
2029. Is to approved motion
from Ms. Watkins, seconded by
Mr. Little. All in favor,
please indicate aye aye, and
opposed? The motion carries.
15B is a resolution to
reappoint Jane Tippett to the
beautification Board Place 14,
her current seat for a 3-year
term to expire September 30,
2029. Is there a motion motion
Little to second Kling. All in
favor, please indicate. Aye
opposed. Motion carries 15 15C
is a resolution to reappoint
Ginger Young to the
beautification Board Place 16,
her current seat for a 3-year
term to expire September 30,
2029. Move to motion for Mr.
Little 2, 2nd from Ms. Watkins.
favor, please indicate opposed.
Motion carries 15D. Is a
resolution to reappoint Amanda
Burns to beautification Board
Place 17, her current seat for
a 3-year term to expire
September 30, 2029. The for Ms.
Watts second for Mr. Little.
All in favor, please indicate
opposed motion carries. 15E is
a resolution to reappoint
Loretta Weiniger to the
beautification Board Place 18,
her current seat for a 3-year
term to expires September 30,
2029. The motion from Mr.
Little, second from the chair.
All in favor, please indicate.
proposed motion carries. 15F is
a resolution to reappoint Sarah
Smith to Burt Memorial
Committee Place one, her
current seat for a 3-year term
to expire October 1, 2029. Move
motion for Mr. Little, second
from the chair. All in favor,
please indicate opposed motion
carries 15G is a resolution to
reappoint Teresa Durbrow to the
Burrett Memorial Committee
placed for her current seat for
a 3-year term to expire October
1, 2029. The motion for Mr.
Little sec for Ms. Watkins. All
in favor, please indicate any
opposed. Motion carries 15H is.
resolution to reappoint Brian
Daniels to the Burrett Memorial
Committee, Place 7, his current
seat for a 3-year term to
expire October 1, 2029. The
motion for Mr. Little, second
from Ms. Watkins. All in favor,
please indicate. I opposed
motion carries. 15 aye is a
resolution to reappoint Helen
Lean to the Burrett Memorial
Committee Place 10 to fill a
vacancy due to the resignation
of Cindy Griner for the
remainder of the vacant
three-year term to expire
October 1, 2028. The motion
Little 2 for Ms. Watkins. All
in favor, please indicate.
Imposed motion carries. 15J is
a resolution to appoint Linda
Fulks to the Burt Memorial
Committee place 11 to the seat
previously held by Don Pompelli
for a three-year term to expire
October 1, 2029. Motion for Mr.
Little, second for Ms. Watkins.
All in favor, please indicate
oppose the motion carries. 15K
is a resolution to a point.
Cody Hogwood to the City Tree
Commission to see previously
held by uh there's a typo there
by Lisa Gardner for a two-year
term to expire October 8, 2028.
Motion for Little, a second for
Ms. Watkins. All in favor,
please indicate you opposed.
Motion carries. 15L is the
resolution to reappoint Janice
Vaughn to the Human Relations
Commission, placed 3 of her
current seat for a 4-year term
to expire September 30, 2030.
Motion for Mr. Little. Second
for Ms. Watkins. All in favor,
please indicate you opposed.
The motion carries. 15M is a
resolution to reappoint Barbara
Hughes to the Human Relations
Commission place for her
current seat for a four-year
term to expire September 30,
2030. Motion for Mr. Little.
Second for Ms. Watkins. All in
favor, please indicate. All
opposed. The motion carries.
15N is a resolution to
reappoint Tammy Hammond's
figures to the uh to the Human
Relations Commission 5, her
current seat for a 4-year term
to expire September 30, 2030.
Motion for Mr. Wolf, second
from Ms. Watkins. All in favor,
please indicate. I oppose the
motion carries. Went through
that very quickly. Thank you
for your cooperation. We have
no board appointment
nominations. Are there any to
be made from the floor? We'll
move on then to 17A Huntsville
Utilities item resolution
authorizing the mayor to
execute a TVA rate change
amendment for implementation on
October 1st, 2026. Is there a
motion to approve motion for Mr
Little, a second for Mr.
Meredith. Mr. Kelly, welcome.
Thank you. Happy to be with you
here tonight. Uh, as you know,
the Huntsville City Council has
the responsibility to set the
retail rates that Huntsville
utilities charges its customers
At its August board meeting,
the TVA board of directors
approved a new wholesale rate
structure and amongst other
things, that right structure
set aside a new rate class for
data center customers and that
has the effect of creating a
retail rate. Because all
utilities that purchase power
from TVA will be buying power,
excuse me, we'll be selling
that power at that approved
rate. So, um. Yeah, I don't
know what happened, man. So
what we have for you here
tonight is, uh, the request for
authorization for the mayor to
sign the new wholesale
agreement which by so doing
creates a new rate. Uh, since
this is a TVA rate. I've asked,
uh, TVA to be with us tonight
and so I'm going to ask Mr.
Robbie Jones, who's a customer
relations manager with TVA to
uh please walk us through this
raid in more detail. Uh, thank
you, Wes, and good afternoon.
My name is Robbie Jones as Wes
mentioned, uh, manager customer
relations here in the
Huntsville office. I'm joined
by my colleague Danny
McWilliams and government
relations. It's a pleasure to
be with you all tonight to talk
about some targeted changes to
the TVA wholesale rate that
impacts the rates that TVA
sells uh power to Huntsville
utilities. I'm pleased to share
that there is no request for an
increase in rates for
residential customers or other
existing customers and in. In
fact, this rate change protects
Residential and existing
customers from the impacts of
the changing energy landscape.
TVA is updating these rates to
ensure that reliability remains
high. For customers served by
local power companies like
Huntsville Utilities, and that
rates remain affordable and
that we accommodate regional
growth, especially as it
relates to computational loads
like data centers. So that's
our goal. This chart is very
busy, but it's the foundation
of the changes that we're
making since February of this
year, TVA and local power
companies have come together to
negotiate changes to again
maintain affordability. And
keep reliability high for the
customers who buy TVA power, so
this chart is the foundation of
what we're trying to accomplish
If you'll see in the upper left
hand corner, these are TVA and
local power company residential
rates compared to the top 100
utilities in the country. You
can see that TVA's rates and
local power company rates that
we enjoy here in North Alabama
are more favorable than about
80, at least 80 of the top
utilities in the country and
the chart in the lower left
hand corner shows the TVA and
our local power companies have
a proven track record of
keeping rates affordable and
better than top quartile in the
country. The upper right-hand
chart shows the same story for
industrial rates. Out of 100
top utilities in the in the
nation, TVA and local power
companies' rates are better
than 90 of those. And again, in
the lower right hand corner,
TVA and our local power company
partners have a demonstrated
track record of doing that. So
data centers are, as you well
know, Uh, driving historic
growth and demand for power.
And so when we started with in
February of this year talking
to our customers about how to
accommodate this new growth
with protecting existing
customers uh through the
negotiation process, the TVA
board voted to adopt a special
data center rate that will
apply to all data centers
starting October of this year
and that rate has two
components to it one is a new.
right that Charges, data
centers, the cost that they
bring to the valley, so that
rate will go into effect in
October, and that results in
about a 10% increase to the
rates they currently pay again
from and that protects our
current affordable rates for
residential consumers and
industrial customers, so over 3
years that will be phased in.
They'll pay about a 10% higher
rate to accommodate their cost.
The other part of the data
center rate change is a
capacity commitment charge.
That's on the right hand side
of this slide. This is a fee
that's paid by a data center
that wants to locate in the
valley and that's an upfront
fee that's non-refundable and
it compensates TVA for the
generation that we will have to
go and build. To serve those
facilities. In between these
two, these, uh, Two components
of the data center rate, uh,
support the ratepayer
protection pledge, which TVA
signed, uh, in July of this
year, and I won't go into the
details of the ratepayer
protection pledge, but you can
see that the elements of the
ratepayer protection pledge,
emerge in the new TVA data
center rate. 10 years ago, data
centers were a very small
portion of TVA sales. Today
it's the largest industrial
sector that we serve. Most of
the data centers we serve are
located behind local power
companies like Huntsville
Utilities. And, but this is the
right time since it's now
become the largest industrial
sector to make sure that the
data centers that want to live
and work and employ people and
do business here uh pay the
cost that they bring with them.
Finally, there are a few
non-data center related items
that are in the package for
your consideration and that
we're asking you to approve.
They are administrative and
again, not increasing rates on
existing customers. These are
to help TVA and local power
companies plan for future loads
uh, managed stated load versus
actual load and then improved
pricing under our time of use
program so subject to your
questions that is the TVA
update on the uh targeted rate
adjustment for data centers.
Thank you, Mr. Jones. Council
members, do you have questions
for Mr. Jones? I have questions
need to have an understanding
of Energy usage. What does the
meta center on average
currently use per month. We
have a contract with that
company that prevents me from
sharing that information in a
public forum. OK, um. What is
the. Average small size data
centers power usage on the
month. We see data centers as
small as 1 or 2 megawatts.
That's a unit of instantaneous
demand, uh, all the way up to
multiple times that with 10 be
considered a small data center
would be on the smaller side,
yes, sir. OK, um, I think it's
called hyper uh Center
Hyperscalar hyper scalar. What
in general would They run a
month. And general, a hyper
scaler is going to be the
really, if you see one data
center, you've seen one data
center. They're anywhere from
the smallest size that could
fit in a residential home to
their reports in the news of.
Thousands of acres out west, so
there is no average and I can't
really give you a, an estimate
for what a hyper scaler might
consume. We. Hm, OK. Um um, If
a data center was hosting AI
versus standardized um.
Computational data. What would
the range be on an AI centered
uh data center versus static
storage. The demand is
essentially equivalent. The
data centers place additional
demands on TVA's system, so the
AI data centers have a
different technical profile
than storage data centers, and
that is part of the increased
cost that they're bringing with
them that these new rates help
compensate for. And I am
assuming that. You I guess it's
an unpleasant word, but with.
Better word, would you require
data centers to have a power
source other than you in case
your system goes down because
it's my understanding data
centers need power 24/7 365. So
what is the requirement
capacity, um, threshold based
on? Is it based on, well, what
is it based on? So the question
is how do we ensure that.
Reliability for the other
customers essentially yes sir.
So there are two ways we can do
that. Data centers can bring
their own generation if they
like, there's an option for
that, and we encourage that if
our timelines can't meet their
needs. Uh, the other option,
the way we protect. Current
customers from reliability risk
is until the generation that's
funded by that capacity
commitment charge is in place,
they are required to respond to
signals when TV when. Demand is
high, they are required to shut
down. Do you, how long Is, is,
how long would you operate
under that latter scenario.
Allowing them not to be able to
generate their own power. They
can generate their own power.
I'm sorry if I misstated. Yes
sir, they can, and we encourage
them to generate their own
power. OK, even in that latter
one where you ask them to
respond is to respond is to
supply, then they can provide
their own or they can shut down
Oh, now I got you. Yes, OK, I
apologize. Thank you. Nope,
that's fine. Thank you, sir. Mr
Clinton. As I understand it,
and maybe I'm not up to date on
everything. TVA is kind of
close to its maximum borrowing
limit. Are you going to be in a
position in the future where
you're going to be able to
build additional power
generating plants. Just because
I'm thinking about this area is
growing, you know, the TVA
region, especially Huntsville,
and is there going to be Power
available, you know, because I
think we have a concern about
what data centers are going to
be taking and as we grow, what
is the power situation going to
be for our consumers? Yes sir,
you may have seen where the TVA
board, uh, approved an
integrated resource plan, the
integrated resource plan costs
for 11 to 35, 40 new gigawatts
more of capacity than we have
today, and yes, TVA does have a
statutory borrowing limit of
$30 billion. However, we We are
going to do our jobs and we
have plenty of financing
authority to finance the
building of all the generation
capacity that we need to serve
the growing needs of the valley
I mean, is your new generation
capacity, you know, is he going
to stay ahead of data centers.
The capacity commitment charges
that I referenced that pays TVA
to go and acquire generation
for those facilities. OK. Thank
you, Madam President. I, it's
my understanding that Meta has
a solar farm in Tennessee that
contributes to the capacity of
um the the the grid here is at
how much, how much do they
contribute? And I'm thinking in
terms of the capacity
commitment charge. How does
that affect the capacity
commitment charge? Do you take
that into account? I'm not able
to speak to meta specifically
again because of our agreements
with them, however, the
capacity commitment charges for
new and expanding loads and
would apply regardless of those
solar facilities. And I, and I
believe, and you may not be
able to address this, but just
for the public's information
that um that met at one point
decided to take expansions to
Montgomery because the, it
would have exceeded capacity
here, so data centers can make
that choice as well. I'm not
aware of a situation where a
data center did not. come here
because of a capacity, TVA
capacity issue. And with regard
and, and I know we're just
talking about electric, but, um
I, I'm wondering if we're
looking at water as well. Is
there a similar sort of rate
charge that we're going to be
looking at for data centers for
water use. I defer to Mr. Kelly
on that. Yes, ma'am. We do
provide, while meta is served
directly from TVA because it's
large enough to be connected to
the TVA transmission system.
Huntsville Utilities does
provide it water. When you
think of uh 2025 annual usage
of the metadata center did not
rank within our top 10
customers. It generally pulls
about as much water as a as an
as a large industrial customer,
but again it didn't even break
our top 10. And it may not have
been much below that, but it's
not on the top 10. But, but so
they're not the, the drain on
the water system that a lot of
larger data centers are meta is
actually small enough, it's,
it's large enough to qualify as
a hyper scale, but. Yes, ma'am.
The technology has advanced
considerably when it comes to
water conservation and matter
of fact it advanced during the
development of the metadata
center here. Originally they're
projected water load was
significant, and before they
even turned the first switch on
they'd put in so much more
advanced technology, their
water needs dropped
significantly. That's great to
know. Um, And I guess before we
move on, the question was asked
earlier about having a
presentation by industry
experts, and we scheduled that.
I just confirmed with uh with
the Mr. Thornton from Meta that
we're going to do that at the
December 3rd council meeting.
We'll have a presentation by
Meta to talk about their
operations here Mr. Little and
I met with them. It was a lot
of the questions were very
specific to Meta because
they're only the closest we
have to a hyperscale. Center
here so that will be on
December 3rd, so a lot of other
questions can be asked and
answered at that point. Thank
you. Anybody have any other
more questions about the rate?
Uh All in favor, please
indicate opposed. Thank you
very much, Mr. Jones. Thank you
Mr. Kelly, for joining us. We
have several items items 18A is
an ordinance authorizing the
vacation of a utility and
drainage easement on Lot 18
High Mountain Estates, 2900
High Mountain Road. There a
motion to approve motion from
Mr. Little, seconded by the
chair. All in favor, please
indicate opposed. The motion
carries. 18B is an ordinance
authorizing the vacation of
utility and drainage easement
on Lot 1. Sniper Industrial
Park, Phase 5, 11563 South
Memorial Parkway. Is there a
motion to approve? A motion for
Mr. Little, seconded by the
chair. All in favor, please
indicate opposed. Motion
carries 18. C is an ordinance
authorizing the vacation of two
utility and drainage easements
for Hank's Hillside. 0 Bob Wade
Lane Northwest. Is there a
motion motion from Mr. Little
second 2nd from Ms. Watkins.
All in favor, please indicate
he opposed. The motion carries.
Will now come to 19 unfinished
business items for action, and
we have a lot of business to
take care of here. 19A is an
ordinance to adopt the city of
Huntsville annual budget for
fiscal year 2027 beginning
October 1, 2026 motion for Mr.
Little. Second from the chair.
Uh, we will begin with a Should
we have a presentation, an
opening presentation from, um,
our finance director. Good
evening, Penny Smith, director
of finance. I don't really, um,
I have a short presentation
that I can go through. It is
really just a rehash just for
the public's. OK, benefit. And
and for council members,
refresh. OK. So All I've done
here is I've pulled out and
selected a few slides tonight.
So this is the annual budget,
um, for this fiscal year for FY
27. And um and I pulled in,
is is the only slide that
you'll see tonight that is new.
It's a couple of key things
just to just kind of reiterate
some of the things that
happened for the FY 27 budget.
Our general fund revenues are
projected to grow. There is a
2% cola that is in this budget,
new positions and changes to
the city authorized positions,
all the, that we have some new
people. The, uh, public safety
changes and salary schedule we
have moved the Alabama Trust
Fund and investment interest to
general fund as revenue support
There is an increase in the
city and employee premiums for
health insurance, um, and then
just that we talked a little
bit about the pressure on costs
for energy and inflation,
pressure on the general fund
revenues through the SSUT. And
then for other funds, that's
all kind of in the general fund
some of those bleed into other
funds, but in, the increase in
healthcare costs and increase
in premiums are captured in our
healthcare plans. We have a new
1% lodging tax. The closure of
previous TIFs and new TIF 9
affects our um advalorum taxes
and then the creation of a new
fund. And then the move, um, of
some appropriate outside
agencies to the liquor and
lodging tax funds. So under
revenues, this is our kind of
general fund pie we talked on
the other night about sales and
use tax on the SHUT we covered
some pilot changes. The
property taxes and licenses.
Just this is just a quick recap
on sales and use tax as it is
our largest um revenue it is
budgeted right now total across
all funds at 332 million, um,
that covers for the general
fund, the Huntsville City
Schools, the 1990 Capitol
Projects Fund in the 2014
Capital Projects funds. On the
expenditure side again for the
general fund. This is the
general fund departments um
that are within that line item
327 million for plus for the
department spending, um, for
all those different apartments,
and that is captured at the um
the the. I'm sorry, operating
in capital within each of those
departments. Our authorized
strength, we went through the,
the certain larger ads and and
deletes within the system, so,
uh, so for that fire and rescue
police, our general services,
our parks and recreation, and
then, um, one that got smaller
was our legal. For the
authorized stuff and public
transit. And then
administration. And we talked
about all of those. We went
through each of those, um, in
relationship to those and then
in relationship to the whole,
it's a new authorization of
3,379 positions. We talked
about the general fund
transfers, and I'm gonna kind
of hit through these cause I
had highlighted different ones,
um, based on the transfers
because that cha that makes
some changes within the general
fund and it affects other funds
that the general fund supports
as a whole. One of the things
that I as we go through this is
that the general fund is our
largest fund. It has the most
departments in it, but it is
also the fund that supports so
many other services and things
that we do within the city. And
then the healthcare benefits,
um, the total cost of
healthcare continues to rise.
And that was mentioned, and
then also the cost compared to
the cola. The cola is a 2%
increase and um, and so, but,
uh, and then we are, we are
asking for the city employees,
um. Premiums to be raised, the
city will cover the remainder
of that rise in cost. So when
you compare that for an average
citizen, for an average
employee, um, the 2% increase
is 1400. The 961 for a family
plan would be 250 and so the
net increase in pay is 12:40
over time. And then going
through our our lodging tax
expenditures, we said that we
added, um, added a number of
those to the, I'm sorry, I'll
click too fast to the liquor
and lodging tax, um. To the
liquor and Lodging tax funds
and then for this was the
remainder we went through, um,
you can see it laid out. We
went through all of our outs,
not all of our outside agencies
we showed you that there is a
book on all the outside
agencies and what all was um
was set forth for their
appropriated amounts. And
that's, that's the only slides
I have. Good, good. Thank you
very much, Ms. Smith. Um,
council members, questions for
Ms. Smith or discussion? I'll
go first, Ms. Watkins, um, Ms.
Smith, for the listening
audience, would you please tell
us that, you know, it's been
over, I think 2 months ago, you
reported about the pilot
shortfall. What was that from?
So the pilot shortfall, so
Huntsville utilities came to us
They had performed some um some
analysis in their change in
their software and I'm, I'm
speaking a little bit for them.
They could explain better
exactly what happened, but they
went through that. It is a
complicated calculation for our
electric pilot. This really
only affects um electric and
fiber. Pilots, I'm sorry, um,
electric and fiber pilots for
for the city. So we have, we
have basically there's 4, it's
divided into 4 different areas
with Huntsville utilities, the
water and the gas are based on
6% off of gross revenues, those
remain the same and those have
not changed. They are by
agreement. The electric and um
and the fiber, which is singled
out, um, are both based on a
calculation that is. Um, pulled
down from a TVA from a
construct that comes from the
TVA contract. Um, so through
TVA they allow um all local
entities to, um, to have a
pilot assessed for those
agencies, um, that are, that
it's the booked value of the
assets that are owned within
that are that are within the
system. So that is everything
from buildings to two different
rights of way, parts of that is
um for use in our right of ways
Parts of that is um is very
easy to pull out of. system and
attribute to to those different
um Avalorm taxes, Part of that
gets very difficult and so that
portion of it is pulled into.
It is a complicated calculation
The reassessment and the look
at that brought that number
down. So, um, so we went back,
we went back and forth with
them. We studied it in the
analysis in the end, some of
that was come back, came back
up through some different um
both re-looking at the
calculation and looking at how
we could better that
calculation. Um, to, to make
assessments more granular, I
guess, um, and so, so in the
end those numbers came back up
um to a better number in the
future, I expect that to
continue to kind of, because
it's based on booked assets,
which is, um, you know, the
asset, the historical asset
value, the depreciation on that
asset and then as it falls off,
we will probably see that
number say about the same or go
down. That. Initially it was, I
thought it was 4 million. What,
what is, what is it the um
amount now? Um, let me look. OK
thank you. So the original
amount for the electric system,
so I'm sorry, the amounts for
the 27 proposed system for the
elector is 15 million,691,0242
for the fiber is 4,687, but I'm
not sure that that's what
you're really asking for so
much as and 2025 we received an
actual value total for pilots
at 32 million. In 2026, we are
estimating to receive the 32.4,
so we had estimated a number
above that, and we brought it
down at mid-year by the 4
million which you just referred
to and um and so it came back
up by about 2 million. Um, so,
so that's where we, we ended
for that and then this year's
proposed is at 32.8%. So just
barely above that figure, and
we expect that electric in
fiber to continue now the the
gas and the water will continue
to grow over time as as those
um gross revenues, and we are
looking into some other
alternatives with TVA, um, to
hopefully manage that a little
bit better. Thank you. So my
questions are all over the
place. My ques appropriations
they proposed a new um I, I
don't, I call it a TDA, but
it's the structure or structure
as well as a couple of things,
so who's going to take my
questions. OK OK. All right. Uh
with the positions this to you,
um, I think go ahead you were I
think gonna go where we're
going to be considering the
organization's. OK is it, but
is this the reason I'm asking,
I saw that and I understand
that, but you want us to vote
on this budget is we are we
gonna be voting on those
positions in the budget, so.
Yes, so let me, let me answer
the, the question. I think I, I
understand y'all don't want to
dive into the details of
something that comes later, but
so I'm gonna give you kind of a
general statement. So if you
look down through paragraph or
through, yeah, through
paragraph 19. You know, 1980 is
the budget. B is the cola, C is
the reorg, D is the police and
fire pay. Every one of those
are related back to the budget,
right? And so, you know, you
could ask the question, is the
cola as proposed in the next
item, included in this budget,
it is, and the same is true of
the others and so this is where
you know we kind of during the
work session we talked a little
bit about if you later in
paragraph 19 amend one of those
things, we may need to come
back and fix the budget. So
what, what we've done is in the
mayor's proposed budget because
he also was then proposing
those other subsequent things
the budget in front of you is
written to capture those other
ordinances as currently written
and so there's absolutely a
chance that if you were to, I
mean, if you were to mend the
cola, we would then need to
come back and, and have you
amend the budget. The same is
true of other subsequent things
so yes, I totally understand
that because I read it. I, I
can read and I'm not being
smart, which when I say that,
but what I'm saying is you want
me to vote on something that's
in the budget now, but then
you're gonna go back down and
then you want me to talk about
it and I can't understand why I
can't talk about it now because
I'm going to vote on it. I mean
that's the truth though, right?
Am I, am I not gonna vote on it
I understand what you're saying
and so that's where, you know,
that obviously that's a
challenge because you have to,
you have to consider and vote
on things in a certain sequence
and no matter what sequence you
do it in, you potentially would
have to go back. That's just
kind of the, the, uh, a
challenge of the structure and
that's why I wanted to be clear
that, you know, so, you know,
so maybe I need to reframe my
my question why doesn't council
receive information uh before
approving. The new orc
structure why we don't receive
the information about the um
the title. Uh, we have the
title, the pay that's gonna go
with it and stuff like that,
please, Miss Robinson, please.
I'm gonna just asking because
This is what I truly don't
understand. I understand
everything else I've read, but
we don't get the information
beforehand that I'm gonna vote
on it. Then after I vote on the
budget that is included in,
then you want me to come back
and then on down in the two
items down, we'll get to talk
about it, so you see it's
confusing and it's as well as
I'm pretty sure the audience is
confused. You want me to vote
on something that I can't ask
anything about then later you
want me to ask about it? Well,
that's, that's my. So first I,
I, I would tell you I'm not
saying no, I understand, yeah,
so I, I, I, I would encourage
you to talk about all things
that relates to the budget. I
understand that you also have
procedures that you want to
follow in terms of the level of
detail you go into. So let me,
if I could kind of maybe
clarify some of the, the, the
personnel component of, of this
is kind of always this way,
whether it's right now during a
specific budget time or even if
we 3 months from now could
bring you the results of an
audit or we could bring you a
recommendation. recommendation
to create a new position and
the process that you're seeing
tonight is actually exactly the
same as you see in any one of
those, so the way, the way the
system is set up for a council
to make decisions as it relates
to changing or creating any
position, and this is obviously
what's on there tonight are
specific to appointed positions
but the process is the same for
merited position. We could 3
months from now we could come
and say, hey, we've determined
there's a need for a secretary
in a particular department in
the process would be the same.
And that you would first vote
on, you know, establishing that
position, you would then have a
separate ordinance that
actually adds that position to
the budget, and that would only
give, that would give the grade
and so let's say for example
it's a secretary grade 10. What
you, when you approve that
position at a grade 10, you're
approving the salary range
associated with that in the
salary schedule. And then the
actual salary is determined
when that department goes to
the hiring process and offers
and in many cases they may be
brought in at higher than
minimum, and so that's when
that salary is actually decided
and so the process you're going
through tonight is the exact
same one you do every time that
we have to amend or create a
position. So it's not, this is
not an unusual um process, but
I understand the concern that
you've got to build on one
thing and then come back later,
um, and so the reverse could
also be true. We had you vote
on if you if we had you vote on
a payroll action, then then the
budget comes later, then you're
having to amend the budget and
you, you're voting on that
thing, not knowing whether or
not the budget can cover it,
right? So no matter what
sequence we do it in, it's
gonna, there's gonna be
potential why I think that, you
know, with the budget on the
floor. Every one of those
subsequent actions are in the
budget. And so, you know what
I'm saying is when you look at
the budget and you look
specifically at the coal or you
look at the personnel actions.
It's written to assume that
those other actions are
approved as currently written.
We understand that may not be a
safe assumption, but that's the
only thing that we can do to
draft you a budget to start
with and so certainly if you
end up amending one of those
other things later. We
understand you're going to have
to come back and essentially
reconsider the budget. You
could do that tonight or you
could do it at subsequent
meeting. But we understand
that's gonna happen and there's
not really a solution to that
problem, so I understand your
frustration. I just don't have
a solution to it. But see, you
gave a great example. You said,
uh, said it was a secretary
step 10 grade 10 step 3, OK, I
can go to Mr. Thomas, the HR
director, and pulled that. But
this new position, I can't go
to Mr. Thomas and pull the
salary. So there's just like
the example I gave tonight,
there's two related actions
that do that. The first one is
the action that creates the
position in the code of
ordinances. The subsequent
action, so 1919. C is the one
you're talking about that
creates the positions 19F is
the one that assigns the grade,
and so if you look at, you know
19C and F have to be looked at
together. So 19F is the one
that, that assigns the grade,
just like in my, my
hypothetical of the secretary
grade 10 in this case, some of
those positions are grade 24,
22, 23. So it's the exact, it's
the same thing, but again, just
like any other time, you've got
to look at the two together to
fully understand the creation
of the position and then the
grade that's. Assigned to it.
OK, so Um, I can't talk about
that because you can't answer
it for me. I can talk about it,
but you just can't answer it
for me, so I'll pass on that
for the sake of time. I'm not
gonna waste anybody's time I'm
happy to answer any question
that I'm allowed to answer by
the counsel. No, well, I'm
counseling and I'm asking you
to answer it, OK, so absolutely
I'll answer whatever question.
OK, how much is the position,
the new positions on the org
chart, how much are they? So
each, each one is different. I
may go pull out and tell you
the grade, and then I can tell
you the salary range. I would
like to know that I can do that
Do you want to do that now or
when they wanna do it now if,
if at all possible. Thank you.
Well, we wait on that, Madam
President, um, Councilwoman
Watkins makes an excellent
point, um, that's always bugged
me, but I know we misuse the
term table all the time here,
but would it be possible to
actually table the final vote
on the budget until after all
these other elements have been
dealt with. Well, it could, if
we have a vote of the majority
of the council to do that.
Legally could we do that, Mr.
Riley. I believe we could. Well
I'll move now that we tabled
the final vote on the budget
until after all the elements of
the budget have been considered
Second, the motion to table
discussion of the budget until,
would you like to identify
which elements you are
referring to, that would be um
19C. 19. 19 E 19G. There, OK,
needs to be included in that as
well. I, I'm sorry, did I, I, I
skipped, sorry, and um also G.
All right, a motion is on the
floor to table discussion of
the budget until we have
reviewed items 19B9 through 19G
All in favor, please indicate.
All opposed? No. So the eyes
have it. The ayes have it. Mr.
We will then Forego discussion
of the budget and move on to
item 19B. 19B is an ordinance
amended. They're going to be.
Amendments that need to happen
under it, but you've just asked
to table it. I said final vote
on it. Not dealing with the
final vote. That was the motion
was the final vote be tabled
until the other elements Mr.
Riley, can you help us with
this? Can we delay a final vote
We have, we've just moved,
we've just moved to table. An
item Can we continue discussion
on it? The motion was to table
the final vote, not on
amendments that we vote on
prior to the final vote being
taken. Madam President, can I
make a recommendation, Mr.
Hamilton? OK, so as I, as I
understood the discussion, the
intent of the request was that
you proceed with discussion and
motion on a potential
amendments as, as you already
contemplate them on the budget.
But when you believe you have
it in its final form to then
table it and move on to the
next thing. So I think what I
would recommend is that you,
since through the process you
just put it on the table, then
you can take it off the table
and then proceed with your
discussion and then the motion
for tabling should come after
all council members have
proposed that that's not the
way it should be done. And if
you need to take a
parliamentary break to look it
up the rules, then you can, but
the motion was to table the
final vote. Not any amendments
to it. This this is complicated
enough. I will honor that
request to take Can I ask for
the patience of the council as
we got to go this is a
difficult situation and uh I've
been beaten over the head by
allowing conversation or
discussion on multiple items,
and now we're going to go and
we're going to do that and my
primary purpose here is not in
service of Robert's rules of
order. Our primary purpose here
is to run an orderly meeting
and which is which, which which
which which which is dictated
to the point What is your point
? The point of order is the
procedures, the rules by which
this council runs are our
bylaws state laws do not have
the Meredith. You have not
point of order and I'm giving
you the points of order, OK
appropriate. You haven't
allowed me to give the points
of order. You are once again
violating. the rules
willy-nilly. I called a point
of order. It is up to you to
ask me what my points are and
in the middle of me giving my
points, you tell me no, you
can't do that. That is an abuse
of power. That is not following
the rules. The rules say you
must at the point of someone
calling a point of order, you
have to ask what those points
are, hear those points, then
you make a determination, then
the council votes on it if we
don't agree. The points of
order is state law, our bylaws
and Robert's rules dictate how
this op operation op operation
this, this council functions,
not not any way we want to
function and disregarding those
and Mr. Riley has just said
that we're gonna disregard the
rules that we have agreed this
body operates under, and you
can't do that. Our rules are
our rules. You can't just willy
nilly say we're not. not going
to follow those rules because
it's inconvenient for us at
this time. I did not hear him
say that. Thank you for
bringing that to my attention,
Mr. Reilly. Continue your
comments here. Here's what I'm,
I'm trying to do. You still
haven't ruled on my point of
order. You, if, if Mr. Riley
said that we are disregarding
rules, um, that was not
appropriate. So Mr. Riley, are
you suggesting we disregard
this? I am not suggesting we
disregard the rules. You're
still not honoring the point of
order. You need a break to go
look up the rules. Go look up
the rules, but I'm telling you,
you're violating the rules.
What rule are we violating?
You're violating the fact that
a point of order was called,
the points were given to you,
you as chair need to make that
determination if 2 members or
more do not agree with it, then
we vote on it and it takes. A
vote of 4, a majority to
override, not override, but
overrule. So now you're just
asking him for his decision.
Well, no, from what I heard you
say. And let me see if this is
what what I heard you said that
the attorney had said we would
disregard the rules, and that
is not appropriate. I agree
with you. If that was indeed
what he said. Is that correct?
Yes, I have asked Mr. Riley,
was that you the point of order
takes precedent. And you are
refusing to give it the
precedent. What precedent are
you wanting, Mr. Mayor? I want
the point of order to be
acknowledged, ruled on, and
that doesn't mean you disregard
and ask you for your opinion on
something, what I said was I, I
have, I have granted your point
of order. You're right, it
would not be appropriate for
the attorney to say we're going
to disregard the rules. So
you're ruling in favor of the
point of order. Yes, OK, so why
do we need to hear from from
him. You just said that we were
going to follow the rules and
the rules are as on the floor
at this time that there was a
motion to table the final vote
on the budget. Not amendments
leading up to the final vote.
There are things that I, and I
know Mr. Kla want to add
amendments to. The budget We
need that opportunity to do
that. The question I asked Mr.
Riley was how if it was
appropriate for us to, what,
what would be the appropriate
step to take? We have, we've
entered into a very. Awkward Um
effort here. Well-intentioned
though it was. And I'm asking
him the best way to the body
has already ruled. There's
nothing for him to do. The body
already made the motion and
voted on it. The There's
nothing to be considered. We
we've already made the motion,
seconded, voted on it, approved
it, and now it's time to hear
um amendments to 19A and when
we have worked through the
amendments on 19A before we
take a final vote as amended on
19A, we deal with the other
subjects. That's what we
approve. And Mr. Little has a
comment. I thought we were
tabling just 19A. Just in the
years past we've approved the
budget years don't have my, my
motion Mr. motion. Mr. Little
has the floor. Mr. Little has
the floor for real. Yeah, for
real. Little, I thought we were
tabling. 1980 that was that was
understanding that was. Then
you looked into Mr. Riley for
clarification if we can just
table the vote. Now I've got
amendments and I've got, I the
budget all year. So why we get
the butter we get the budget
approved and then we're like,
hey, I got this amendment. I
got this amendment. I want to
do when we get to 19D, I've got
an amendment for that that's
going to be voted on later.
Well, here's that's not what
the motion that was passed
stated, Well, I guess I
misunderstood. Well, you
misunderstood. That doesn't
mean that what happened doesn't
exist because you misunderstood
I was I just want, I mean, he's
our lawyer. I don't understand
the rules as good as you and
him. Well, that's why I offered
to go and look and have a
parliamentary break to go look
it up. Well, I can't give the
citations, but as in my term as
president, I learned the rules.
And whereas I can't cite it
like a priest can can cite
scripture, I know what it says.
Let's take a 5 minute break. OK
To figure out what we've done
here and how to unravel it and
to go back about the city's
business, so we will come back.
At 8:23. OK, the meeting is
called back to order. And we
have reached some clarity on
this. We will continue the
discussion on 19A, the budget,
we will entertain other
discussion. We will entertain
other amendments. And, but we
will not take a final vote
until consideration of items
19B through G has been
completed. Is that everyone's
understanding of what we're
going to do? Yes, ma'am. I All
right, then Is there further
discussion on the budget? Is
this a time for amendments if
you would like to offer an
amendment, Mr. Kling, we will
entertain that. Well, uh, we
had some discussion at the last
meeting and uh let me just say
that I think Mr. Meredith and I
I'll just say we agreed to
disagree on the way, but I
think we both had a similar
objective concerning the
Abatement of sales tax on
hearing aids. And I would like
to propose an amendment to yet,
so this is that that would be
item 19G. you can't do that.
It's, it's improper place, this
is just about the, we're back
on 9A. We're back on A when we
get to 19G, we'll get there. So
19A is the budget itself. Are
there amendments to be made to
the budget? I actually have one
Well, let's start with One,
that's actually addressing the
hearing aid issue, however. It
is tied to the budget because I
want to put the money into
enable, which is part of the
budget through the outside
appropriations, so here's the
motion. I move to amend
ordinance number 26-830, City
of Huntsville, annual budget
for fiscal year 2027 by
increasing under agency
appropriations, the amount
assigned to enable Madison
County in Perenz Casa by 150.
$0,000 for a total
appropriation of $170,000. The
the source of said increase
shall be a reduction in the
same amount to the street
resurfacing budget that um.
That fund down to $13,850,000
from 14 million. Could you
repeat that last piece that it
would be helpful if we had
these in writing for and copies
for everyone. Do you have that?
I moved to amend ordinance
number. 26-830, City of
Huntsville annual budget for
fiscal year 2027 by increasing
under agency appropriations,
the amount assigned to enable
Madison County in Perenz Casa.
By $150,000 for a total
appropriation of $170,000.
Period. The source of said
increase shall be a reduction
in that same amount to the um.
Street resurfacing budget
bringing that fund down to
$13,850,000 from 14 million. Is
that reduction 150, the
5,050,000. To the resurfacing,
yes ma'am. Well, the amendment
has been to the budget has been
made by Mr. Meredith is there a
second? 2nd, 2nd from Ms.
Watkins. Is there any
discussion? Yes, um, Mr.
Meredith. Is it possible you
could move the, move funds from
another line item instead of
the street resurfing
resurfacing. Absolutely, if
somebody would like to make an
amendment on that and it passes
absolutely. Madam President. I
can still talk about what's on
the table, right? OK. Just for
clarification, there are 4
different Budgets that
constitute what we call street
resurfacing and, uh, but Mr.
Meredith had brought up, you
know, talking about dropping to
13 million. It's still net
result is still in the ballpark
of 22 million with all four
budgets. I just want to get
that clarification so somebody
may have heard us talk about 22
million earlier than the year
13, and they wonder. What's out
there and I just want to get
that on the record. If I can
address that, I am taking it
from um the 1990 Capital
Improvement Plan, uh, from
street resurfacing, the source
of the funds being sales tax,
that is the $14 million. OK. My
my only comment would be that
um we have a process by which
agency or appropriations are
made, it is an exhaustive
process. We have staff who
invent, who invest literally
months of their time in making
allocations to agencies. I
Sometimes question some of how
some of those allocations are
made, but I know they've
studied it out, so, um, I, in
deference to the staff, I don't
plan to support any amendments
that alter those appropriations
I have confidence in the staff.
If a council member wants to
change something, add money to
an agency's fund. They can do
it out of their improvement
funds. No, we have done it many
a times in in in in this body
we have changed those outside
appropriation fundings quite
often, UCP comes to mind where
we have taken money from one
that already had more than
ample funding and we have taken
it from an organization and
given it to UCP so this happens
all the time, so it's not, it's
not unusual. It is not
something that has no precedent
here. We do it all the time.
President, I, I, Mr. Hamilton,
seek some clarity and So How
much, how much the council
wants to appropriate to enable
and how much you want to put
towards resurfacing is
absolutely your decision. The
issue is there's no resurfacing
in the budget that's before you
right now. The resurfacing is
in the 1990 Capital plan, which
comes later in paragraph 20 so
I think just kind of process
wise what you'll need to do,
the amendment. For the item
that's on the table right now
or on the floor right now would
be to increase and enable
obviously Meredith, you've
expressed the intent to amend
the 90 capital plan later in
order to pay for that, but
there's, there's no resurfacing
in the item in 19 AA for you to
do the full, you'll, you'll
need two amendments in order to
complete the transaction is all
I'm saying. We'll need to come
back at 20C and amend the 90
capital plan in order to
complete the item that is
before you. I understand what
you're saying. I disagree with
it, but I'm not going to pitch
a fit over it and if you want
to, we'll do it in 2, but the
reason that um I did it the way
I did it is because Enable is
in the budget and we're making
a change to enable and um I
should cite the source of the
additional money, and that's
all I did was cite the source,
but you know if you want to
split it into two votes, we'll
split it into 2 votes, but I, I
don't think it's necessary, but
um. I've, I've. I've upset my
colleagues enough and I won't
upset them even further on this
The issue is I, I'm not arguing
for or against your thing. I
just, we've got to get it done
properly anytime we bring you a
budget amendment that moves
money from one fund to the
other. You actually do both
things in order to complete the
transaction. And so all I'm
saying is, yes, the general
fund for this transaction would
need to increase the
appropriation to enable in this
case. It would also need to
receive a transfer from the
fund 302 twenty0 at. 20C will
need to come back and amend it
to cause it to transfer the
money to fund 1000 is all and I
said I was comfortable with
that, so I mean, I don't know
why he had to repeat it, but.
OK. Are we ready to call the
question on this? Call the
question. Thank you. You You,
you. All in favor of No thank
you. I know you don't like
being corrected, but no, no,
I'm fine with that. So all the
time, yeah. To call the
question the question. I move
to call the question. Second,
All in favor of calling the
question aye, nay. No. Then we
will vote on the amendment as
it has been stated. All in
favor of Mr. Meredith's
amendment. Please indicate by
saying aye. Um, the state what
the um amendment is is to
increase. The amount to enable.
By 150,000, bringing it to a
total of 170,000. Which we're
gonna go down to 20C. No, that
will. With funding coming from
by reducing street resurfacing
from the 1990 Capitol plan to
20. No, the the way Mr.
Hamilton suggested doing it,
and I'm not going to split
hairs with him. The motion
would be to amend ordinance
Number 26-830, City of
Huntsville annual budget for
fiscal year 2027 by increasing
under agency appropriations,
the amount assigned to enable
uh enable Madison County in
parent. Vince Casa by $150,000
for a total appropriation of
$170,000. And then the other
part will get to under the sea,
I guess I should say that the
reason for this is to have
enabled. Cover, um. Assistance
with hearing AIDS, not
necessarily specific to tax
relief, and the reason for that
is state law does not, well,
state law precludes the city.
From Granting tax relief until
September 1 of 2027. Therefore,
anything we do along the lines
of. Enacting a one year tax
moratorium on hearing aid sales
tax really only has one. Month
of effective. Relief by giving
the money associated with it to
enable who already sponsors and
does tremendous work for the
hearing impaired in the they,
through their organization
would assist folks in. That
that are in need of hearing aid
Hearing aids. Thank you for
providing that additional
information. The question has
been called, and that means we
cannot have any more debate, so
we will vote on Mr. Meredith's
question. Uh, amendment, all in
favor of. Approving Mr.
Meredith's amendment, please
say aye aye, and he opposed nay
The amendment does not pass.
What other amendments do we
have to propose on the budget.
I would like. To amend the
ordinance number 26-830 city of
Huntsville annual year 2027 to
end the automatic renewal of
automated automated license
plate reader contracts and all
new cameras installations. And
all new, let me start over. I'd
like to move to amend ordinance
number 26-830, City of
Huntsville annual budget for
fiscal year 2027 to end the
automatic renewal of automated
license plate reader contracts,
and all new camera
installations and moving
forward all contracts and
camera installations must be
voted on by the council. Any
funds unused by HPD, we align
item HPD operating material and
supplies, um, that's in
parenthes 1,000-41-41110-515340
in parenthes by this action is
to remain in the HBD budget but
used for a different purpose.
It, it would be so helpful if
we could have that. For all of
us, there was a lot in there.
Let me, let me offer, may I
offer a Mr. Riley situation
here aside from uh the, the uh
Mr. Riley, if I can interrupt,
so that motion has been made.
We can't have discussion on it
until we have it on the floor.
We have a second from Ms.
Watkins. Mr. Riley, the concern
that I have is that we cannot
buy a budgetary motion alter or
amend existing contractual
obligations. We would need to
review any contracts that are
in place and if we wish to
terminate those contracts, we
should do course or under the
procedure that is provided in
the contract which we have
agreed and, and to which the
council has approved. And that,
that's just a, a point. I don't
think we can unilaterally
modify those contracts. Mr.
Meredith has made a saying
terminate them. I'm saying we
allow them to run their natural
course. All I'm saying is the
automatic renewal. I'm not
saying let's end all of our
contracts based on this. I'm
saying let them run their
natural course, but when it
comes time to renew That that
renewal or that installment of
a new camera has to require a
vote of the council. And that
doesn't have anything to do
with the budget. It that's,
that doesn't mean it's a budget
It's budgeting this item under
line 1,000-41-41110-515340.
It's in the budget. Does that
include the two license plate
readers you purchased with your
council improvement funds.
Actually it's 3. OK. And the
reason that was done was
because those communities asked
for it. Now the people are
saying they don't want it. That
is one of the ones that won't
be automatically. Renewed if
this passes. We have been told
by our attorney that that's not
that we can't do that because
those are existing contracts we
are legally obligated to
fulfill and no one and no one
is saying. Please, and again.
Thank, please, can we have
order in the chambers. It isn't
what I said. You, you're not. I
don't know if you're doing it
on purpose or or you just not
paying attention to what I'm
saying for whatever reason. I'm
not saying in these contracts.
I'm saying when they come up
for renewal, we should be able
to vote on them. Is there any
more discussion for Mr.
Meredith or regarding Mr.
Meredith's amendment. Any other
comments? All in favor please
indicate by saying aye aye aye,
and he opposed, no, no, no, the
amendment fails. Do we? You
will be asked to leave the
chambers if you continue to be
disruptive. Are you, are there
any other you again. What we're
asking for, for just for good
conduct. That's all we're
asking for is order and decorum
in the chambers if you're
welcome to stay, but any
outbursts are not going to be
tolerated. Are there any other
amendments anyone would like to
make to the budget, Ms. Watkins
amendments for appropriations
we can discuss that now, right?
Yes So, I moved to amend
outside agency appropriations
by increasing the amount to
community action by 250. They
had originally, they received
um I believe it was 175, they
were reduced by 250. The source
of said increase shall be a
reduction in the same amount,
bringing Wellstone down from
900,000,925,000 to 900,000, and
the reason why I'm proposing
that is because One. If
somebody can ask this question,
what is the impact of wells so
being reduced by 900 by 25,000.
Yes, I did. You made your
amendment. Is there a second, a
second from. From Mr. Meredith.
Your question, please. What is
the impact of Wellstone being
reduced by $25,000. Who would
you like to ask that question
of? whoever, you know, I'm not
only appropriations Committee.
I don't even know how they're
designated, how they're
assigned. I just need to
question and answer. That
probably would Mr. Hamilton, do
you want to attempt to answer
that? Yeah, sure, I, I mean,
I'll, I'll, I'll share, so you
know, Wellstone is one of the
agencies that receives
appropriations from a number of
different sources. The city is
only one of those, uh, in, in
the appropriate sorry,
appropriation process like any
agency, they submit, you know,
the general statement about
their mission and the things
that they'll do with it. I
don't believe that the, that,
that application goes to a
level of detail that could
precisely answer your question.
I think it's a valid question.
It's just that the information
they provide us doesn't break
their budget down to that level
of detail to say, OK, this
25,000 will cut this program or
do those things. They have
built an overall budget and uh
and the 9250 contributes along
with lots of other monies from
the state and federal and also
some of their earned revenues
as well, so it's a, it's a big
budget, but I don't think that
we could precisely tell you. At
what what they may not be able
to do because of the 25,000. OK
thank you, Mr. Hamilton, um,
one of the reasons I'm asking
community action to receive
that 25K back is because 96% of
Community action funds go to
the community. They help people
with their utility bills and in
some cases, um, rental
assistance, but I think this
particular fund is utilities
and another reason I'm asking
that is I did a little digging
and found out that. Wellstone
had a net profit of 7.6 million
or increase of 22% and I don't
see how an agency that had a
7.6 million profit, net profit
increase would miss 25,000 from
an agency that helped keep
people's utilities on.
Utilities has risen. They have
risen high. And I don't see why
we would cut this agency out,
but we increased Wellstone.
That concerns me and to address
your your comment, Miss
Robinson, when you said the
agent the employees here, they
bring this budget to us and
we're supposed to vote on it.
We count on them to do their
job. We do count on them to do
their job, but the people
elected us. And we have to
answer to the people and I just
don't understand how an agency
that has a $7.6 million dollar
profit. Needs $25,000 that,
well, can't afford $25,000 to
come out of their account and
go to an agency that help our
uh the people that cannot
afford their utilities, income
income, and I don't think you
understand what this rising
cost of gas, $4 a gallon. Last
winter we had people lined up
complaining about their utility
bills. Imagine gonna be like
this winter. Costs have not
decreased, they have increased,
so I'm asking my council
members to consider. I know
some of you have already told
me you made your mind up,
you're change no appropriations
but when somebody has a $7.6
million dollar profit and you
don't want to give the
community action 25,000 out of
their 925,000, that concerns me
Questions or comments regarding
Ms. Watkins' amendment Mr.
Mayor Battle, a little clarity
in the in this because as we go
through this, uh, Wellstone is
our, um, nonprofit that helps
with um with mental health and
mental health is one of the key
issues that we watch in our
community on a day to day basis
mental health affects the
homeless. It affects people who
are single. It affects
everybody across the board and
there are lots of people who
need help with mental health,
uh Wellstone provides. Free
mental health, uh, care in many
cases if someone doesn't have
insurance and doesn't have a
way to um to pay for it, uh,
and we, we felt that this was a
full committee sitting there
that went through all those. I
was not on the committee, but
the, the feeling was that
mental health, we needed to do
everything we could to provide
for mental health in our area,
um, whether it's mental health
there or whether it's uh um in,
in another place, we as a
community. recognize that, you
know, mental health affects our
law enforcement affects our
police. It affects our
workforce, it affects, uh, what
we have to do with the homeless
and, and that was the reason
that we, we funded them at the
level that we did. Thank you,
Mayor Battle. Any other
comments or questions? One
comment is Wellstone the only
mental health agency in the
city of Huntsville, Madison
County, because there's several
other agencies that could have
been funded as well. It seems
like Wellstone has monopolized
on the industry and we don't
want to take any funding away
from them, and that's not right
Do you have any other comments?
All in favor of the amendment.
Please indicate by saying aye
aye. And he opposed say no, no,
the amendment fails. Are there
any other amendments anyone
wishes to bring? I do. I have
another amendment. Pretty sure
this one won't pass. I moved to
a men outside 1 agency
appropriations by adding United
cerebral palsy and increasing
amount assigned to them to
40,000, the said increase shall
be a reduction in the amount to
ability plus bring that fund
from down to zero from 40,000.
And the reason on the floor. Is
there a second? 2nd, Ms.
Watkins, continue. And the
reason why I proposed it is
United Cerebral palsy was
written out of the
appropriations budget. But
we're going to give Ability
Plus. $40,000. For them to do
some capital improvement. So
capital improvement versus
services for handicapped
individuals and also assisting
them with having mental health
counseling that they don't
charge them for assisting them
with having respite care
because when you're caring for
someone 24 hours a day that
cannot take care of themselves,
you do need a break. And I
don't I don't understand how we
wrote UCP out. And Roability
plus in um has assets of $1.5
million. They have fixed assets
of 2.6 million, Ability Plus
has 6.99 million in assets and
4.16 in fixed assets. Who needs
the money the worst. So, uh, I.
Just saying I don't see how we
write UCP out and give them $0.
Questions or comments, other
questions or comments? Well,
I'll comment that I totally
concur with uh Ms. Watkins on
that. Makes no. Um, you're
giving them a monopoly. If you
were. On the issue Thank you.
Any other comments on go back
to where we were when we went
through this, you know, ability
plus does group homes. They do
residential homes and they
serve more than 75 individuals
with intellectual and
developmental disabilities in
the city of Huntsville. those
type homes if you've ever been
to 805 or some of those type
homes they absolutely need
money. They're, they're always
running hand to fist, but
they're trying to take care of
those who can't take care of
themselves out in our community
And those uh and trying to get
them work out in the community,
but also giving them a place to
live independently even though
they have intellectual um and
developmental disabilities.
That was the reason we went to
A B T Plus, um, and you know,
there's there. I'm sure that
UCP is, is, is a great
organization. They, uh, Cheryl
comes and tells us all the time
all the all the things that
they're doing, but this one was
um, we felt like it was more
important because these are
people who have nothing.
Anybody else have any other I
do have. The very well for
individuals with disabilities
that are in these group homes,
not only that, we are going to
help repair group homes that an
individual owns or a company
owns and we are going to give
them money to do a capital
improvement plan when UCP
office Services direct to the
families and to the individuals
so I don't see how capital
improvement. Uh, Trump's.
Services. Any other comments?
All in favor of approving the
amendment, please indicate by
saying aye, aye, and he opposed
say no, no, no. The amendment
fails. Is there, are there any
other amendments? Are there any
other amendments? Then we have
a motion to table a final
consideration of 9A until we
have taken up 19A till we have
dealt with 19 B through. So
final vote. There are no more
amendments. The final vote will
then take place after the
conclusion of the others, so 19
everybody clear on that one.
19V is an ordinance amending
ordinance number 89-79 to
provide all eligible employees
of the city of Huntsville, a
cost of living adjustment, as
reflected in the first pay
period in the fiscal year 2027
budget effective October 12,
2026. Is there a motion to
approve motion for Mr. Little.
Second from the chair. Miss.
Smith has made the budget
presentation, including the
cola, Ms. Smith, could you come
back up to the podium because I
do have a question about this.
So just to just to clarify, we
heard earlier the comment was
made, we have a 2% CA. I think
you indicated it for an average
employee would be a raise of
1490 if I have the numbers
right, um, and the comment was
made that healthcare premiums
were going up 19%. This is
where you get into trouble when
you compare percentages on
apples and orange, uh, and that
would be $9009.60. For a family
plan for a family plan, so the
relative increase in the cola,
the 2% cola, to the relative
increase in the premiums is
really not comparable. It's a
very small dollar amount of
increase to the employee for
the less than $10 while the
increase is close to 1500. Well
the the the, the less the, the
9:26 is over 26 pay periods. So
by the time you multiply that
out, it's $250. So $250 OK, in
about 1490, 250 leaves you
12:40, I think I've remembering
my math correctly, just to make
sure we've got context for that
All right. Anybody have
questions or comments regarding
the cola? Oh, in fact I have
comments about Ms. Watkins, I'm
gonna read my statement. I want
to make sure we do not overlook
the rest of our city workforce
as we discuss compensation. I
support paying police officers
and firefighters competitively.
Their work is essential and we
need to recruit and retain
experienced public safety
professionals at the same time,
employees in sanitation, public
works, parks and recreation,
engineering, inspections,
administrative services, and
many other departments keep
pumps for operating every day
under the proposed budget,
eligible. employees will
receive a 2% cost of living
adjustment while certified law
enforcement and fire
suppression employees are being
considered for a separate
salary restructuring. My
question is not why are we
investing in public safety, but
whether have we adequately
evaluate the needs of the rest
of our workforce if recruitment
retention, salary compression,
and competitiveness are
coerns for one group, we
should determine whether those
same issues affect other
departments. We need to know
whether all city employees are
being compensated. it
competitively before making
these decisions, I would like
HR to explain how does the 2%
cola compare with the actual
increase in the cost of living
to include the healthcare and
when was the last comprehensive
compensation study conducted
for our non-public safety
workforce. This is not about
taking away anything from
police or fire. I want to make
that clear. I support you all,
but we got other people that
make this world go round up
here in the city, and it is.
About ensuring that we consider
and and support the entire
workforce. Would you like Mr.
Thomas to come up to so you can
ask specific questions can ask
specific questions Mr. Thomas.
Yes, Byron Thomas, director of
human resources. Councilor
Marvin Watkins, one of the
questions or issues you just
brought up is something that we
do on a continual basis. So
we're often asked by our
department heads as well as
employees to evaluate their
positions if they think that
they're doing something other
than what they are currently
assigned. So we'll evaluate
that and we make the
appropriate adjustments whether
the salary wise or titles, but
also we participate in other
surveys throughout the
community to make sure we stay
in alignment with our salaries.
Make sure they're competitive.
There are adjustments to some
departments because um we're
having a hard time recruiting,
you know, public safety has
been one of the ones where
especially with our police
department where we've had a
hard time getting new police
officers. So it has been
challenging and through the
mayor and administration and
council, we've done a great job
of trying to make sure we stay
extremely competitive with
those positions, but other
departments, you're right, all
of our employees are essential
to us and important to us. So
it's important that we have
evaluate them and we try to do
that, not just one time a year
but annually, working with our
department heads to make sure
we stay competitive. And I'm
quite familiar with it. It's
sort of like desk audits
position audits, and from time
to time I noticed, you know, on
the agendas we have positions
that are reclassified, but I'm
talking about overall, and I
think I, I asked that before Mr
Hamilton and I was told that it
hadn't been done overall for
everyone is done as a
supervisor might come to you
and say, hey, can you evaluate
this position? I believe
they're doing more than what
they. normally too. My thing is
we're giving 2%. To employees
and I'm not fussing at you,
Miss Thompson. OK, I'm just
making statements because
people get nervous, um, we give
a 2%. Two employees when we
have had rising costs. For the
last 4 years, rising costs and
right now gas is at an all-time
high. $4 a gallon. And I'm
concerned about the employees
like the sanitation workers, uh
our clerical workers, our lower
paid workers, 2% to them is not
gonna be much. And that's my
concern, and I know you have no
control over that, but just
canceled us. And so I'm just
saying 2% is not enough for the
employees, and I'm not saying
that to you, Mr. Thomas. 2% is
not enough for the employees,
mayor and council members. Does
that conclude your comments? Mr
Oh, Mr. Meredith. What would
the impact be if it was a 3%
code. I'm going to defer to our
finance director on that with
the numbers. Thank you. 2.1
million. So each percent um
according to our figures right
now would be $2.2 million. And
what is the impact of the
police and fire shift. That I,
uh, I mean. So as proposed
approximately 1.6 million. OK.
Thank you. I'd like to make a
motion to change the cost of
the cola from 2% to 3% increase
Second, I. From 2%, so the
motion is to amend to For a 2%
to 3%. How do you How would,
how would you propose to fund
that additional 2. I've been
told earlier that I needed to
wait till we got to where the
money was coming from. Um. All
in favor of Mr. Meredith's
amendment, please indicate by
saying can we do a roll call
vote. Roll call vote on on Mr.
Meredith's amendment. Mr.
Meredith, vote. Mr. Kling No
advance notice, so I vote no.
Mr. Little? No.. Watkins, yes.
The chairboats no, so the
amendment does not pass. We're
back to the main motion, which
is the consideration of the 2%
CLA, Mr. Thomas, could you come
back up to the podium, please.
Um, if I might, Madam, Madam
President, um. Mr. Bell. You
know, We weren't happy with 2%
when we had to fit it in the
budget, but this is, this is
one of the first years that
you've seen our budget be
somewhat constrained and and it
was constrained because of, uh,
SSUT, uh, which cost us $40
million this year. It's much
it's easier to be on the other
side when you have the money to
We've had to be very, very
cautious with the, with the
dollars that we have this year
and I think part of. This
budget is is pretty cautious
with our our dollars, but it's,
um, nobody's ever, you know, I,
I wish we could pay everybody
everything, uh, because they do
a great job. We have great
people in the city who do a
great job day by day by day, um
but when it comes down to it,
you have to make a decision in
that budget decision is how do
we, how do we, uh, fund, fund
our city and make sure that our
city can move forward and
actually do what it has to do.
And with this 2% cola, which is
um, we wish but it's 2% and and
it does provide for us, you
know, we, we're usually a 2 and
3%, uh, type of increase as we
go along because I don't
believe in going up and giving
everybody a 5% and the next
year give them a 0. I, I like
to make sure that we keep it
moving and going up, but um
It's, it's never um I, I wish,
I wish I could say that we
always have enough. Mr.. sorry,
thank you, Mayor Battle. Um, uh
Mr. Thomas is this 2% cola the
only increase our employees
will have this year. With
regards to salary, yes, but we
will have an increase as has
already been stated with
regards to our health insurance
premiums. Our premiums will
increase at 7% but Ms. Smith
has done an excellent job of
explaining if you look at the
average salary for our
employees, with a 2% cola
compared to a 7% increase, it
is um significantly more on the
salary as well as opposed to
the increase on our premiums.
I'm sorry, I didn't ask my
question clear enough Is it the
only salary? Increase our
employees will get during the
year. I, I follow you. Those
that are eligible also get step
increases as well, yes ma'am.
And there are for years of sort
of merit, there's a, there's a
third one in there somewhere
also. My point being that cola
is not the only longevity.
Longevity pay as well, yes,
ma'am. Yes, so, so the cola is
not the only increase that
employees get, and so, it
averages out depending on what
what step you're, what step
you're at or whatever, that
it's, it's somewhere in the
neighborhood of 5%. It could
potentially, yes, ma'am. Thank
you. Just to make that for
clarity, it could potentially,
but what is it on average? I
mean, varying steps, anywhere
can be 3%, 2%, 1%. So, and then
when you add a 2% color, so it
could be 5% on some, it could
be 3% on some, it just depends
on where they are within the
STEP system, OK. Thank you, sir
Yes. Any other comments? Uh,
we're back to the main motion,
um, all in favor, please
indicate. Could you read it? An
ordinance amending Ordinance
Number 89-79 to provide all
eligible employees of the city
of Huntsville cost of living
coal as reflected in the first
pay period in the fiscal year
of 2027 budget effective
October 12, 2026. All in favor,
please indicate any opposed.
The motion carries. Thank you
all for your work on that. We
will now go to 1919C is an
ordinance amending chapter 2
administration Article 7
departments, department heads,
and other appointed officers of
the code of ordinances of the
city of Huntsville, Alabama.
Move motion from Mr. Little.
Second from the chair. Can we
get an explanation of this? Mr.
Hamilton, would you like to
walk us through, um, The
changes being made here in the
organizational structure that's
being proposed. Council members
this is the 2nd presentation
you tell at the work session,
so just, uh, go back through.
Um As you recall, the first
slide just shows the way, and
I'll just kind of build it
quickly uh to get to it, how we
are currently organized. Uh And
the next slide really kind of
shows you what is being
proposed to change. It is a
combination of amending some
existing positions as well as
creating new positions. So this
reflects those things that that
were, you know, so the previous
slide is how we're currently
organized this slide, what,
what you see so far is all of
those things that are not
changing and affected by this.
I do, you know, reminder, the
one, the one thing I
highlighted in yellow there
obviously looks different. That
was just to give you an
understanding of the concept
that we've recommended to move
towards over time so that
position just shows an intent
for a future concept that is
not in this current ordinance.
So the first the first item is
uh director of economic urban
development, that is a position
that currently exists and the
ordinance before you would
amend some of the duties
associated with that position.
And then these are the
departments that would our
supervised and provided
oversight by that position. And
then this would the before you
would create and so that's why
I highlighted a different color
is a new creation of an office
that a new position, the
position of senior director of
engineering. Both of those
highlighted in bright yellow
are pieces of structure, an
office and an individual
position. And then the three
departments that be supervised
by that position. The green
check mark, so this is also a,
a component of this as we
talked about during the work
session is to continue the
process of getting our
organizational structure fully
codified in the code of
ordinances. They all exist by
some number of prior ordinances
uh, but the intent is to
modernize that and get into the
code of ordinances where it's
much easier to find and
understand. So the ones in
green check marks are the ones
where we've completed that
process, though some of them
are being amended by the action
tonight. So first is a position
that exists in currently exists
in the office of the mayor.
It's currently titled External
Affairs Officer. The proposal
before you would change the
duties of that position and
therefore also affect the title
so that the title would would
be converted to external
affairs and industrial
recruitment officer. The
multicultural affairs Office,
that is one as we just
discussed before y'all, not too
long ago passed an ordinance
that changed the title to that,
uh, but as I noted, we
discovered we did not do it in
a way that actually got it into
the code of ordinances. So
tonight is really just an
administrative clean up taking
what you've previously done and
just getting it into the code
of ordinances. Then you would
create that office, as I've
mentioned before. And create
that position, the senior
director of engineering. And
amend the duties of Director of
Econ Urban Development. We also
would codify the city
engineering department, as I
said, it, it already exists and
it's already functioning, but
it's not in the code of
ordinances in this format, so
this action would add that
department. As well as codifies
the position of the city
engineer, which is the
department head or the director
over that department, and do
the same thing for the
community development
department. It would codify
that existing department and
codify the position the
department had Director of
Community Development. And so
those are the actions that are
before you as we were
discussing earlier what what
this particular thing does is
creates the position and the
duties associated with it and
it creates those departments as
noted here and of course amend
some existing ones that are
already in the code. Obs
discussion about, OK, what,
what do the, the individual
positions associated with these
things, what are their salaries
that is actually partially
addressed later on your agenda
at 19F and so we'll get into
that specifically. So this
particular action has no
payroll related piece to it,
but it's sister ordinance in
19F is what would establish the
grade. It's like gives the
range, and I know that's one of
the things we want to kind of
talk about what is the range of
the payroll that goes with
those. Answer that that that
earlier questn that was kind
of tabled. I'm, I'm happy to
answer that whenever y'all
think that's appropriate, but
the specific ordinance action
that addresses that is what's
at 19F which will come later.
So council members, do you have
questions regarding the
organizational structure. Again
this is not about grades. This
this is just about the
organizational structure,
comments, and I might say this,
this was done um Because of
Shane Davis right there. Uh, we
have to replace Shane with 2.5
people is what what we've kind
of come up with, um, you know,
there's, there's gonna be a, uh
or, or director of economic and
urban development is going to
also be the recruiter for
residential and for retail, uh,
trade. The only way that we can
work our way up to where we can
get back where we need to be in
budget wise is bringing in more
sales tax and a part of, part
of their job. as director of
economic and urban development
is to work on the retail trade
and the residential trade, uh,
the office, uh, the External
Affairs and Industrial
recruitment officer is working
in legislatively, uh, in fact,
he was very, he was
instrumental along with uh with
engineering and with other
departments and bringing $10.8
million in, uh, last week or
just this week for resolute way
And uh then our city engineer,
of course, uh, Kathy Martin has
held that, uh, done a great job
with the that. She, uh, and
we've got somebody, somebody
new coming in there. So we've
got new people coming in at
this point with the, the
structure that we have today is
the same structure we had in
1984. Ralph Gibson and um and
uh Dallas Fanning were the 22
people who, uh, ran each side
of the government and
everything. else, and that's
the same plan that we had in
1984. This takes us to 2026 and
gives us a little bit more room
uh, for these guys to be able
to breathe and do the things
that they need to do, guys and
girls and ladies, uh, so that
we can make sure that we're um
uh we have a, a government that
can respond to the people and
respond to the needs that we
have today. Council members, do
you have questions regarding
this, the structure of this.
Organizational chart here and
Uh Anything specific, Ms.
Watkins, Mayor, I appreciate
those comments, but, um, I've
been on the other side of the
coin. Where people have been
transferred into jobs. That I
was qualified for and
overlooked for. And when I say
it's not a good feeling, it's
not when you had an education,
you had the experience and they
bring somebody in and overlook
you. Not only that, shame on us
for letting Shane Davis do 2.5
jobs. We don't work you out the
door. So I do have comments.
Mayor has several questions
regarding the proposed
organizational changes and keep
in mind, a lot of you don't
know, I, I emailed the mayor
prior to this meeting a couple
of days ago and respectfully,
Mayor, I wasn't satisfied with
your comments, um, particularly
the new positions that would
have responsibilityilities
involving governmental affairs
and industrial development.
First I'd like to understand
the process. If we are creating
a new position with significant
responsibility Possibilities
was the position not advertised
or opened through a competitive
process so that qualified
internal and external
candidates could be considered.
Second, because this position
would have responsibilities
involved in development. I
would like to understand what
qualifications and experience
have been established for the
position we currently have
professionals within our
planning, planning, economic
development operations who work
directly involves planning,
long range development, and
economic development. Were any
of those employees considered
for this opportunity before I
vote to create a position, I
believe councilors should
understand the financial
obligations associated with
this position. What is the
proposed salary range? What is
the anticipated salary? What
will the cost be to the city
when salary and benefits are
included and where is that
funding contained in the FY 27
budget. I'm not questioning
anyone personally, and I'm not
questioning the, I, I am
questioning the process. If
council approval is necessary
to create the position, then I
believe council should have the
information necessary to
evaluate the position before,
not after we approve it. I
would therefore like to
understand why. salary
information. Well, I now we can
talk about it. Now, if we're
approving this position tonight
we're going to prove the salary
as well, then, um, I wanna say
this before anybody gets
offended. This is not targeted
at the individual that's been
selected. It's about the
process. I've been in this
position for I'm in this
position right now. Where I see
people walking in the door with
no experience and people want
you to train them and they
don't have the experience and
they don't have the education
or the background, but they get
the position. It has to be fair
across the board. We can't just
pick people because that's who
we want to go into the position
These positions should have
been advertised. Those are my
comments. Now, Ms. Watkins, are
you asking about specific
individuals who are going into
these positions or or the, or
the organizational structure
itself if I say their name, I
think we would have to go into
executive session because of
the name and good character and
I would not want to say an
individual's name on this
microphone. I'm not trying to
degrade anyone. I'm just asking
questions about the process
that the positions were not
advertised Mayor Battle. You
have, you have not yet hired
anybody to fill these positions
Is that correct? This is simply
a consideration Robinson, don't
do that. Don't do that because
you already know we been to his
office and he done told us who
he wanna hire, so don't do that
don't act like you don't know
because you do. All of us did
our 2 21s. We went to the
mayor's office and he told us
who he wanted for these
positions, but I'm not gonna
say these people's name on the
microphone. Because that would
be disrespectful to them. I
have that much respect, but you
know Ms. Robinson, don't act
like you don't know. What I'm
saying is that's not part of
the ordinance that we're
considering, Mr. Hammill. I, I
think the part of, part of the
issue is that the, the kind of
the answer to the question in
terms of a process of filling a
position is, it varies. Not all
of them are the same, and let
me explain what I mean by that.
So some of the positions that
or or the the senior director
of engineering is a brand new
position. So obviously at the
moment you create it, it's
vacant and the mayor then has
to come back subsequent to that
to appoint somebody. The city
engineer is we've been notified
that Ms. Martin is currently in
that position, so it's not a
vacant position, but she's
notified us that uh that she's
departing and also, you know,
the mayor could contemplate to
move her to another position.
That's again, that would be an
appointment. So if, if she
moves to another position that
becomes a vacancy and then the
mayor would have to appoint a
backfill into the city engineer
OK? The community development
position there is already a
director of community
development. What we're really
doing there is just codifying.
That is not a change. That
position is already filled, and
there's there's nothing really
changing about it. The external
affairs industrial recruitment.
What's really happening there,
obviously it's, it's a little
bit different because it's an
appointed position, but it's
also very similar to what
happens during an audit, so we
have a person in a particular
position and the duties
associated with that change. We
audit and then, you know, Mr.
Thomas brings you that and you
approve it and so it gets a new
may get a new title, a new
grade, whatever it may be, but
the position's already filled,
so it does, it's not a vacancy,
it's an amendment to an
existing field position, and
that's what is proposed to. N
is an amendment, a change in
some duties and a change in
title to a position that is
currently filled now because of
that process and because it's
an appointed position. The
mayor still has to you to
effectively he wants to keep it
filled by the same person who's
already there. He has to go
through a reappointment process
that would come back to you on
a resolution along with any new
appointments that he does, so,
you know, part, part of, part
of, I think the answer to the,
the discussion is that not. Not
all of these are the same
because they're they're a
little bit different situations
So in that particular case, you
know, the mayor has to go
through a reappointment process
that he brings back for counsel
consent at a later date, OK? I,
I don't think he addressed the
issue of why these jobs weren't
posted. But Because the
positions haven't been created,
he talked about ones that are
filled, I don't want to hear
from you, um Mr. Mr. Meredith,
I'm going to ask you to to be
civil, how was that? I just
said I didn't want to hear from
him. He said, if you wanted to
hear from him, I told him I
didn't. Mr. Hamilton has a
microphone. He's the one
talking about it. He's the city
administrator. He knows about
this. He's are qualified to
answer the question than the
legal guy. It, it's not a
difficult question to answer,
so you know, for appointed
positions, the mayor has the
authority to appoint. The
person he wants to put in that
position, OK, and. Every single
one is considered differently.
Oftentimes I'm sitting in his
office and we're talking
through what's the best way to
fill this, this new vacancy in
many cases there is somebody on
staff already that's highly
qualified and he believes is
the right person and so he
brings you that appointment, OK
? Sometimes there's not
somebody internal or there's
multiple people internal and he
interview everybody who is
deemed to be qualified and then
he makes a selection and he
brings you that appointment.
There's also cases where we
actually advertise We we say we
don't believe anybody on staff
right now is qualified or we
think that that particular
position, given its nature, is
best selected through a more
competitive process, a more
open, broad process like we do
merited positions and so we
will advertise the same way we
do a merited position, but But
at the end of that process, the
mayor still selecting who he
believes is best qualified and
appropriate for that position
and bringing you the
appointment that's the, the,
there's a difference between
appointed positions and merited
positions. They also have
different protections around
them. All of us that are
appointed officials serve at
the pleasure of the mayor, and
we serve only for the term of
the mayor and so there's,
there's differences between the
nature of an appointed position
versus the merited positions
that have under the law
absolute certain rights to
their positions and a lot of
rights that are protected by
city ordinance that this
council establishes, but
ultimately whether the mayor
does it through some sort of
broad interview process
external to the organization, a
more narrow interview process.
In terms of the organization or
has figured out that's the
right person for the job, he
ultimately brings you an
appointment for your
consideration, and so that's,
you know, there's a mixture of
answers in these particular
cases and in more recent cases
as well as the way in which the
mayor has chosen his, his
appointee. Well, I, I, I, I get
all that and you know, I
understand he's got that luxury
but when the chief of police
was named, there was a job
description when other people
who are appointees Or are
presented before the council,
particularly in the 221s that
Miss, uh, uh, Watkins mentioned
earlier, there's a job
description. There's no job
description, at least that I'm
aware of, for senior director
of engineering. There's no job
description for external
affairs and industrial
recruitment office or officer.
There will be, so there's
there's, there's kind of two
things that occur here. So what
happens in the code of
ordinances, is, you know,
what's, what's on the document
tonight for your consideration
are the the duties. That's only
A portion of what we call the
blue sheet. Oftentimes, you
know, amongst the employee, the
parlances, the blue sheet
because the, the HR prints it
out on a legal length piece of
blue paper, and it is the same
duty description that you see
tonight, but then it also
includes specific
qualifications and some other
administrative kind of things
on it, so. Absolutely there
will be a blue sheet for every
one of these positions. It
contains a lot more data that
HR puts into it beyond just the
here are the duties of these
positions. So what's before you
tonight is, you know, do we
need one of the examples, city
engineer, and what will be the
primary duties of the city
engineer. That's what's on this
document. That does not
ultimately end up that, that
plus a lot of other information
is what results in the blue
sheet when a position gets
advertised or we notify people
the basic duties. thank you for
that explanation, but it, it
sure. Lends itself. To a sense
of certain people are being
favored for very high paying
jobs that's the appointment
process that the mayor has to
come back to you later. At this
point, he can't bring you an
appointee to a position that
hasn't been created, so you
gotta create the position
before he can appoint somebody
to do that, but you know,
saying that we have this tight
budget, but yet we're going to
split Shane's job into 2.5.
Well, you're you're, you're,
you're adding 1.5 additional.
People at that salary and
that's what the mayor's gonna
propose. Well, I mean, assuming
he sticks with the right now
the concept for the
appointments that he's to
discussed with you all
previously. That's not the way
the numbers actually play out
because there's multiple other
positions. There's also some
positions that go vacant
because of it. So when you,
when you put them all together
in the net, uh, while it is a,
a bigger number, it's not as
big as it seems like you might
be contemplating the one that
isn't going to be filled is
director of. City services. The
deputy director of economic
urban development, uh,
currently filled would go
vacant. And some of the other
fills come in at a lower salary
than the incumbent. So that's
why I say in the net when you
put multiple positions together
the current cost to the city of
those those groups of employees
The number is bigger in the
aggregate, but, but not as much
as uh. As much as you think. Um
well, I look forward to seeing
the numbers to verify that um
under the planning department
you have vacancy, um, isn't
that Mr. Nunes's position? No,
he is. So the reason I broke
out the three divisions that
are there is because those are
all also led by appointed
officials, so in general when
you say appointed official,
you're talking about a
department head, but there are
some exceptions. So for example
your director of communications
your multicultural affairs
officer. External Affairs
officer and those three
managers are also appointed
officials, and so the
abbreviation I have there for
long range urban planning,
that's Dennis Madsen, the
planning services is Thomas
Nunes and GIS is Amy Keenan. So
the three of them are managers
of those divisions. There is a
department head position, a
director of planning that has
been vacant for some time and
right now the mayor has not
contemplated filling that
position. Got you. Thank you
very much, Mr. Hamilton. OK Um,
Mayor Battle, I, I commend you
for. Taking an, making an
effort to adjust the
organizational Chart to reflect
the needs of a growing city. I
think that's what this really
is about. It's not about the
people. It's about. What we're
trying to accomplish here to
meet the city's needs. So thank
you for that. Uh, any other
comments? All in favor of Mr.
Mayor. I guess let's do it. In
two amendments, the first would
be to delete the external
affairs and industrial
recruitment officer position.
Mr. Meredith has made an
amendment to Can I ask a
question just to make sure we
understand what what's proposed
there, Mr. Meredith, are you
proposing to completely
eliminate the entire position
or to to not amend it and leave
it as it currently exists. Not
amended. Leave it as it
currently exists. OK. OK. Ah,
OK. So what that would do,
Madam President, that amendment
should be to delete. That
paragraph and I can grab it and
we can kind of figure out the
mechanics of it, but we just
need to delete that paragraph
from this particular ordinance
amendment, and that would leave
what exists already in the code
unchanged if if counsel were to
approve that amendment. Thank
you for clarifying that, Mr.
Hamilton. Is there a second?
2nd 2nd for Ms. Watkins. Any
discussion or questions. All in
favor of Mr. Meredith's
amendment to the organizational
chart, please indicate by
saying aye aye aye and he
opposed no. The amendment fails
The next amendment would be to
delete the senior director of
engineering since No one's
going into it anyway. 2nd 2nd
for Ms. Watkins. Any discussion
? All in favor, please indicate
opposed? No, the amendment
fails. Any other discussion? Uh
let's go back to, uh, All in
favor of 19C. Please indicate
by aye aye, aye. And please
roll a roll call vote has been
requested for 19C. Mr. Meredith
how do you vote? I Why do you
always start with me? Because I
happened to look to my right.
You never looked to the left
with Mr. Little. Mr. Little,
how do you do? Ms. Watkins. Mr.
Kling, Maybe you ought to ask
Mr. Riley how he votes. Mr.
Clank. If he was a council
member. Mr. Kling Mr. Meredith,
nay. And chair votes aye and
19C passes. We'll move on to
19D. 19D is an ordinance
amending ordinance number 89-79
classification salary plan
ordinance for the addition of a
public safety salary schedule
to provide pay rates for
certified law enforcement and
fire suppression positions. Is
there a motion to approve
motion for Mr. Little is
seconded by the chair. Mr.
Hamilton. Councilor, what's,
what's before you, uh, in this,
this slide set I here is
exactly the same one that we
showed at the work session, but
what's before you is a proposal
to amend the current salary
schedule for our certified
police and fire suppression
personnel, uh, you know, for
clarity, both of those
departments have a number of
other civilian positions that
don't fall into that category
and so uh I want to be very
clear that this only applies to
those positions that are
specifically certified law.
enforcement. So that's in
grades 14 through 20 or
certified fire suppression
personnel, and they fall in
grades 13 through 20 as well.
The ordinance specifies the
specific positions and so you
see those listed out in the in
the ordinance. Uh, you know,
the, the things that we took a
look at was, you know, kind of
looking at how our salary
structure, uh, compares to
surrounding departments and
where, where do we see
ourselves being competitive and
consistent with the general
salary structures in those
departments and where are we
inconsistent? So seeking to
address those things. One of
the, one of the challenges in
this process because obviously
our salary schedules. Structure
is, is fairly complex in the
manner in which employees move
through that can be fairly
complex is understanding that
we're trying to build a salary
structure one that makes sense
of what you want to do in terms
of incentivizing employment and
retention amongst folks that we
haven't even hired yet, so
thinking of someone who may
come in as a brand new employee
and how they will progress
through their careers. Because
what you're setting is the way,
you know, someone who's will
not here yet but will spend the
next 25 or 30 years with us,
but also that addresses some of
the, the issues that we have,
particularly as it relates to
compensation or retention for
our existing employees and
trying to balance those two
things, it would be easy to
really, really focus on one or
the other and throw the whole
thing out of balance. And so
it's really trying to find kind
of a happy medium to where
you're you're making sure that
you have something that makes
sense for both both of those
categories of current and
future employees. We found in,
in general our entry level and
and early career salaries were
pretty competitive, but
mid-career advancement was
falling behind, basically
slower than what we saw in some
of those surrounding agencies
and then also just the ultimate
top out was lower than
surrounding agencies and so you
know for for those that may not
be familiar, our salary
schedule a position as great as
say a 13 or a 14 or a 15.
That's their grade, then
there's step 1 through 25. And
so, as Mr. Thomas was talking
earlier about, you know,
compensation, you know, every
year unless unless something
occurs to actually disqualify
someone from their step
increase, which is actually
pretty rare circumstance. They
on their anniversary of their
hire date get a step increase
that progresses them up until
they get to step 25 and then
they're topped out. So you'll
hear that term topped out
meaning they're at the highest
for the particular grade
they're in. Obviously if they
get promoted then they get a
raise. associated with that
promotion a move to, you know,
wherever they fit on the salary
schedule. In most cases, then
start progressing back to the
top out at that new higher
grade. So the positions
affected and as I said before,
range in grades 13 through 2013
is specific to firefighters. 14
is your entry level for police
officers, but then there's also
other positions associated with
the grade 14, and you see all
the way down through the deputy
chiefs, both of our chiefs of
police and fire are appointed
positions, and they are not a
component of this. It's only
addresses the merited employees
in grades 13 through 20. So
when you see my errors are
messed up there in the
PowerPoint, uh, in this version
but really what we're doing so
right now firefighter is a
grade 13. There's lots of
employees in the city that are
grade 13, not just firefighters
but what this does is for those
positions that we listed
earlier splits them out and
creates a new grade labeling
within our payroll system of
13% and then 14% 15% on down.
It, it does, uh, because of the
way in which we build that
salary schedule and the way we
every, every year when there is
a CLA applied, the way we
construct those, it's important
that we keep grade to grade to
grade consistent with how it's
structured, uh, because one of
the things that uh that you
could do, I have people ask,
hey, how about doing a targeted
race for your firefighters and
your police officers and not do
anything for the people above
that. The problem there is if
you advance the lower grades
and not the higher grades, you
basically disincentivize
promotion, you know, why would
Someone seek higher
responsibility at a lower
salary, right? So you need to
keep them uh structured in a
way where as our our employees
get promotions that they're
incentivized to do so in terms
of compensation and they
actually get a raise by by
virtue of promotion, so a lot
of this is also making sure
that we keep the structure of
the salary schedule such that
they actually get a raise and
are incentivized to get
promoted, so it's important
that we do it all the way
through that rank structure.
And by keeping it aligned with
its kind of sister grade, so
keeping 13% and 13 aligned with
each other in a certain way,
and I'll show you how we
structured that allows us then
allows payroll to continue to
apply those those steps and we
keep them consistent with the
way in which we build those. Uh
The one of the things it does
because we are able to compress
some of the, some of those
earlier steps and accelerate
that mid-career step process
which gives us room to do an
extended model for each of
those positions and so it
continues to go out to a full
20 steps and therefore get to
the higher step, the higher
salary that we sought at the
top out. It does accelerate
some of the step-based salary
raises at the mid-career point
for those entry levels for
firefighters and police
officers, and one of the things
that, you know, we do
understand we have folks that
come in as firefighters and
that's where they want to be
and they don't seek promotion.
That's OK. They spend their
entire career as a firefighter.
They might spend their entire
career as a police officer, and
that's totally fine. We want to
make sure that that structure
of that salary incentivizes
them to come and be part of our
team, but then also that
compression at those grades
then have a positive. effect on
those who do get promoted
because it actually accelerates
them through the process as
well as they go through those
promotions because they will
have pushed further down the
steps schedule before they get
those promotions and just to be
clear, the way city policy is
and this is true for all
employees, not just police and
fire, when an employee gets
promoted internally, they move
from one grade to the next.
They, they get, uh, they get,
they move to that higher grade.
At whatever step gives him at
least a 5% raise grade. So if
they move one grade, so a
firefighter who goes to a
driver to the step at the next
higher grade that gives them at
least a 5% raise if you have a
police officer who goes to
sergeant, that's actually a too
great increase, so they would
go to a step that gives them at
least a 10% raise, and that's
the same policy that applies to
all of our employees, and so an
important part of the way the
salary schedule is structured
is so that those raises for
promotion are actually possible
and they don't just move from.
One top out to the next that
they actually have the
opportunity to get some
additional step increases when
they enjoy those opportunities
for promotion. What it does not
do, it does not alter the
relative grade level of any
position. It does not alter any
of the HR processes for
determining the grade grade
level process doesn't change if
our hiring standards or any of
the job descriptions. This is
purely a payroll action. This
is not affecting any of the HR
systems associated with these
positions. So the top line is
the full 25 step associated
with grade 13. I blew up the
bottom part so you can in
better detail, but one of the
things is already by ordinance,
and this is something that uh
that y'all did a few years ago
that did result in a
significant raise across the
entire police and fire forces
was setting the new entry level
at step 8. So let me explain to
you how that works. That's
another, you know, you'll talk
about, OK, how do, how do our
employees get raises throughout
the year, obviously. The Cola
is the quick obvious answer,
but then also their step
increase if they're not yet
topped out is the second answer
uh, but then also when new
employees come in at higher
than minimum, anybody who is
already in that like position
gets advanced as a result of
coming in. So that's what
happened here. So a few years
ago when y'all approved making
entry level step 8 for both
police and fire. That
immediately took every single
police and firefighter in the
city and advance them multiple
steps, and so they got a
significant raise by virtue of
that process so that we kept
all of them in their cohorts
aligned the way they should be
by step, OK. So they are step 8
for approximately 9 months till
they finish finish finish their
training, and when they become
certified, they skip over steps
9, 1011, and jump directly to
step 12. And then when they hit
their one year anniversary,
they jumped to step 13. And so
what we've done, what I put
below is just compressed, got
rid of all the steps that
firefighters don't use, and so
they come in at 8, go to 12 to
13, and then all the way out to
step 25. 1 of the challenges is
that they're getting topped out
on their 3rd. 14th anniversary.
So then for a typical 25 year
career, the next 12 years,
there are no step increases, so
that's why, you know, Mr.
Thomas and I both are quick to
say, yeah, every employee who's
not yet topped out gets a step
increase because once you're
topped out, all you're getting
is the cola, uh, associated
with, with what everybody gets.
And then the police this is uh
uh basically a repeat but just
that they're, they're grade 14
and so it's the exact same
process structuring, uh, for
them as we did for the
firefighters that you saw on
the prior slide. So they're,
they're similarly situated in
terms of those timelines and
steps, but because police
officers are one great hire. It
is a little bit higher salary.
And so there you see a current
13 aligned with the 13%. And so
just kind of how their career
would now progress on that 13
structure, they get to the top
out at their 13th, uh,
anniversary under the new
structure. These are how the
salaries line up. So everybody
right now, you know, because
one of the things I, I wanna be
clear, what we're, what we're
proposing tonight does not give
every single firefighter or
every single police officer or
race in November, right? So
what happens, here's what's
going to happen to our
employees with the approval of
the COA, every employee in the
city gets that 2% cola that
takes effect in October. Same
way it does every single year.
This ordinance then would take
effect in November, right? So
that gives time for payroll to
get all these new systems built
in place to make sure we get it
lined up properly, and then in
November it takes effect. But
what happens in November, a
firefighter who's currently a
step 12. Goes to the new step 2
but you'll notice it's the same
salary, OK, because this is
about really accelerating as
they're getting into their
mid-career. So at the 6-year
mark. What happens is we
actually this is the
compression we deleted what was
step 18, and so anybody who
hits their 6th anniversary
after this would jump what
effectively be a two-step
increase, OK. And that, that
jump right there, it should be
between 5 and 6%, just that one
That's just a step increase.
And then we shot a 2nd
opportunity for compression, so
at what was the step 21, we
delete it, so 10 year mark is
doing another two step increase
So what that. Gets them to is.
The current top out, which is
77,1126, and again these are
the FY 26 numbers with the COA
that y'all approved tonight,
those numbers will be bigger,
but with just using these so
you understand structurally
what we're doing. The top out
salary right now is 77,126 that
you get to at your
thirteen-year anniversary.
You'll now get to that same
number at your 11 year
anniversary, so it accelerates
getting to the current top out
number 2 years faster, but then
because we've been able to
extend the scale. They continue
to have additional steps that
otherwise they would never have
had. So under the structure of
the leaks today. And
firefighter gets to that 77,000
number and other than Cola's is
never moves off of that number
where now they will continue to
get steps beyond that top out
all the way out to a new step
25. And the way that lays out
career-wise, uh, is that we get
to that new top out at year 23.
So prior to retirement
eligibility, they're getting to
that high number and have the
opportunity to have the highest
possible number for the last 3
years which is kind of the way
it lines up with our retirement
system and the way you're, your
pension is. Uh, calculated. And
then this is exactly the same
police. There's no change. In
terms of the structure and the
timeline process, so I'll kind
of speed through this for you.
Now grades 15 through 20 are
all those who have gotten a
promotion. I will, let me back
up. Firefighters that come in
at 13, drivers are 14, so grade
14 is entry level for police
officers, but also is that
first promotion for a
firefighter into the into the
driver position and so then for
both sides 15 represents a
promotion and some physicians
go to the 15, like for example,
investigators, you might have a
police officer who wants to be
an investigator and they get
that one great promotion, but
those that want to go into
leadership positions and want
to jump to sergeant, it's
actually a two grade promotion
to 16, and, and I've just laid
out here for you what what
we've done here is it's lined
up as it's currently structured
so they all moved to the new
step where they at the same
salary, but now you have that
extended scale, so those and
most of your folks that are
promoted are approaching, uh,
the top out range now have
extended scale that they
otherwise would not have had.
And Go run through just a
couple of examples of some
folks of kind of what, what
they will look like in the near
term. So here's an example.
These are, these are actual
employees, obviously. I took
the names off just for, for
their privacy, but, uh, an
example of a current
firefighter who's a grade 13,
step 17, he's got 5 years of
service. We'll get the 2% cola
because of, because he's one of
the more junior folks, he's a
little bit away from that, that
two-step jump does not get a an
increase in November, but then
does get a step increase. In
December, which will represent
4%. So across that time frame,
uh, from today till till
January would be a 6% raise and
you see other examples there. I
kind of did a variety of grades
and years of service to give
you a sense of uh of what that
would look like. Council
members, questions for Mr.
Hamilton. Any questions? let
David go first OK thank you. I
have an amendment. Thank you.
Thank you for providing your
amendment in writing. to What I
can email it to you. All right.
We all on the floor and
everything and ready to amend.
Yeah, your motion, please. You,
you need to make your motion.
Yeah, OK, I make a motion to
amend proposed ordinance number
2683 as follows by amending
section 3A 15380033, you said
83. 0, excuse me. We'll start
over. Motion to amend proposed
ordinance number 26833 as
follows by amending sections
3.8 or excuse me.A.15 through
3.18 to read as follows. 3.8. I
want to say 83. A 15, step 25
employees with less than 17
years of service with the city
of Huntsville. Shall move to
step 15. 3. A 16 step 25
employees with 17 years of
service with the city of
Huntsville, but less than 19
years of service shall move to
step 16. 3. A 17, step 25
employees with 19 years of
service with the city of
Huntsville, but less than 21
years of service shall move to
step 17. 3. A. 18 step 25
employees with 21 years of
service with the city of
Huntsville, but less than 23
years of service shall move to
step 18. And by amending
section 3.A by adding the
following subsections 3. A19
through 3.213.819 25 employees
with 23 years of service with
the city of Huntsville, but
less than 25 years of service
shall move to step 19. 3. 20,
step 25 employees with 25 years
or more of service with the
city of Huntsville shall move
to step 2 3.A. for step
assignment calculation pursuant
to 3A. What is that, uh, 15-20.
Of this ordinance, years of
service shall be calculated
beginning with the in-service
date the employee began service
and the police or fire
suppression career field.
Second, the chair seconds the
amendment. I think Mr. Hamilton
discussions question Mr.
Hamilton. Got something to help
us. That. Damien, if you could
pull up the screen please. So
Michelle, thanks, thanks for
giving us a heads up on this
kind of working through because
uh, you know, as we talked
about in the work session, one,
we recognize that what's laid
out here is pretty complex, but
also changes that you might
want to make could, could vary
significantly in the potential
cost and so your amendment does
cost more money in the budget,
so first I want to make sure
it's. You know, that that was a
whole lot of words you read
there to amend this thing, uh,
and so this is this intended to
kind of summarize it so that
make sure we understand it and
if I, if I could, uh, back up,
there's really, there's two
major sections to the ordinance
that's in front of you. The
first section is creating the
new salary schedule and
defining the positions affected
by that new salary schedule.
The second section tells us for
the existing employees, what
step to assign them to in the
new salary schedule. And so the
only thing that your amendment
affects is that piece where we
assign those those employees
and more specifically for those
employees currently topped out,
OK? And so regardless of grade
at every single one of the
grades that we talked about
here, you have some number of
employees that are currently
topped out and so what this
does is provide A, a, a Higher
compensation for a number of
those. Let me explain what we
did there. So one of the
challenges you have with with
top down employees is in terms
of their years of service that
could, it can and, and in some
cases does range very, very
broadly. Um, All the way, as we
said, you know, our police and
firefighters get topped out at
their 13th year if they
continue to serve 35, 40 years,
then, you know, you've got
topped out employees in that
kind of range, so in our
initial proposal, the way we
sought to kind of separate them
into kind of into buckets by by
years of service is as you see
there and assigning them to the
3 steps, 1516, 17, and so what
Mr. Little's proposal does is
really. Find those makes those
windows smaller so that you you
more significantly recognize
those additional years of
service, OK, so, uh. That that
moves a lot of employees in the
current proposal that would
have been say step 16 or 17,
some of those will now go all
the way up to step 20, so it's
different on every individual
one of them, but what we've
done is kind of apply that.
Proposal to what's the
additional cost above what's
already in the budget, OK? So
to be clear, what the, the
increases that are proposed as
currently written are fully
baked into the budget, so the
additional cost of this change
is $720,000. Now I understand
you've communicated that you
have, you have a concept for
how you deal with that. We've
looked at it and it actually is
basically funded out of the
existing police and fire
budgets and so. Basically,
those two departments are
paying for their increases in
terms, in their, in their
operating budget, uh, but
that's something that will have
to be amended when you go back
to the budget in 19A because
that's where that action is, um
but we've looked at that, it's
executable, and so if it's the
will ofounsel that we that we
increase the compensation
package for for those folks
that are currently topped out,
this certainly doesn't and if
with the approval of your
amendment to the budget, then
you know it would be affordable
in that sense. OK, thank you. I
would like to if I can ask a
question, how are you going to
pay for it? It is basically
some expenditures that the
police and fire will have to
hold off until July of next
year. It's, it's specific to to
and, and, you know, uh, so both
of those departments were
provided new authorizations, so
over and above what they're
currently authorized today, and
Full year salaries were put
into the budget for those new
positions by delaying how long
they can fill those new
vacancies that frees up the
money to cover this. It does
not affect existing vacancies
and so they both have existing
vacancies that are already in
the authorization, so you know
hypothetical numbers, I don't
know the numbers off the top of
my head. Let's say that 50 and
80. Yeah, so, you know, let's
say, let's say that, you know,
the fire department currently
has authorized 100 people and
10 of those are vacant today,
then they would still have
those 10 vacancies and be able
to fill those 10 vacancies.
This new budget as as it's
currently written, starting on
10 October, they would have 5
new people, so they would go
from 100 to 105. We're saying
delay the hiring on those 5 new
It has no effect on existing
vacancies it's already working
to fill and so by delaying that
hiring you're saving, you know,
a portion. of a year of salary
and in the aggregate across all
those new positions, it is
sufficient to pay for this. Uh,
if you say so, it just. My
understanding is the number is
50 on field slots and the
firefighters and 80 unfilled
slots in HPD are unaffected by
this. But why are we holding on
to that that money if we can't
fill it. These, these, it's not
like This is those numbers.
Only occurred to this current
fiscal year. There was carryo.
And there will be carry over
into 2027, so how come some of
that can't be allocated towards
paying for this because there's
not carryover and the general
fund does not carry over but
also more specifically as it
relates to payroll, uh, not all
vacancies are fully funded in
the in the current year. So in
FY 26. The initial budget used
historical fill rates and, and
spending rates to decrement it
somewhat also as we went
through the year, we further
decremented that. So for
example, at the midyear, one of
the actions y'all took because
as we went through the mid-year
we saw that Parks and recs
payroll number was bigger than
it was going to need to be, and
other departments were short
and you actually moved that
money from Parks and rec to
other departments to fill the,
the void in those departments
and so there's Not an excess
payroll number at the end of 26
that you can roll over to 27.
This is specific to the 27
budget we budgeted for them.
Full salary for these new
positions by delaying their
hiring you free up that that
budget number to pay for this,
so discounting the new hires,
the number you gave 5 is an
example of the The money that
of the previous unfilled jobs
are essentially a slush fund to
pay for employees that um
departments that go over their
budget on employees call fund.
I mean, we laid out a budget
that we thought was the way we
could execute it, but a part of
why we, we do a mid-year review
with you and bring you
amendments is because sometimes
the revenue number is not
what's estimated or sometimes
expenses may come along, but we
may have somebody retire
unexpectedly, and there's costs
associated with that. So
there's always kind of
unanticipated costs in the
budget. The finance department
does what I think are good
models where it's generally
accurate, but you're always, I
mean, the reason we're
constantly bringing new
amendments is we're seeing
little changes that we need to
make in the particular case
this year. I was actually kind
of unusual, uh, that, that we
ended up in balance between
Parks and rec and the other
departments, but, uh, but also
because of some of the
vacancies, we're burning
overtime, so some we might have
budgeted straight salary number
that now because we're unable
to fill a position we've got to
use some of that to pay
overtime to somebody who's
filling the gap, so it's,
there's Hundreds of different
little examples like that that
are all in the aggregate expend
our budget, but there's not,
there's not going to at the end
of 26 when we close out the
books on 26th, there's not
going to be excess payroll
sitting there available to do
something else. Now, if there
was, I mean, if, if we in fact
underspend our budget, then the
city doesn't lose that money.
The money is still there and we
would bring you a budget
amendment if there was
something where we needed to
expend those funds, but in this
case what we're focused on
right now is that at the end of
all your process tonight, you
have a balanced budget. Uh, so
that we can move forward on a
balanced budget. We will
continue to do the quarterly
updates and the mid-year
reviews and things if we need
to, we're seeing things not
going exactly the way we
anticipated they would, and
then we've got to come to you
with solutions to that, but
what you know what my
discussion with Mr. Little is,
you know, this looks great, but
we got to have a way to pay for
it. And so we spent some time
kind of looking through what
some of those options were,
work with the chiefs, you know,
they, they both said, hey, we
need, we need to get those
authorizations into the
department. We talked through
the impact of delaying the
hiring. Versus being able to do
this and in a perfect world,
you do both, but we don't,
we're not in a perfect world,
as you know, and so we've got
to have a way to pay for it.
This is a suitable compromise
in order to shift resources to
be able to pay for these
increased raises for these
particular employees. Well, I'm
I, I think. I think it's um
Pitiful. That the city of
Huntsville forces police
officers to cover themselves
out of their own pocket. When
that police officer said he had
to pay out of his pocket to
have a colleague fill his time.
That should never happen. I
mean, why on earth are we
asking our employees to find
their own replacement and pay
out of their own pocket for
that replacement asking them to
I will have the chief look into
that situation, but if, if, if
that employee worked a private
arrangement with another
employee. I had. We, we'll look
into that situation. I, I took
the note just like you did, and
we will. Please get back to me
on that. I appreciate it. Thank
you, sir. not just just real
quick like to thank uh Penny
and her team for getting out
the pencils and calculators and
spreadsheets on this, and Mr.
Hamilton and Chief Giles and
Chief Mack for their
willingness to work with us on
this because we heard from a
lot of people in this range, a
lot of, I, I hadn't heard from
that many employees about
anything in a long time, you
know, so I really just
appreciate y'all being willing
to try to, I know, like we were
saying, there's nothing ever
perfect in our budget. Can't do
all we want, but I appreciate
the effort on everybody being
involved and I do want to be In
my presentation was kind of
just showing you how we
structure the salary schedule,
you know, our, our salary
schedule is showing you the,
the base pay and that the
number I just rather than
having all the hourly and
weekly wages I just showed you
the annual number. So for sake
of understanding how we're
structuring it, that, that is a
portion of the compensation for
an employee and a portion of
the overall cost, you know,
every one of our positions
costs the taxpayers' money. You
know, so if we have an employee
who's paid $100,000 the actual
cost is more than that because
of the benefits packages and
things like that, and so this
the 720 number is not just the
salary component of uh of this
additional cost. It's also the
FICA, the retirement
contributions, all those things
are also part of that number.
So that is the full, you know,
burden cost associated with
with this proposed change as
part of, as we've gone through
all of this looking at what are
the additional costs, we
sometimes, you know, focus on
that. That salary number that's
on the schedule and forget
about all the other costs that
go along with uh with having an
employee, so. Ms. Watkins,
you've been very patient. Your
comments? Oh, absolutely, um, I
do have a couple of comments,
um, spoke with a couple of
police officers and they're
disappointed because they were
expecting an 8% raise and part
of that was to bring them up
where they would be retained
because part of the issue we
have is they're leaving us
going to other agencies that
pay more. Not only that, um,
I'm a little bit concerned in
Mister. To, I appreciate you
working on this, but it's still
a little muddy. Because it's
not very clear and I think
what's going to happen is if we
approve this tonight, we're
gonna have to offer an
opportunity for. Police
officers as well as
firefighters to come to the
table if they get dropped off
and they don't get any kind of
movement with the steps.
Because it, it's. I think if
you're gonna find a couple of
people are not gonna get stiff,
and that's what they're they're
expecting and that's what
they're waiting for. So I'm
just asking, um, if they have
some issues or concerns or if
they don't get the step
increase if down at the table
with them and discuss this. I'm
happy to sit down and explain
it to any of them, um explain
it. If they're dropped off, if
they don't get a step increase,
where we sit down at the table
and talk with them. OK, sure,
thank you. I will say I've,
I've heard the same rumor that.
And where they started it
around an 8% raise. There was.
That that was never part of the
equation and I'm not sure why,
why internal to some of them
that that rumor got started
that was never in terms of what
we looked at was going to be
possible. 8% was never part of
the conversation, uh, just
because that, that again,
that's, you know, uh, well, you
know, I wasn't involved. I know
you weren't. No, I know. I'm
going was told, but we gotta
have a retention plan and. If
this does not address our
retention plan, we're gonna be
in failure mode. And that's
what we don't need to happen
have happen because I was so
shocked when the gentleman said
that North precinct is
shorthanded. I, I've never been
told that. And I would think
that if something like that
happened in my district. That
someone would tell me. I hate
hearing stuff on the street. I
I, I absolutely hate somebody
telling me something without
Administration just come to me
telling me. I know sometimes
you all might feel like, well,
we don't want to tell her
because of this, but I can take
the truth. I just don't want to
be blindsided. That's all. And
uh we have got to get a
retention plan in place and I
think that's something that
we're gonna have to work hard
on, um. The, the truth is
Madison County is getting a lot
of our officers. And we've got
to have a plan in place because
we're growing so fast. That
we've got to have officers in
place. Sure, and that's why,
you kno, so first of all, I
would tell you. Every component
of the police department is
below their authorized strength
OK. And so it's not just North
Precinct. All three precincts,
the investigative division,
every single kind of building
block of the department that's
got vacancy spread across it,
OK? And that's why a few months
ago we brought you a contract
for a consultant to assist with
recruiting, and that was a big
part of the conversation was
the fact that we are well below
authorization and so obviously
you and I have not sat down and
specifically looked at the
authorizations in detail across
those precincts, you know, the
reason we brought that contract
and thought that. was a good
investment specifically around
recruiting and around the
shortfalls that we have and so
that is absolutely the case, I
will tell you that there are,
there are some agencies around
us that have unlimited funds,
and we are never going to win a
bidding war with them. That is
just the reality of the
situation we're in. And so what
uh what we've brought is
Everything we can do
financially so we would love to
Give a bigger cola as the mayor
said earlier to all employees,
we'd love to do bigger raises
here every one of those, you
know, the challenge for you
then is, OK, then how do we pay
for that, uh, because the, the
budget has come to you balanced
to zero as it has, you know, it
has to be balanced. It can't go
to a negative. It's balanced to
a zero and so finding a way to
pay for those things becomes a
challenge. Would love to do
additional work here and if we
find a good source for that
funding, then those
opportunities are there. I
would say. say again, kind of
to the, the sort of a
conversation about the
complexity of this, uh, if
there's additional amendments
that counsel wants to consider
on this, we likely will want to
postpone it so that we can go
do the financial analysis and
actually tell you the cost, the
work to come to that 720 number
you see there was not
instantaneous. We had to get
kind of Mr. Little's intent and
go through some analysis and
the modeling to to come to that
number, so certainly would love
to hear other ideas. is for,
you know, for increasing this
further, but ultimately we've
got to find a way to pay for it
So, uh, happy to, happy to work
with you on any ideas that you
might have and explore what we
can or cannot do, and I, I
would like to give credit where
credit is due also, when Mr.
Little and I approached Mr.
Hamilton because we had been
getting concerns expressed to
us from police officers,
particularly senior officers
who had topped out, when we met
with him, he already had a plan
in place, but it was only going
to be, I think, a $200,000
impact. It was not as
aggressive as this. So when Mr.
Little shared with me what he
and Mr. Hamilton had continued
to work on, um, this, this, I
think tends to check more of
the boxes and particularly
impact retention of senior
officers who are investigators
and and others who who we need
to, need to encourage to stay
with us. So Mr. Hamilton, thank
you for being proactive. and
thinking through this and for
working to address the needs
the concerns that have been
expressed. I actually have a
question for Mr. Hamilton, I
too was surprised that the West
uh, precinct. For police isn't
staffed uh with the minimum
manpower necessary and you
mentioned paying for this, uh,
increase would be taken by
freezing the newly allocated
slots. The ones that have gone
unfilled prior to now are still
slots that can folks can be
hired into. OK. Thank you. Any
other thoughts? All right?
Everyone, uh, all in favor. of
approving the public safety
salary schedule as it has been
presented to us. Please say aye
aye. Any opposed? You mean the
amendment, right? Yes. Oh, I'm
sorry. You're right. You're
right. I'm sorry. I thought we
have been talking about this so
long I forgot where we were,
Don't don't worry, I got hung
up on uh the call, the question
and we had 3 votes, not 4. You
need 4 for it, so I understand
getting caught up in what's
going on because it happened to
me tonight as well in favor of
proving. The amendment as
presented by Mr. Little, please
indicate by saying aye aye, and
he opposed the amendment is
approved. We will now move back
to the main motion as amended,
all in favor of approving the
public safety salary schedule
as amended. Please say aye, aye
Any opposed? The motion is
approved unanimously. Thank you
all for your support. We'll go
now to the tricky. Your part,
and that is 19E. 19E is an
ordinance to amend Section 8.2
appointment rate of ordinance
4-315 personnel policies and
procedures manual. Jem to
approve, second by Mr. Little.
So this is where we need to
marry up that amendment. With
what's going on in E correct.
So as I said before, you know,
by ordinance. As it exists
today, police and firefighters
come in at step 8. We've now
realigned that to step one, and
so we need to correct that so
that they now come in at step
one, that's that's lined up
with this new salary schedule.
It also affects the way
laterals transfers come in and
so what you're doing now is
essentially just. Updating
those policies to align with
the new salary schedule, so
they're still consistent with
the process and the salaries,
but it's the step numbers
really that change. So 2020 was
amended. Are there amendments
that need to be made to make
20E work with we're, we're good
? OK, very good. It's not as
complicated as I thought it
would be, and it's 19. I'm
sorry. 19D was approved 19E is
what we're working on right now
so any comments, questions on
this? OK, all in favor, uh,
please indicate by saying I've
I've got. So you said that the
job posting isn't gonna happen
until the appointments are made
at least share it with us, is
that correct? Was in front of
you right now is related to the
police and firefighters. I
thought we'd had already passed
that. OK, sorry, so just back
up to make sure that everybody
understands. So what you just
did at 19D creates a new salary
schedule. There's a component
of the personnel manual right
now that specifies that police
and firefighters come in at
step 8, jump to step 12, the
kind of structure I showed you,
well, that, that is no longer
lined up with the new salary
schedule. So essentially you're
amending the policy about how
we bring in police and
firefighters and to align with
the new salary schedule. OK,
what I wanna talk about is F.
OK, thank you. Any other
comments? All in favor of
approving the ordinance in 19E,
please say aye aye, and he
opposed the ordinance is
approved. 19F is an ordinance
to amend ordinance Number 89-79
classification salary plan
ordinance motion motion from Mr
Little Second by the chair. So
this is the um. Actual
classification for the newly
created or renamed positions
that were introduced in 19B. Do
you, if you want, I can run you
through them, each one of them,
uh. Yeah, uh, let me just go
and sequence as they exist on
the ordinance. So the first one
is the senior director of
engineering. So maybe call on
the on the org chart there,
that is a senior executive
level position. Could you throw
that up traffic. Thank you. OK.
So when you, when you look at
the way the executive level
leadership is structured, so
Executive is my term to try and
help create distinction between
a level of supervision versus
department heads, OK? And so
you've got. Really right now
today. Two positions that have
a set of duties, but a big part
of that is direct supervision
and oversight over a number of
departments. So my position,
and you see the ones that are
in kind of that cream, pink,
pink cream color. Her
departments that I provide
leadership for, and so those
department heads report to me
for for for day to day
operations, and let me go back
one so that Go back and slide
so you see how we're, I'm sorry
So My position and then the
position currently filled by
Shane Davis for about another
week, director of economic
urban development, and so we
both provide executive level
leadership over some number of
departments, and they're kind
of functionally aligned. You
all did, so we were both grade
24s. That is the top grade
within the city salary schedule
You also have certain key
positions that That ought to
report directly to the mayor,
but don't have oversight over
the other departments, uh, but
Provide functions that are
great at the same level, so the
city attorney leading the legal
department, our CFO leading the
finance department in the city
clerk, the municipal judges are
also at that same grade, and
your, your contract uh with
them specifies the steps they
go to and things and so the
municipal judges are at that
same grade, but they're,
they're hiring process is
different than everybody else.
OK. So What the proposal that
You approved at the, at the
earlier. Ordinance that sets
the new salary or the new the
new org structure is this, and
so the city administrator
position is unaffected by that,
but the director of Eom and
urban development was split
into two, and so now you have
two executive positions with
oversight over some departments
So the director of urban
development was already a grade
24, remains a grade 24, and the
senior director of engineering
has attended to be at the same
level organizationally and so
the ordinance that's on the
floor now, which sets the
grades, sets the senior
director of. Engineering at
grade 24. I'll tell you that
position supervisors positions
that are at grade 23, and so
you know it's natural to have a
supervisor, be it one at least
one grade above the folks that
they're supervising, so the
senior director of engineering
in this ordinance would set
that grade at grade 24. The
second one on there is the city
engineer that is an existing
position. Really what you're
doing here is just codifying
that existing position it is
already a grade 24 or grade 23,
I'm sorry, it's a grade 23, and
this ordinance retains it as a
grade 23. The third one is what
codifies the position of
director of Community
Development. It is already a
grade 22, and this ordinance
retains it as a grade 22. The
4th 1 is external relations
officer being retitled to
external relations and
industrial recruitment officer,
that action's happened, but it
classifies the grade at grade
22. That the position that you
have retitled and set the new
duties to. So the prior
position the external affairs
officer was a grade 2, and so
this new position is upgraded
to a grade 22. And those are
the positions addressed in this
ordinance because those are the
ones that need to be addressed
in the budget related to the
earlier action. Now I believe
there was an earlier question
related to what are the ranges
associated with those grades.
I'm happy to, to, to go through
those, and I'm sorry I grabbed
the wrong. OK, and the numbers
I'm gonna share here are the
updated, so this reflects the
2% cola that you've, that
you've just added. So this is
the numbers as they will be
when they take effect here in a
few weeks. And just like any
other physician, the salary
schedule for these positions
for these grades is 1 through
25 in terms of steps, so that's
the range I'm going to give you
step 1 through step 25, and
when the mayor brings his
appointment, he specifies the
steps, so it generally will
fall somewhere in between this,
but starting at the, the lower,
the lower grade that's on here
is a grade 22. Uh, that salary
range is 99,777. This is
obviously the annual number. Up
to 169, 395. And I'm happy to
give you all a copy of the
salary schedule. This is I'd
like that when you. Uh, for
grade 23, step one is at 114,
774. And it goes up to step 25
at 194771. In grade 24 ranges
from 1131, 996. Up to 224016.
Do you have any other questions
Mister Meredith? No, but I'd
like to offer an amendment. To
On the external affairs and
industrial recruitment
recruitment. Office or officer
downgraded from a 22 to a 21,
grade 22 to a grade 21. Is
there a second? 2nd 2nd for Ms.
Watkins. Any comments or
questions. Mr. Kling. What's
the rationale? The rationale is
it's too big a jump. If you're
taking a city engineer, moving
them to senior director of
engineering. It's a one great
jump. Why is this which is a
lower grade at 20 to begin with
making a two-step. As opposed
to a one step like the city
engineer moving to the city.
Director of engineering would
make. Mayor Battle, would you
like to share your thoughts on
that? I just say it's an
expansion of the job. When you
look at the job, the job was
originally um he was working
with um working as an aide in
the office uh today it's, um,
it's working with legislative
affairs, uh, working in both
Montgomery and Washington and
working with uh the, you know,
senator and and uh
congressman's uh staff, uh, but
then also taking on the
industrial recruitment. side.
Uh, he's the one that's going
to be our face to see Boeing.
He's going to be there face to
see Mazda Toyota. He's the next
uh, Eli Lilly that comes along.
He's gonna be the one to,, be
the face to that and uh I will
say Mr. Davis has done a good
job of training him over the
last several months, but
there's still some, there's
still some learning to be done.
I mean, it won't start, start
at the top of the grade, but
it's definitely a job that is
uh. worthy of the of the grade
because of uh the
responsibilities that it's
going to be taken on. Just, you
know, as I said just this week,
$10.8 million came in and uh uh
not all, all of that person's
work, but it's it's some of it.
And so when you start putting
that kind of stuff in, Katie
Britt invited $7 million for
bridging and Ms. Martin had a
whole lot to do with that, but
also, um, our, uh, legislative
affairs person was working with
Katie Britt's people to make
sure that it came through. So I
I think that you know the uh
responsibilities are worthy of
what it is. I wouldn't, I
wouldn't count this as an old
job. I'd count this as a
totally new job because it
really is almost a new job. And
I respectfully disagree with
that, and I think that he
should be come in at a grade 21
and once he Earns his keep, so
to speak, then you could move
him up to a 22, but I think, um
You know, I tried to strike the
job to begin with. I just, I, I
don't agree with its need. I
don't agree with the need to
reorganize, period. Um, and I
certainly in this tight budget
don't see how you split. Mr.
Davis and create 2 jobs at that
price point, um, and again,
you've got city engineer who's
only gonna go up one grade.
While you have This created
position going up too, and it
just I don't agree with you.
Thank you, Mr. Meredith. Any
other comments? Uh, so there we
have an amendment on the table
to reduce the external affairs,
industrial recruitment position
from a grade 22 to a grade 21.
All in favor, please indicate
and we have a roll call vote
please. Miss Watkins, how do
you vote? No, Mr. Little, yes
voting on the amendment I'm
voting in favor of downgrading
from 22 to 21, right? Yes. No.
Mr. Kling. Mr. Meredith, yes,
cheer votes no. The amendment
does not pass. That brings us
back to the original The
original ordinance. To, um,
Regarding the the
classification and salary plan.
Are there any more comments?
All in favor please indicate.
Can we have a roll call vote?
You keep beating me to it. Mr.
Little, how do you vote? Mr.
Kling, how do you vote, Mr.
Meredith, how do you vote? Nay.
Ms. Watkins, how do you vote?
Nay chair votes aye and the
ordinance is approved. And then
the last item that we were
going to deal with in this
section is G19G is an ordinance
to exempt hearing aids from
city sales and use tax. The
chair moves for approval.
Seconded by Mr. Little, are
there any comments? I've got
amendment. We are on 19G. OK,
just wanna make sure, um. I
want to move to strike under
section 3 effective date,
duration. Be Duration that
entire sentence and insert the
duration of the foregoing
exemptions under section one
and Section 2 shall be until
September 30th, 2029. Second,
now the reason for it is when I
requested this. Out of legal.
It wasn't written the way I
wanted it written. I wanted it
written. So that it did not
expire in one year. I'm gonna
leave Mr. Riley alone and not
say why I think it was written
the way it was written, but
again, as I mentioned earlier,
given state compliance issues.
Anything we pass on the hearing
aid relief cannot take effect.
Until. September 1st, 2027,
which would only give effective
of relief. So by extending this
to the life of what the state
legislature has allowed for
gives. The 2028 year. All year
of tax relief and I understand
Mr. Kling is going to introduce
something, but again, it It
only allows for tax relief on
hearing aids. From September 1,
2027. You got a written form of
that I could look at. May, may
I interpret it? Let's let's let
Mr. Meredith finishes, OK, so
and that's why. What I offered
under the amendment earlier
under 9A to give the money to
increase the money to enable is
so that there is some benefit
to hearing aid recipients
during that portion of the year
11 months, that the state.
Through its compliance
mechanism does not allow the
city to reimburse or or I
shouldn't say reimbursed, but
um forgive the tax or not
collect the tax on hearing aids
And you got a written.
Amendment I don't need a
written amendment. I actually
talked to legal before putting
it in and, and that was part of
the reason why I made such a
fuss over this special session
being made a work session is I
was going to introduce it then,
but I wasn't able to do that.
Mr. Riley told me of the
limitations and there and that
it needed to be an ordinance
and not a budget amendment,
which is why I took the the
tack I took. Mr. Riley, you
have tried to get in. Here on
this one, this one, go for it
you may I, may I just turn the
floor over to Mr. Riley. Thank
you for trying to make that
effort, Mr. Riley Point of
order. What is your point, Mr?
Under the bylaws, council
member takes precedence over
anybody else, you're right.
You're right. OK, going back to
my original request. I'm just
trying to see if there was a
written copy of people can't
You need I have asked if I
could copy of what was being
brought in. OK. Earlier this
week or at the last meeting.
And earlier I'd asked everybody
to share their ideas, their
emotions, and I received input
from 3 council members. I asked
Mr. Meredith again today, I
mean, I'm voting on something
and I'd like to at least see
what it is that he's proposing.
Our bylaws and our Robert's
rules does not specify that I
have to do that. You don't have
to do that. You're right,
Professional courtesy does that
Mr. Mr. Riley. Now that's a
joke. You got after all, Mr.
Riley. OK, the, the reason, and
and admittedly, these are.
Funky provisions the way the
statute is written up, but the
reason that I told you it
couldn't come in is because the
statute says the exemption is
approved by the county or
municipality, the, the, uh,
ordinance must include all the
following provisions and
effective date of September 1.
And the duration of the
exemption, which must be in
fiscal year increments or in
perpetuity. Now, I didn't write
it. That's just what it says. I
that doesn't make much sense,
but, uh, that's what it is, it
is what it says, so, uh, You
could I just, I just offer you
that as the as what the statute
says. And it also, of course,
provides that we have to let
the Department of Revenue know
by July 1 for it to take effect
that won't be a problem because
You know, we got plenty of time
between now and July 1. But
that's, that's what the, the
law, the enabling law says, uh,
you know, fiscal year
increments. So Mr. Riley, if we
notify the Department of
Revenue in July 2027 that this
is going to go into effect.
Could it then Continue through
the next fiscal year. Well, it,
it would continue at that point
from if we did it in. fiscal
year increment, it would
continue from September 127 to
September 128, and I, I
actually in October 1st because
you said it has to go by
incremental fiscal year. So
September 1, 2027. That's why
I'm offering this amendment so
that it rolls over to the next
fiscal year, alright. OK. Well,
but still, it has the fiscal
year requirement whether you go
to the next one and it does
seem sort of silly and I don't
know. Who's going to complain,
but it could be the Department
of Revenue that we don't want
that. Yeah. Any other more
discussion on Mr. Meredith's,
um, I'd like to ask that it
please be restated so I can try
to understand it. I moved to
strike under Section 3
effective date. Duration be
duration. That entire sentence
and insert the duration of the
foregoing exemptions under
section 1 and Section 2 shall
be until September 30th, 2029.
Any questions Any questions Mr
Any questions Any questions Mr.
So with the start date be
fiscal year October 1 for 20.
The fiscal year, uh, this, this
would kick in on September 1st,
2027 and then run through the
29 is the limit that the uh the
state has put on how long that
exemption can last. Let me say,
I can, I can certainly inquire
and if we find out that it's a
problem, we can always move to
aid. Correct the dates and date
Um, All in favor of Mr.
Meredith's amendment. Let's do
a roll call. All in favor of Mr
Meredith's amendment. We'll
start with you, Mr. Meredith.
Hi, Mr. Kling. I Mr. Little. Hi
Ms. Watkins. Aye, chair votes
aye, and the amendment is
approved. Which brings us back
to Mr. Mr. Kling, I believe
that you had an amendment as
well. He didn't have it on this
one. He had it on. capital
improvement, didn't he? You do
not have an amendment. It comes
under capital improvements. Oh,
thank you. OK. Yeah. Oh, that's
right. We're going back to the
the then we, it was no other
amendments. All in favor,
please indicate. Aye and he
posed. The motion carries
unanimously. Could we have had
a request to take a break, and
I want to honor that request
because I think all of us need
a chance. We're going to come
back now that we've done all
that and come back to the
budget for the final
consideration on the budget
we'll take a 10 minute break
which will take us to 1040.
Yeah. Oh that's. OK. I can't
even begin to explain. get some
I just texted her. It. This. Oh
When we get back, when we get
back to the actual ordinance
that's the. OK. I. All right. I
Yeah. Don't know nothing I want
the water? Anybody need a water
? No thank you. Let's No.
Speaker. That. You don't OK,
guys That. All right. All right
all the council members are
present. We'll go ahead and
resume the meeting and call the
meeting back to order. Emotion
was made earlier to delay. A
final vote to table a the final
vote. On the budget until items
19B through G had been voted on
That has taken place and so now
we will take item 19A off the
table. And it is now back on
the table. Um are, are back on
the floor. And I believe the
intent was to do that so we
could accommodate any
amendments that were made to 19
B through G that might
potentially affect the budget.
So are there any amendments
that need to be made to the
budget to bring it in line with
the action that has been taken
previously. Yes, ma'am, I have
an amendment, Mr. Liu. And this
amendment, uh, just for the
folks in our listening
audiences to amend the budget
to line up with the pay scale
changes we made. Amend
amendment to budget ordinance.
I move to amend ordinance
number 26-830. The budget
ordinance of the city of
Huntsville for the fiscal year
beginning October 1, 2026 by
adding graph, adding paragraph
in which reads 12 of the
full-time positions listed for
the police department in
Exhibit C shall be authorized
effective July 1, 2027, and
five of the full-time positions
listed in Exhibit C for the
Fire and Rescue department.
Shall be authorized effective
July 1, 2027. 2nd, seconded by
Mr. Meredith. Any discussion on
any of this? All in favor of
the amendment, please indicate
by saying aye aye, and the
opposed. The amendment is
approved. I move to pass the.
Well, it's already on the table
that motion already out there.
Are there any other amendments?
Mr. Liu, just, OK, the hearing,
the hearing aid. Sales tax
exemption issue has been taken
care of, correct? The
authorization of the exemption
has the authorization to, if I
can clarify, yes, but it
doesn't kick in until September
1st, yes yes OK. OK. For the
sake of discussion, I
understand the dollar amount
you're talking about, but is
there Uh, Um, is there
something that's being reduced
to cover. That impact on the
budget. I realize you're
talking about one month. Well,
Is there a source of what I'm
funding is what I'm coming. No,
but I was told by legal that it
didn't need to have an offset.
It's, it's so minimal. I think
it's just a, a. Correcting
error, OK. But at this point,
it's, it's. I think, I think Mr
Hamilton wants for clarity, so
you know obviously all sales
tax, you know what we're doing
at this point is estimating
what would happen next year. So
based on, based on prior your
modeling from the finance
department, their estimate for
sales tax on hearing aid sales
in Huntsville for, for the
upcoming fiscal year for a full
fiscal year would be $150,000.
With the action that council
took tonight, the last month of
the year, there they'll be
exempt from sales tax, and so
just doing a 1/12 modeling
across that, that, that one
month, we estimate would be
$12,500 that will now not be in
that revenue number and so the
impact to the budget would be
the last month of the year at
an estimate of $12,500. And
y'all are comfortable you can,
you can handle that, so we
don't even need to get into, uh
Capital funding or anything. In
can In can in. OK. I guess that
leads me to ask the question.
Um, about reconsideration of my
amendment to up the
appropriations to enable
Madison County in order to
cover the um the time that is
not covered by what by what we
just passed. Do you understand
what I'm asking? I know you're
asking for reconsideration of
the motion regarding enable.
Were you on the prevailing side
? No, that's why I'm asking if
one of you three that was on
the prevailing side would
Father to, uh, Of that or ask
for that reconsideration. Does
anybody want to ask for that
reconsideration. I, I'm still
not clear what the
reconsideration is. The
reconsideration would be to
amend the budget ordinance to
increase the money to enable
Madison County by $150,000 so
that we can allow them to
provide relief for hearing aids
during that time period that we
as a body, the city of
Huntsville, not the body, but
we as a city of Huntsville
would be precluded from doing.
Because of state compliance
issues. OK. What do you need a
second? I'm sorry, a motion to
reconsider a motion, yeah. Well
I asked. I can't since we were
not on the prevailing side. I'm
asking one of the three that
was on the prevailing side if
they would be willing to do
that. I'm not hearing anybody
make that motion. Could we go
on then? Are there any other
amendments or or any other
discussion so that we can take
a final vote on item 19A, again
just for everybody's Memory in
1980 is the ordinance to adopt
the city of Huntsville's annual
budget for fiscal year 2027
beginning October 1, 2026. Um,
All in favor, please indicate
by saying aye aye, and he posed
The budget is approved. Mayor,
you have a budget for 2027.
Many thanks to everyone who was
involved in the process, Penny
Smith especially, for your, um,
your, your team, their work, Mr
Hamilton, everyone who worked
with us to make this happen.
Thank you all for your patience
OK, we'll go on to. OK. 19 19H
is an ordinance amending
Chapter 8 Business, Article 4
vehicle for hire, Division 2
delivery vehicles of the Code
of Ordinances of the City of
Principal, Alabama to amend the
taxi vehicle for higher rate.
They motion for Mr. Little
second from the chair. Ms, good
evening. Keisha Bryant,
director of parking and public
transit. This ordinance
amendment before you is to
increase the amount that our
taxicab companies can charge
their fares, and I was
contacted by Mr. Junior Jordan,
who has remained with us
throughout the meeting, um, to,
to do this increase. The last
time the taxi companies got an
increase was in 2022. Are there
any questions for Ms. Bryant?
All in favor please indicate
aye, any opposed. The motion
carries, uh, thank you, Ms.
Bryant. Thank you, Mr. Jordan,
for being with us. Uh, 2019, 19
is an ordinance annexing 236.58
acres of land lying on south of
Huntsel Brandre Road west of
Greenbrier Parkway. Is there
emotion motion for Mr. Little.
Second from Mr. Meredith.
Council members, uh, Thomas
Nunez, manager of planning and
zoning services. Uh, good
evening. Uh, this, this item is
located south of Huntsville
Browns Ferry and west of
Greenbrier Parkway, it is
overall 236.58 acres. I Are
there questions for Mr. Nunez?
Any questions? All in favor,
please indicate. I opposed
motion carries. Thank you,
council members. Thank you. 19J
is an ordinance declaring
certain real property a surplus
and authorizes the mayor to
enter into purchase and sale
agreement between the city of
Huntsville and Lehman Ferry LLC
The chair moves for approval.
2nd 2nd for Mr. Liu. Hey
council members Jim McGuffy
City of Huntsville Economic
Development Office. Uh, this is
a sale agreement. For 2.4 acres
Front in Lehman Ferry Road, uh,
had the property appraised, uh,
we're looking to do a mixed use
project here. It's going to be
an office phase one in a
restaurant phase 2. The total
sale price is $871,200.
Questions for Mr. McGuffy.
Discussion All in favor, please
indicate. I do oppose. The
motion carries. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. McGuffy. This
brings us, and thank you
getting us through that section
We're now coming to new
business items for
consideration or action. These
items will be approved in one
motion unless any member of the
council wishes to remove an
item for discussion. The
reading of each item will be
waived unless the council
member requests otherwise.
Chair will request holdings
item C and D, the capital
budgets, um, are there any
other items anyone wishes to
hold? Yes. I want to hold B, C,
and D as well. F J P S U V
sorry it's late, but the
business still got to be
conducted Items B, C, D. FJ P S
U V. Are there any other? No,
no, there is no. There is. V as
in Valentine. V as in victory.
Got it. And I'd like to hold a
A a Anything else? The chair
moves for approval of items 20E
20 GHI 20K. 2020R, 20T, and 20
W to Y. Is there a second?
Thank you. All in favor, please
indicate deposed. The motion
carries. We'll start with item
20A. 20A is a resolution
authorizing travel expenses. Is
there a motion? Moved to
approve motion for Mr. Little a
second from the chair. I would
2nd from Ms. Watkins. Mr.
Meredith, what was your
question? My question is, Was
is. reimbursement for the music
officer to go to Sweden, a part
of this. I'm sorry. Trying to
pull it out of my folder. Yes,
sir. It was. I'm sorry, ask the
question, um, was Were any
expenses regarding the music
officer's trip to Sweden on
here, not in this. OK. Could
you please let me know when
they come up? Yes, we will.
Thank you, we are tracking.
Appreciate it. Thank you. Any
other questions? All in favor,
please indicate. Aye. Any
opposed. Motion carries. 20B is
the resolution authorizing the
mayor to enter agreements with
the low bidders meeting
specifications as outlined in
the attached summary of bids
for acceptance. The motion to
approve motion for Mr. Little,
seconded by the chair. Uh, what
que I don't know who held this.
What questions do we have? Uh,
I just want her to tell the
public what that what it is. So
this is a periodic bid that's
utilized by various departments
um, but in general, it is, it
is a bid for drug and alcohol
testing system. It's mainly
used court, that is the
department that put this
forward, the award, um, was
through our bid process was
went to microgenics Corporation
doing business as thermo Fisher
Scientific. Any questions for
Ms. Ms. Smith. All in favor,
please indicate a opposed
motion carries. 20C is a
resolution approving City of
Huntsville 1990 capital plan
for fiscal year 2027 to 2036.
Chair moves for approval.
Second by Mr. Little. Um, Mr.
Hamilton. Is it the desire of
council to see the presentation
we did at the work session
again, or what is it? If you,
if you could just give us the
highlights. I So Councilor Rosa
before you is the 1990 Capital
Improvement plan. It covers 10
years, as is typical from FY 27
through 36, obviously we spend
most of our time kind of
focused on the near term,
looking specifically at FY 27
to the total revenue into that
fund is estimated at 55.4
million total expenditures at
101 million. We'll have a
beginning balance at 1.3
million at the end of the
current fiscal year and
anticipate ending balance in
that account at 3.3 million.
And obviously when you see that
planned expenditures are that
much more above revenues
because that includes debt, uh,
for, for some of the projects.
When you look at kind of some
of the major things this, uh,
this fund really does, I kind
of think of it in two big
buckets. There is maintenance
of our, our number of our
facilities and our streets and
things, uh, and maintenance and
replacement of our capital, so
a lot of the things that the
departments need just for
operating on a daily basis, and
then it also does construction
of our vertical structure. So
City Hall, police stations,
fire stations, recreation.
Facilities things like that. So
what you're seeing here is kind
of what I've put into a big
bucket of really kind of the,
the facility and infrastructure
sustainment account has as Mr.
Kling noted, we have
significant investment going
into all of our horizontal
infrastructure maintenance,
street resurfacing being the
biggest chunk of that, but
there's also other road
maintenance drainage and pet
infrastructure maintenance and
construction all kind of rolled
in there together. Then you see
what we're doing for fleet. Uh,
one of the things I did want to
note, you know, Fleet. is an
area that we've spent a number
of years really improving our
funding there. We're in a
pretty good place now. It would
be nice if we could fit a
little bit more, but, but it's
in a pretty good place. But one
of the things also that we're
able to do in this update. You
don't see it in 27, but
starting in 28, I was able to
add an additional line that is
specific for fire trucks and so
that kind of takes the fire
truck load off of this fleet
fleet capital. So while, while
you don't see that number go up
from last year. Uh, starting
next year, it goes up by effect
of pulling fire trucks and
funding them separately and so
I anticipate we'll be able to
start getting a lot healthier
in that regard as well, so kind
of a good news story in this,
in this fund as we continue to
move forward. Some of the, some
of the major projects, things
that are already under
construction funded by this
fund, but from prior year
dollars, uh, so you see a
number of projects that we have
ongoing right now. Some of
those are nearing completion.
Then we have some things that
are in design and so then the
construction funding for these
are things that you see in this
budget and then some other
stuff looking just a little bit
beyond that, uh, as we've
talked about a couple of times,
we're in the process of setting
a condition to be able to do
some replacement of some
existing fire stations, 5 of
those, mostly in the northern.
Part of the city and then a few
other things that are kind of
not not in this fiscal year but
but upcoming soon so I wanted
to give you a sense of some of
the things that we're working
on coming up over the next few
years. And happy to take on any
questions that you have. Any
questions or comments regarding
the 1990 plan. The fire trucks
that you were talking about,
didn't we just buy a bunch. A
couple of years ago with some
federal COVID money that we got
we, we bought a bunch and we
need a bunch more and
unfortunately fire trucks are
very expensive, so, you know,
one ladder truck is right now
in the vicinity of $2.5 million
Uh, your pumper trucks are up
north of a million now. There's
a few other kind of specialty
pieces of equipment like for
for hazmat response and heavy
rescue that also require
vehicles, so, um, you know, the
the, the things that we need to
do to make sure that we have
the right. Response out of our
fire department is very costly.
Any other questions or comments
on this? You've. I, I said this
at the work session. I'll say
it again, you have covered
every area of the city, and
addressing needs. So thank you
for that. All in favor of
approving the 1990 capital plan
Please say aye. And he opposed
the motion carries and the
capital plan is. Approved 20 is
a resolution authorizing the
city of Huntsville 2014 Capital
Improvement plan for fiscal
year 2027 to 2036 motion for Mr
Little Second from Mr. Kling
and Mr. Davis, this is your
swan song. Make it good. He's
gonna get misty. I I have to
Had to find the, the PowerPoint
presentation's been so much
talked about and so many
windows open in this laptop
here, so I apologize. Good
evening council members. Shane
Davis, director of Urban
Economic Development. So I, uh,
much like Colonel Hamilton just
did, I'll quickly go through
the capital improvement plan.
Uh, it's certainly loaded with
needs for this city. Uh, annual
recurring revenue is just under
$70 million. There's no planned
debt issue for FY 27, so you
don't see any debt revenue that
would add to that total. Again,
that, that should say FY 27.
Capital projects uh is right at
$64.3 million. Those are new
projects, annual existing debt
service within the plan is just
over $9 million for a total
expenditures of $73.7 million
the plan currently has a
beginning balance of $5.6
million. We'll have an ending
balance at the end of FY 27 of
just over $1.3 million. So as I
like to remind you and the
public each each year this plan
when it was developed in 2014
was meant to be a cash as you
go, uh, certainly we knew we'd
put that service in it to
advance a growing city, mainly
in roads and transportation
efforts, uh, but really we
wanted this plan to to adapt,
to be able to react to
opportunities in our community,
whether that's a restore roads
without diet or much like
resolute way, there's
opportunity to go get federal
funding. You need matching
dollars. We want to be able to
respond quickly to that.
Certainly economic development
I think North Huntsville Town
Center, the Target Home Depot
is an example of that. Eli
Lilly's of the world and, and
all of our industrial, uh,
recruitment has allowed this
plan to, uh, bring a lot of
good to this community, and it
was set up that way. As to see
FY 27, about 12% debt and then
the ten-year projection is a
little misleading. It shows to
be 28.7%, uh, you know, just
under 13, but that is temporary
So you passed uh TIF 9 for
downtown, so we, for all TI
districts when we create a
capital plan has to seed the
early years, so you know we
have to be. Uh, heavy loaded on
deploying those under the TIF
statute. You must have all
projects started within 5 years
uh, so a lot of times that
private equity or that property
tax revenue is lagging. Uh, so
to cover that debt service 2014
plan does that now certainly
once the TI districts get up
and running, and, and they're
producing, it's able to
reimburse those payments, so in
later years, this plan will get
revenue that is planned out for
that debt service we'll come
back into the plan, uh, once
it's, you know, those TIFF
districts are supporting their
self. So I did want to, they,
they didn't want you to think
that, that big jump in debt is
a long term. Uh, projection
This is the same type of
information but broke down by
um the major categories within
that plan, uh, so for FY 27
redevelopment efforts kind of
dominates, uh, almost at 30
million. I wanna walk you
through what that is. It's
certainly some projects going
on in the parkway. It's
certainly Mill Creek, uh, that
is, that is occurring for
affordability in our
partnership with Huntsville
Housing Authority. And be able
to do that with our, uh, Choice
Neighborhood CNI grant that we
won. Uh, roads and bridges,
that's the, the heart and soul
of this plan is still very
healthy, multimodal parking, uh
there's a, uh, some parking for
downtown, certainly the Ryan
Amphitheater to provide that
permanent solution. We knew we
would do that 4 or 5 years into
operating the Orion. Uh, our
annual debt services you see
there and then economic
development, economic
development really provides a
big lift for the general fund
both capital plans, but it
makes up a very small
percentage of the overall
expenditures within this
capital plan. And then some
cash reserves. We really want
be healthy and not be on the
what I call the red thin line,
uh, and how we operate this
plan. The 10 year, uh, project
category funding as you see, uh
certainly the Mill Creek
project is a short term project
in in overall long term capital
plan. So as you see as it
starts to balance back out it
is exactly what this plan was
intended to do for roads to
lead and dominate this plan as
you see again the annual debt
service that you see there's a
little misleading. So you see
that 29% and it almost equals
the road and bridges. That's
for a very short time, almost
about the first next 5 years
for TI 9, and this already
models the projected TFA should
you move forward with that
certainly if you do not move
forward with TIFA and Limestone
County, that red bar you see
there would be almost half that
but it would be for a very
short period. Uh, cash reserves
uh, comes in 3rd at just over
$100 million. I will tell you,
uh, that number will shrink, uh
because that's really making up
years 9 and 10 in this capital
plan what we will do is, as
we've done since 2014, we will
come in vision or the staff
will come into vision with
working with planning and
engineering and traffic
projections and they'll start
to identify new road projects
that will get put in this plan,
so that cash balance you see is
really in the out. outer years,
projects that they get
identified will actually absorb
some of those funds. But that's
what this plan's meant to do.
Our redevelopment efforts, one
of the things I think I'm most
proud of in this plan that
allowed us to do is. You know,
a lot of the news stories is
about roads and it's Eli
Lilly's, but this plan really
we focused on having a category
to go in existing neighborhoods
existing corridors, and make
sure we keep those healthy, and
that's what you see in the blue
bars there. Certainly parking
and then the economic
development piece. Just some
budget highlights, uh, that
should say 47 active uh
projects uh I, uh, couldn't
type it, it's very apparent and
putting this together for the
work session. Uh, total over
half a billion dollars, uh, I
do want you to understand and
for the public since we've
created this, uh, our city has
completed over half a billion
dollars of road projects that
there's a little over 200
million active in this
community, and with this, you
start to see in, in the future
years we'll be able to say we
have invested $1.2 billion just
in roads and transportation,
and that's what this plan was
meant to do. Uh, some of those
key projects in Northern bypass
P phase two, which would go
from Memorial Parkway to
Winchester. Chester Road, which
I really believe will really
help I-565 Memorial Parkway, uh
both mornings and evenings. It
gives you an alter route to get
to the west side of the city
and back to the east side of
the city without it being the
sole way to do that is pretty
much I-565. Uh, our governor's
drive improvements there to
help, uh, evening traffic get
over the mountain and into the
Hampton Cove community, our
Homes Avenue project from
downtown to Research Park, go
through UAH and through that
section of our city, uh, the
Eastern bypass, Winchester Road
will start next year. That's
the last piece that will finish
the full widening of Winchester
Road. Uh, from a essentially Uh
Memorial Parkway all the way up
past the Buckhorn community. A
swancot Road is still in this
plan. I know there's a pending
TIFF 8, what this Wacott Road
did was only, uh, we discussed
it in, uh, council Meredith's,
uh, town hall meeting last week
and explained it to the
citizens out there that, uh,
what this fund was allowing us
to do is a very small section
of a three lane from County
Line Road just to get started
on a, an area that's growing
very rapidly. It's try, try to
stay ahead of it. Should you
prove TF fate, these funds
would be. used to help
accelerate all the design plans
that are anticipated to fate so
we can go as fast as possible
to get all those projects
started. resolute way phase one
Uh, is in here. You, I know we
just, uh, were awarded $10.8
billion dollar grant that will
not pay for all of it. So the
way we put this in is, uh, Zach
McGovern and Cathy Martin and I
received a call about a month
ago that we were a finalist and
based on that call, we felt
pretty good. There were some
follow up things that staff
needed to get them, but we felt
like we would be awarded that
if we could deliver those
things, so, uh, knowing that
was coming, we were able to
accelerate this, so we put our.
hedge funds in to to actually
get that project delivered to
the community in the Redstone.
The Hindenberg extension down
at Hayes Farm, uh, to allow
that, uh, neighborhood to have
an alternate route other than
Memorial Parkway, uh, to get to
Grissom High School or wherever
they may be going to Redstone
Arsenal. And then old Big Cove
Road. Out in the Hampton Cove
area from Sutton Road that
actually will go, uh, all the
way down to Taylor Road. It's
very much needed, uh, so we're
in design phase there, but this
starts adding construction
funds to that and then also the
county line road relocation.
Future key projects is resolute
Way phase 2. That's the actual
flyover of the interstate
connect to Governors West and,
and additional on and off-ramps
along I-565, the East Arsenal
connectors will be, which will
actually be the first piece of
the Southern bypass long term.
Uh, the northern bypass phase 3
that'd be the last leg to take
you from Winchester Road up, uh
US Highway 72 East uh Corridor
V, which is what it's
technically called, but, uh,
layman's terms for the general
public, it's Interstate 565
extension east, so that takes,
um, I-565 where it ends as you
start of Champ Mountain, gets
it east of Shields Road. Uh,
that will be a game changer for
this community, um, and you
know our version of malfunction
junction and probably the
heaviest. lift in this
community is I-565 US 231
interchange upgrade. That will
take federal funds, but we have
funds in here to help
accelerate that project we've
already spent a couple of
million dollars to accelerate,
get those alternate alignments,
get federal highway to sign off
on those. So we are trying to
help push state and federal as
much as we can to say look
we're doing our part to help
you push that forward. And then
Interstate I-565 exit 3
upgrades, you know, we put
15,000 jobs there. Uh, we're
starting to see retail in areas
certainly rooftops in that exit
needs more capacity. Drainage
improvements, uh, Pen Hook
Creek flood mitigation
improvements Brogland Branch,
uh, you know, this, this has
always helped fund and
supplement the 1990 plan from a
general, uh, drainage
standpoint, uh, economic
development efforts certainly
Eli Lilly, uh, some, some
improvements we'll do there.
Those should come hopefully
should you approve TF 8, we'll
relieve those obligations from
this plan and put them in a TI
district. Uh, Cummings Research
Park, it is one of the
heartbeats of our economy, so
we're constantly reinvesting in
there to keep Research Park
healthy and and be attractive
to to more companies to, to
move into this area. Uh, the
BBC expansion, there'll be some
things outside the TIFF
district that we'll do some
utilities. It's a long park, uh
that's ongoing with this pretty
minor district will cover 98%
of that. Uh, Northwest
Huntsville Industrial
Development County Line Road
retail corridor as I mentioned,
Swancott Road residential and
commercial. Um, a lot of that
will be picked up in the TF 8
district should get approved
and jetplex Industrial Park
been having conversation with
Barbie Peak and my buddy who's
also a retiring. Butch Roberts
out there, um, we are looking
where to build the next
industrial park. Uh, our
industrial parks, our legacy
parks, they've served us well.
We've got a little land left in
North Huntsville Industrial
Park, but we need a new
industrial park. Chase is full,
uh, North Huntsville will
probably be full in the next 5
years. The jet plex is almost
full, uh, so really working
where's their land that we
could go create an industrial
park. We, we talk about at the
chamber a lot. And other
industrial development partners
it's greater 500 acre site or a
big site, but there's a ton of
projects they get RFPs in that
need a 25 acre 50 acre, but
they want it in a more business
type part. And the city has
built those over the years. Uh,
corridor redevelopment, you got
uh, as I mentioned, Mill Creek,
uh, Choice Neighborhood Project
along Governor's Drive, uh, the
park project, uh, from, uh, the
heart of downtown. That's under
construction. There there'll be
2 more phases of that to bid,
uh, it's funded, uh, as I
mentioned, the North Parkway
retail corridor. Uh, one is
that, uh, US 255 and Memorial
Parkway, but there's some, uh,
activity around the Hollow Road
area, and we will make sure
that we can capture that. The
downtown business district um
is always in this plan just to
keep helping grow downtown,
keep it healthy, and, and I
think you've seen the results
of that in the last 10 years.
Uh, university Drive in South
Parkway Quarters, that's part
of that redevelopment corridors
I speak of, and then Governors
Drive West. Answer any
questions this counsel might
have. Questions for Mr. Davis.
No questions, but It sure has
been a pleasure working with
you, sir. You will be missed
more than you could possibly
know. Thank you for all that
you've done to help me and
certainly the district and the
city as a whole. We're gonna
miss you. There's a hell of a
team. Well, I, I would also say
I think it's really appropriate
that your swan song is the 2014
plan because so much of the
good you have done has come
from It's not. It, it's been an
honor. I came here, said I, I
came from private industry, got
tired of traveling, said, I'll
go do a government gig for 2
years, fell in love with this
city and this staff. There's 9
departments, 9 department heads
and a bunch of employees. You
have the chamber and all of our
economic development partners.
I'm just one guy of a team of
many people. Uh, this thing,
this place is not going to miss
a beat when I walk out of here.
And you're building a house out
in the Comoin Cove officially
sometime early next year,
you're living here that you're
not going anywhere. I'm excited
I'll get to vote. How about
that? We will miss you, Shane.
Thank y'all. Listen, you can
always come back home. No, 90
days from now I may be begging
for that. I may wanna see if
you'll fill one of those vacant
positions you've created. Yeah,
there you go. Thank you again,
Shane. Uh thank you guys. Thank
you for always supporting. I've
brought some pretty radical
stuff here. I do want to close
with this. I know it's been a
long night and I've still got
an hour drive, but, uh, I was
talking to Paul Gaddis today
and he said, What is one thing
you'll remember I've been to a
lot of council meetings. I've
actually give two presentations
to a body of city council and I
said, if you're not 100%
committed, please vote no. The
first one was take over mid uh
Madison Square Mall. And save
Research Park in that corridor,
and I'll never forget I gave an
hour and a half hour hour
presentation, went through all
this modeling. And I looked at
council and I said, if you're
not 100% behind this vote no.
And I went and sat down and I
thought to myself, why in the
world did I spend an hour and a
half and then ask them to vote
no. They voted unanimous. The
mayor and this administration
can bring great ideas, but this
body's not behind it. Nothing
happens. So thank you. Amen.
Thank you, Shane. All in favor,
please indicate any opposed?
The motion carries. As always,
thank you, council members to
take a vote about Shane leaving
Um, 20th, 20 is resolution
authorizing they are to enter
an agreement between agreement
renewal between the city
council and the arts council
Inc. doing business as Arts
Huntsville for the promotion of
arts programming and public art
Move to approve motion for Mr.
Little second by the chair. Mr.
Hamilton. Good evening,
counselors. So what's before
you is renewal of our contract
with Arts Huntsville. It covers
two programs that they manage
on our behalf. So, in the
budget you just passed, you
made allocations for some grant
programs that they manage for
us. That's the first major
section of it, uh, and so what
what happens is there's two
different grant programs that
they received the funds they
manage the the. mission and the
paneling process and ultimately
the allocations out to some of
our local uh kind of grassroots
arts groups and so all that
that grant funding, they are
purely a pass to. They keep
none of that money, uh, but we,
they do have some personnel
costs and administrative costs
associated with managing the
program for, so this contracts,
uh, provides for that, so it is
both the costs associated plus
the grant funding is is in
there that they then pass on to
the to our to our various arts
groups, uh, and then the second
thing is they manage our public
AARP program for us that also
has some management costs
associated with it. So this
both allocates the
appropriation that they use
specifically for the capital
purchase of those fixed assets,
but then also the
administrative costs associated
with managing the RFP and the
competition process selection
and ultimately the installation
process and that's an asset of
the city that perpetuates and
so they do all the fixed asset
management for us along with
our finance department for all
the public art that we have
throughout the community. Any
questions for Mr. Hamilton? Mr.
Watkins? No. All in favor,
please opposed? Motion carries.
When TJ is a resolution
authorizing Mayor to enter an
agreement between the city of
Huntsville and Alabama
Department of Transportation
where installation and or
operation and or maintenance of
traffic control signals and or
roadway lighting for Alabama
Highway 255 and US Highway 231
at North Village. Is there a
motion to approve? Motion from
Mr. Little, seconded by the
chair, Ms. Martin. Yes, Kathy
Martin, director of City
engineering. So this is an
agreement with ALDOT very
similar to what we took at the
last meeting. What it allows
the city to do is install 2 new
traffic signals. went along SR
255 at the New North Village,
uh, right in between Target and
Home Depot, and a second signal
along Memorial Parkway at the
new Huntsville Hospital,
free-standing ER. So there's no
cost to the city. It's just an
agreement to allow us to
install and maintain those two
new signals. Thank you. Are
there any questions for Ms.
Martin? All in favor please
indicate any opposed. Motion
carries. 20% is a resolution
authorizing the mayor to enter
into a termination agreement
between the city of Huntsville
and municipal Corporation in
the state of Alabama and Ripple
Works Inc. The chair moves for
approval. Move to approve. I
seconded by Mr. Little. Oh, I'm
sorry, second. You're back. I'm
back. Saint David's director
Urban Economic Development. So
council members, this was a
contract that we've had for
several years now and, and it
really helped us streamline our
inspections department. So, uh,
we had Ripple Works write some
custom programming. Our, our
biggest issue was our shuttle
system that we like to call
that that did our permitting
and our inspection review and
schedule inspections for
residential and commercial,
industrial. And then how we
were able to track pass and
fail rates, uh so ripple Works
came in and, and did a great
job of building us a program
that would interface multiple
different softwares we have.
And uh and then helped us
maintain it, um, this had a
multi-year contract. Our
inspection team feels that
they've got a great handle on
it now. They can handle it on
their own. I do want to give
you some stats of uh uh uh met
with the homebuilders
Association at their, their
monthly meeting with Alan and
Brian Mandel for inspections
this week and we shared this
before we had this, our past
fail rate. On average across
all trades was 56%. pass rate.
Putting this in, it is now up
to 86% now you can say, OK, it,
it, it some of that's the
homebuilders academy of, of, of
really helping train and and
provide trades on their, their
end, but it's also allowed us
to get uniformity with our
inspection team, uh, so it was
well worth the money. I think
it was $20,000 a year, but
we're moving that in-house, so
we're terminating those extra
years. Thank you. Questions for
Mr. Davis. All in favor, please
indicate oppose the motion
carries. 20 20 yes is the
resolution authorizing the
mayor to execute a settlement
release agreement between the
city of Huntsville and Level 3
LLC. Move to approve motion for
Mr. Little, seconded by the
chair. Mr. O'Reilly, is this
something we need to go into
executive session for? Uh,
technically we probably should,
but I think I can. Explain it
simply enough. This is just
simply uh uh uh resolution of
an agreement or a disagreement
resulting over the use of our
rights of way, uh, the party,
uh, level 3, had a, uh, an
ordinance. You had passed an
ordinance back there that
allowed them to be in our
rights of way and it, uh,
expired on August 23, 2021, uh,
they were, uh, able to hold
over for a period under that
contract at the. sufferance of
the city, but they were
supposed to pay their use fee
during that course, and that
did not occur. And so there was
some discussion and after, uh,
as it states, diligent research
and good faith negotiations,
the dispute was resolved
between the parties resulting
in payment of additional
amounts as reflected on the.
The ordinance here. Any
questions? Resolution. All
those in favor please indicate
opposed. Motion carries 2U. He
has a resolution authorizing
Mayor to enter into a
memorandum of understanding
renewal forming the missed that
I wasn't. No, I'm sorry. 20
years is a resolution
authorizing the mayor to enter
into a memorandum of
understanding renewal forming
the North Alabama Drug Task
Force and between the city of
Huntsville, Alabama, the
Alabama law enforcement agency,
Madison County District
Attorney, Madison County
Sheriff, Morgan County Sheriff,
the city of Madison, Alabama,
and the Department of Justice
and Homeland Security agencies.
Move to approve Mr. Little 2
for Ms. Watkins. Chief, I just
got one question and you won't
have to go into details. This
has nothing to do with ice.
Correct. You're correct. OK,
thank you, Chief. Thank you.
Any other questions? All in
favor, please indicate any
opposed. Motion carries. 20V is
a resolution authorizing mayor
to enter into a live user
agreement between the city of
Huntsville and Prime Info Inc.
for the Huntsville Police
Department. The motion for Mr.
Little, second from the chair.
Anybody have questions for the
chief? Yes, what is this chief?
So basically what this is, is
just this is a live user
contract it provides and if you
bear with me, but you say a
command and control, so we have
a SWAT team and a K-9 team, and
depending on what the mission
is, this helped us keep up with
um, operational plan, equipment
inventory, training, we, when
the supervisors put these
things together and it and
they're fluid. They're in
different folders in different
um. Uh, spreadsheets and so
forth. This allows us to
combine everything into one and
it allows us to also use it off
our cell phone because a lot of
time when you're actually on
the mission, you don't have
access to the MDT, but you do
have access to your cell phone
because it's portable. So this
allowed us a better keep up
with the inventory, things of
that nature, so it's a one year
contract. Thank you, Chief. Any
other questions or comments?
All in favor, please indicate
opposed. The motion carries.
That includes um a business
items, item 21, new business
items for introduction. This,
uh, we have one item. This item
is for introduction only. will
be considered at the October
8th. Regular council meeting
21A is the introduction of
enormous declaring certain
equipment surplus and be sold
at public auction. We will look
forward to taking that up at
that time. That that brings us
to 2nd roster public comments.
This portion of the meeting is
reserved for persons wishing to
address the council on matters
relating to city business,
whether or not such items are
on the meeting agenda. We have
several folks who have signed
up to speak, and you may come
to the roster when um. When
called, approached the
microphone, state your name,
home address, city of residence
Each speaker may address the
council for 3 minutes. Speakers
shall refrain from entering
into a dialogue with council
members or city staff and from
making comments regarding the
good name and character. Of any
individual Bill. We will start
by hearing from Morgan Grant,
who will be followed by Joe
Winston. Is Morgan Grant here?
So. Morgan Grant is not here
and Mr. Winston left. We'll now
hear from Joe Joel Williams.
He's Joel Williams here? Joel
Williams. I need to Uh, Jordan
Gober. Jordan Gober. Attorney
Gaskin Attorney Gaskin here.
Francis Acridge. Tyler Gotney.
Mm And Mr. Ghani will be
followed by Lena Painter. OK, I
was hoping I wouldn't be first,
but uh. Um, so, you know,
obviously you name Oh, I am
Tyler, um, uh, my address is on
the sheet. It's correct. Are
your city of residence
Huntsville. Thank you very much
Um, so. Mhm Basically, uh, I, I
I attended, uh, my council
members town hall on ALPR
surveillance and uh there there
was a lot of um things that I
heard. Uh From Leadership
within the city and. Um, That
led me to believe that a lot of
people don't believe that.
Flock or ALPR technology
constitutes AI, um, but the.
Problem Is it's not like, you
know, you scan a barcode at the
grocery store and it just shows
up fundamentally. You computers
Operate on data structures.
Everything is binary and. The
binary that a computer will
receive from a camera. It
doesn't. It's not. What's
telling the computer what's in
the image it's telling the
computer how to display the
image where to put pixels on
the screen and what color to
put them. Um, And There's no
way that you can. Convert that
image data into text to be able
to know. Where it's going where
what, what it represents. The
computer doesn't know like a
human. And so we have to use
machine learning algorithms
largely what's referred to as
image. Um, recognition software
or image processing, um, and
that is using algorithms that
are. Basically in computer
science a term known as
heuristics, and we use
heuristics to. Represent Or
solve problems that we don't
have a pure way to convert into
this data. And so, you know, my
point is that You know, I'm in
opposition to FLC, and I know
the city voted down. Mr.
Meredith's resolution today,
but I don't really think this
is over. Um, And, you know,
I'll still be here. To oppose
it and several others of us
will as well. Um, I didn't know
many of the people that are
here. Um, I am an outsider, but
I'm from Florence, Alabama. Uh,
I moved in. In 2022? And uh You
know, That's I yield my time.
Thank you. We'll now hear from
Liliana. Painter who will be
followed by Doctor Angela
Somerset. Good evening council.
Mayor Battle. My name is
Liliana Painter. I'm a
Huntsville resident and my
address is correct on the sheet
Thank you. Tonight I want to
address ethics, the treatment
of city employees and the size
of this council. How someone
campaigns can show how they may
use. Public power. During this
election, I witnessed conduct
connected to the council
president's campaign, including
loitering at polling locations,
signs that appeared to violate
city ordinances and personal
attacks that went far beyond
legitimate political
disagreement. Questions have
also been raised about dog
whistle messaging, whistle
blowing, and weather city rules
are enforced equally. These
concerns should not be
dismissed as campaign drama.
They deserve documentation,
independent review, and clear
answers. I'm not asking anyone
to prejudge. I'm asking for one
ethical standard that applies
to everyone. Especially those
who hold public office. Public
servants are supposed to work
for the public, not the other
way around. Holding office does
not place anyone above scrutiny
or entitle anyone special
treatment. It creates a greater
responsibility to answer to the
people. That same standard must
be, must protect city employees
when elected officials treat
employees, residents, and
others with hostility, the
entire workforce sees what
leadership is willing to
tolerate. The cost is real.
Employees who experience
bullying or fear retaliation
are more likely to leave and
less likely to report
wrongdoing, raises matter, but
pay alone cannot fix workplace
culture. And that fails to
protect dignity. And reward
honesty or welcome
accountability. Too much power
also rests with too few people
since 20 the 2020 census.
Huntsville has added more than
18,000 residents, about 10
people every day. We now have
more than 2030, I mean, 230,000
residents, but still have only
5 city council members, just 3
votes can decide and an issue
for the entire city. Huntsville
has outgrown a five city
council. Remember a mem a a
5-member council. I'm asking
for 5 concrete changes, expand
this council, adopt an
enforceable code of conduct for
elected officials, establish an
independent process for
employees to report
mistreatment, provide real
protections against retaliation
and public report and publicly
report employee turnover and
how complaints are resolved.
Elections and accountability,
elections and accountability
does not. Huntsville deserves
leadership. That welcomes
scrutiny protects employees who
speak up, treats people with
dignity, and remembers who
government works for. Public Of
office belongs to the public.
This is public service, not
privileged service. Thank you.
Power to the Thank you, Ms.
Painter. We'll now hear from
Doctor Angela Somerset, and she
will be our last speaker. Sign
up on there. Good evening. Hi,
I'm Doctor Angela Somerset, 9
Chalkstone Street. After that
presentation. It's kind of
difficult, but anyway, my topic
this evening is basically now
you see it, now you don't, or
maybe we're playing playing
truth or dare. Right now we are
at very, very pivotal times.
The reason that the citizens
you're seeing such a backlash
is because the citizens are
seeing that there are rules
that are for us. And there is a
different set of rules for all
of you. I don't mean any harm.
Councilwoman Jenny Robinson.
But you ran on a campaign of
listening. And there is a
distinct difference between
hearing. Listening and
communicating. Miss Penny Smith
I am still waiting on who that
tenant is direct your comments
to the council, please, not I'm
talking, well, I wanted to say
to the council first of all, my
freedom of speech gives me the
right to be able to express
myself and I am not a person
who is not articulate, so I am
still waiting on an expression
or excuse me, an explanation of
exactly who that tenant is. The
other thing is none of these
citizens need anyone to speak
for them. I know that some
things may be difficult taken
out of gallbladder is difficult
but it is not impossible and it
is not that complicated. When
we have $4 million deficits and
we have money that we pop up
with money whenever we want to
for certain high executives,
yet you have police officers
now that are outstretched and
annexed to areas where they are
not only having to divide their
time between the calls for the
citizens but also for mental
health issues as well as other
things, but in order to
understand those things, maybe
you have to be in healthcare. I
don't know, maybe you just have
to care enough or to be.
Passionate or stop flipping
papers in order to be able to
pay attention. So I think that
what we need to start doing is
understanding the basic concept
as it also states in the Bible,
whatever you do to the least of
these, you also do to me. And
when Huntsville utilities
happens to come up and
especially about those data
centers, let's keep in mind
that TVA stated that that
increased rate is going to be
based on those data centers. So
when, when our uh CEO happens
to come in, we need to know
when they're asking for
increased rates. I need to know
how they're padded, what
percentage is them, what part
is TVA, which part is fuel
usage, etc. it is time for
accountability. It is time for
transparency. It is time for
adults to act like adults. It
is time for us to stop trying
to speak for each other and to
understand that as citizens we
pay your salaries, you do not
pay ours. Thank you. Thank you
Ms. Somerset. Mr. Helbling, I
have you that you spoke earlier
our bylaws permit you to speak
either on a gender related or
non- agenda. You can't sign,
you can't sign up twice. You
can't sign up twice. So did you
did you speak? Are we following
the rules now, or? I mean, I, I
I, the rule has always been I
move to adjourn. Thank you. Let
the record show that Councilman
Kling, Councilman Little, and
Council President Robinson
heard from all the people of
Huntsville, how much they
dislike the mass surveillance
system in place and decided to
internalize that and instead of
voting with Meredith's motion
to um. You know, not even
cancel the contracts but just
put it up for a vote. You know,
to, to listen to the people and
uh be be very public about our
opinions on these things, uh,
and you have just decided to
ignore us, uh, and it's
incredibly frustrating,
especially from you, Council
President Robinson, considering
that you emailed me ahead of
this meeting telling me that
the time to discuss these
things regarding ALPRs was at
contract renewal and given the
option to vote on that exact
thing decided to vote it down.
That is shameful, and you
should feel terrible for
yourselves. I will Continue to
push for the right thing, and
I'll be here when you guys
catch up. Thanks